Chapter 4
Memory transcription subject: Governor Tarva of the Venlil Republic

Governor Tarva,
Leader of the Venlil Republic

Date [standardized human time]:
July 12, 2136

If the sensor data was to be believed, the Federation warships were gunning to Venlil Prime at a blistering speed. Their hails seemed urgent, frantic even; they were resending the communication request every few seconds. I had never seen such a harried response, but it made sense.

Venlil Prime enjoyed a strategic location, nestled in the galaxy’s outer arm. It was a fair distance away from Arxur space, so it was difficult for them to execute a surprise assault. Not to mention that it was a key supply route for our troops and a launch-point for rim patrols. Losing such an outpost would be a major setback for the Federation.

As we accepted the hail, I was surprised to recognize the face on screen. It was Captain Sovlin, from the powerful Gojidi Union. He had risen to galactic fame after leading a valiant charge to break an Arxur siege on his home world. Typically, the Federation would just send the nearest available assets, but this time, they’d scrounged up someone competent.

“Governor Tarva.” The relief was plain on Sovlin's face, as he realized that we were alive. “We’re here to assist. What is the reason for your distress?”

The humans were waiting in the wings, just out of view of the camera. Sara jotted something down on her notepad; she seemed to be sketching the new alien before her. A pang of guilt stabbed at my chest, as I realized my instincts were still abuzz. Seeing them out of the corner of my eyes was making my skin crawl. The way they craned their heads to look at the screen…it was sickening.

“I see the Federation sent their finest,” I said. “The Venlil Republic expresses our sincere gratitude for your response. Unfortunately, you’ve come all this way for no reason.”

“By galactic law, that signal is only to be used for an extinction level event. You owe us an explanation. A good one,” the Gojid growled. “Did you deal with…the problem on your own?”

“There was no problem.”

Sovlin blinked several times. “I’m sorry?”

“It was a false alarm. Our sensors malfunctioned due to a software update.”

“What did you think you saw?”

“We thought a pred—um, Arxur ship jumped into orbital range.”

“And you figured out that was false because?”

“There’s nothing up there on visual, Captain. Our backup sensors didn’t detect anything either. Not to mention, we’re still alive.”

The Gojid squinted at me, and I could tell he didn’t quite buy my story. Sensor malfunctions made themselves apparent quickly, due to the lack of corroborating evidence. He knew we should’ve rejected faulty data much faster than the span of a few hours. The sharp glint in his eyes told me he intended to sniff out the truth.

“Kam. You’re awfully quiet,” the Federation officer noted. “Do you have anything to add?”

“I don’t feel like talking.” The military advisor paused. His gaze was not focused on the screen, so I figured he was studying the humans out of his periphery. “Nothing to add anyways. Tarva said it all.”

I breathed a silent sigh of relief. With the extent to which Kam despised the visitors, I half-expected him to out them at the first opportunity. Had this call taken place a few minutes earlier, I suspect he would’ve turned the humans over. But their recent behavior must have impressed their sensitivity upon him too.

Sovlin scrutinized us, suspicion marring his features. “Why didn’t you rescind the distress signal? It’s still broadcasting now.”

“I forgot,” I replied.

“You forgot?!” The captain’s voice leapt up an octave, and he flicked his claws in disgust. “You’ve got to be kidding me. Do you have any idea the systems we’ve exposed by coming here? While we’re chatting, a planet with a real fucking threat could be glassed.”

Well, at least he seemed to buy the story. The Gojid's anger was justified, in fairness. If the Arxur invaded our neighbors now, Federation forces wouldn’t be available to come to their defense.

“Sorry,” I offered meekly.

“Whatever. We’ll need to scan the subspace readings ourselves,” Sovlin said through gritted teeth. “For our logs.”

I swallowed. If the Federation took the measurements themselves, they’d find ample evidence of human activity. The realization that we were hiding predators would horrify a seasoned veteran like Sovlin. With the amount of exposure he had to the grays, he wouldn’t accept the possibility that predators could be more than animals. In all likelihood, he would assume we were acting under duress, no matter what we said. Ships would be requested to bombard Earth the second the trail was identified.

“That will not be acceptable. It’ll only waste more of your time and energy.” I straightened, and tried to make myself look confident. “There is no need for a formal survey. Is our word not enough for your report?”

“Standard protocol dictates—"

“People are freaked out enough from the false alarm. The last thing they need to see is a Federation armada, frolicking around in the atmosphere.”

“You called us, Tarva. I’m going to do my job, and then, I will leave.”

“You’ll leave now. Your ships are not welcome here. If you enter our orbit, you will be fired upon.”

Sovlin’s milky eyes glowed with hatred. “Go ahead then! Fire away. You wouldn’t dare.”

The indicators plotting out the armada’s position crept toward our homeworld, and I sighed in dismay. The last thing I wanted was to be trading missiles with our Federation allies, but we might not have a choice. It seemed that Sovlin would barge into our territory all the same, since he had the firepower to disregard our warning. He figured we’d give into simple, brutish intimidation.

I gave a few tail signals to Kam, indicating for him to detonate missiles just short of their formation. This was an irreversible step, firing upon our long-time allies. The Federation would, at best, abandon us in the fight against the Arxur. Was I damning our species to extinction? I mean, what were the chances that the humans would protect us? Hell, I still wasn’t positive they wouldn't drop the facade, the second this fleet was gone. We should be grateful if they didn’t murder us all themselves.

Captain Sovlin wrenched his claws in shock, as the computer warned him of inbound missiles. He barked at the crew to reverse course and divert power to shields. Then, he relayed orders to the rest of the fleet to fall back. I thought he’d forgotten the video call was open, until he shot a blistering glare at the camera.

“You SHOT AT US!” The Gojid stared at his weapons console, as though considering whether to return fire. “You actually shot at us. That’s an act of war.”

“That was a warning shot. We don’t want to hurt you, but we will,” I hissed.

“How can you be so ungrateful? After all that we’ve done for you,” he spat. “I’ll be recommending sanctions in my report. And the next time you call for help…we’ll let the grays eat you miserable fucks.”

The feed cut out abruptly, and I sank to the floor in relief. There would be hell to pay at the next Federation summit, but at least our mistake had been undone without bloodshed. It remained to be seen how the humans would reward our gamble; their body language betrayed little emotion. What if the astronauts were cross with us? We had plotted and nearly gone through with their execution, after all.

"They're gone." I turned to face the predators, and prayed that we made the right decision. "You're safe now."

Noah clasped his hands together. “Thank you, both of you. You didn’t have to protect us. I hope the consequences aren’t too severe…that guy sounded pissed.”

“Ha, it was worth it. Did you see the look on his face?” Kam chuckled.

Noah’s lips curved up, and a rumbling sound came from his chest. It sounded like growling, but my translator was insistent that it was laughter. The way predators conveyed emotion left a lot to be desired. My logical brain agreed with the machine, but my instincts weren’t as convinced.

Sara jabbed an elbow in her partner’s stomach. “What did they say about smiling?!”

“That hurt!” he protested. “I can’t help it. Kam made me laugh.”

The military advisor flicked his ears. “What can I say? I’m a funny guy.”

“Funny or not, Sovlin wasn’t playing. The Gojids have a lot of pull with the Federation,” I muttered. “We just burned a serious bridge.”

“Can you patch things up down the road?” Sara asked.

“After decades of groveling? Sure.” I sighed, shaking my head. “But enough of that. We need to talk.”

The female predator nodded. “What about?

“First off, do you still want to be here? We’ve been terrible hosts. I understand if you rescind your offer of friendship, after what we put you through.”

“It takes more than that to scare us off, Tarva. I’m happy we could work through our differences together.”

Sara was well-spoken, same as her partner, but I couldn’t shake the lingering doubts. If our species were to make an honest attempt at friendship, disclosure of Arxur history was a must. A secret that abhorrent couldn’t fester between us, especially when it would be the subtext of all our interactions.

When the humans learned what the Arxur had done, they would realize their own species’ untapped potential. The tales would trickle back to Terran leadership and circulate amongst the populace. What if it inspired them to take up the torch? It wasn’t too late to change their mind on harming us. How deep could a predator’s compassion run, anyways?

I drew a shaky breath. “We never answered your question, about the…first predators we encountered. I think we owe you a p-proper explanation.”

“You don’t owe us anything,” Noah said in a soft tone. “If you’re not ready, you don’t have to talk about it.”

My resolve hardened as I met the male human’s eyes. I recalled the horror in Noah’s voice, when Kam suggested they were here to kill us all. The feel of his rough thumb, wiping saline from my cheek. Those weren’t the actions of the Arxur. These were people, with intelligence and emotion.

“I want to. I want you to know everything.”

“Are you sure that’s a good idea, Tarva?” Kam asked.

“Yes, I am. I have to believe that the humans are worth the risk we’re taking.” I could feel my heart rate accelerating, despite my confident words. The mere thought of the grays conjured fear and dread. “The first predators were the Arxur. The Federation has been at war with them for centuries.”

The male human raised an eyebrow. “All of you, against them?”

“And it’s not enough,” I responded. “Noah, they’ve hunted twenty percent of all sentient species to extinction. In this galaxy, anyways.”

His predatory eyes widened. “…why?!”

“They kill for pleasure. They want us to suffer.” I reached for my tablet, and pulled up a recent video the Arxur had sent us. “See for yourself.”

Noah pried the device out of my paws, and Sara leaned in to look at the footage. It depicted a group of Arxur guards, laughing as they released farm-raised Venlil pups from their pen. The reptilians wanted to hunt their meals. To watch their prey squirm in terror. The younglings had their eyes gouged out, and if they didn’t run fast enough to amuse the guards, they were prodded with an electric rod.

As the Arxur clubbed a pup repeatedly on screen, making sure to break all of its limbs first, I watched the humans’ reactions. At first, they seemed shocked, but then…their countenance morphed into something else. Their faces contorted into a mask of pure hatred: eyes dilated, lips curled back, neck veins bulging. There was the predator that had been concealed with such care. I was suddenly more inclined to believe that a “smile” was their friendly expression.

The humans either had a sudden desire to eat us, or were livid at the treatment of our people. I hoped it was the latter.

“This is how they treat prisoners? Children at that?” Sara asked.

Children at that. She seemed to implicitly understand that made it worse.

“Prisoners? No, that’s a farm.” Kam eyed the humans warily, but his tone had lost its edge. “The hardy species become slaves, the ones that taste good become food, and everyone else gets their planets blown to smithereens.”

Noah passed the tablet back to me. I flinched at the iciness in his glare.

“Send us everything you have on the Arxur,” he said. “There’s a human concept I’m sure Earth would love to teach them.”

I stared at the angry predator. “And…what is that concept, exactly?”

A toothy smile crossed Noah’s face. “We call it ‘karma.’”

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 5
Memory transcription subject:

UN Secretary-General Elias Meier,
United Nations

Date [standardized human time]:
July 13, 2136

The 2136 climate change summit was the latest in an ongoing saga, complete with the usual finger pointing and empty promises. The United Nations had taken on a role as a central world government following the Satellite Wars of the late 21st century; Russia, China, and the United States were still rebuilding their crippled power grids in its aftermath. After realizing the extent of our dependence on technology, the world’s countries signed the Treaty of Shanghai to govern cyberwarfare. As part of the accord, the UN was given greater authority to mediate disputes, in the hopes of preventing escalation in the future.

Following several natural disasters this year, the general assembly convened to discuss solutions. Investment in fusion energy was the main item on the docket, though I doubted any parties would commit beyond fancy words.

Despite my jaded view, as UN Secretary-General, my presence was mandatory at all of these events. I was zoned out while the Canadian ambassador spoke, nodding and smiling every now and then to keep up appearances. An aide tapped me on the shoulder, startling me out of my trance.

«Sir,» she whispered. «I need you to come with me.»

What was so important that it couldn’t wait an hour? My staff were instructed to only approach in an emergency. There was the brief moment of worry, as I wondered whether there was a credible threat to my life. My security detail seemed relaxed though, so that likely was not the case.

I followed her into a briefing room, where several serious-looking individuals were waiting. The amount of military personnel present made me think that some conflict had erupted. The strange thing was that representatives of various space agencies were present, including ESA, NASA, and CNSA. The gears started to turn in my head. The first extrasolar mission had departed a few weeks ago, but they weren’t supposed to return for months. Something must have gone wrong.

I settled down at the head of the mahogany table. «Quite the crowd we’ve got here. Could someone please fill me in?»

«The Odyssey crew made contact with extraterrestrials.» A short-haired woman in a leather jacket passed me a folder. Her nametag read Dr. Kuemper, SETI. «They call themselves the Venlil. According to our new friends, there are hundreds of other intelligent species out there. We’re not alone, Mr. Secretary. This is the biggest news of all time.»

I leafed through the dossier, taking a moment to process the news. The first page was a grainy image of the astronauts, standing with a group of Venlil. The aliens were bipedal, like us, but that was where the similarities ended. They had woolly gray fur, side-facing eyes, and spindly legs that bent inward. I wasn’t even sure if they had noses.

Any information released to the public needed to be handled with the utmost care. Science fiction had gotten people used to the idea of aliens, but the revelation of hundreds of species at once? That would shatter any notion of humanity being special. Some people would be frightened, and we needed to make sure they looked to us for the answers. The last thing we needed was for conspiracy theorists and UFO-hunters to take control of the discussion. The situation could devolve into a panic fast.

Not to mention how delicate communication with the aliens would be. Their culture was entirely new; we could offend them without even realizing. It was no small task ahead of us: learning their language, establishing diplomatic relations, and monitoring potential threats. It would be the work of an entire generation.

«I count at least forty generals in this room, which seems unnecessary,» I said at last. «Are the aliens friendly?»

Dr. Kuemper frowned. «It’s not so simple, I’m afraid.»

«What do you mean? That shouldn’t be a hard question.» I had been expecting a ‘yes’, not a noncommittal reply. My heart sank as her implication hit me. «Either they’re friendly or they’re hostile.»

«The aliens are friendly, except for one species. That species is at war with the rest of the galaxy, and they’re quite the formidable foe. They wiped out 62 worlds, and fighting them has cost billions of lives.»

«They destroyed 62 planets…by themselves?! Jesus Christ. Please, tell me you’re kidding.»

«I wish, sir. There’s a full brief on the page labeled ‘Arxur’ in your file. There’s also footage of them committing every war crime in the book. I mean, they literally eat children.»

«Shit. Let’s face it: we’re barely spacefaring. We need to hammer out alliances with the other aliens, pronto. I want every diplomat relegated to this project.»

«Well, that’s the thing.» Dr. Kuemper gave me an apologetic smile, as though she was about to give more bad news. How could this get any worse? «The Federation is afraid of us. The Venlil governor thinks they wouldn’t want our friendship, even with her blessing. In fact, she says they might attack us on sight.»

«Why exactly?» I asked.

«Humans are predators, and the only other intelligent predator…»

«Let me guess. The Arxur,» I sighed.

The SETI researcher nodded. With a heavy heart, I leaned back in my chair. Humans could be petty and violent, but even on our worst days, we didn’t eat children. You could at least give us that.

A bitter smirk played at my lips. «So I’m hearing not to invite the Venlil to the family barbecue. Yes, Doctor?»

Dr. Kuemper stifled a laugh. «And not to make that comment to them either, sir. I doubt they’d be amused. The poor furballs thought we were there to kill them.»

«But we won them over, didn’t we? Are you certain we can’t bring the Federation around too? I don’t like the odds, us taking on a technologically superior species alone.»

«I’m positive. Tarva was quite emphatic. Our astronauts say her primary concern was for the safety of Earth, as a whole. She believes there could be some…drastic overreactions. After what they’ve been through, I can’t say I blame them.»

In that case, humanity shouldn’t expect a welcome party from our neighbors. It was a shame our evolutionary link with the Arxur precluded that possibility, or even the prospect of civil relations. The fact that first contact hadn’t ended in violence was miraculous, by the sound of it. Things could have fallen apart without the astronauts ever realizing why. We’d know only that the aliens attacked a research vessel without cause; this would be a very different briefing.

I made a mental note to give Governor Tarva a proper thanks, for staying her hand and filling us in. While I didn’t want to rule out swaying the aliens, gambling with Earth’s security was out of the question. Mankind were on our own against a genocidal scourge.

«Well then. This is the rare occasion I’m open to suggestion from the peanut gallery.» My eyes locked with the American and Chinese generals, who appeared to be discussing something. «Do you have a proposal?»

General Zhao cleared his throat. «It’s not all bad news. From what we’ve seen, the Federation’s tactics and weaponry are subpar. We should spend a few months building a proper fleet and running joint exercises. I think if we catch the Arxur by surprise, we might stand a chance.»

«I agree.» General Jones offered a supportive nod, and I raised an eyebrow at her. This might be the first time I’d seen the US and China work together since the war. «Once we’re ready, UN forces can coordinate an offensive. We’ve found several potential targets, including planets where sentients are bred as food.»

«A ground assault is the perfect way to test our forces, without showing our hand. We don’t want to overcommit,» General Zhao added. «If we can liberate some Federation citizens and bring them home, it might buy us some good will.»

«We all agree that these Arxur are a menace, but I must ask. Should we really get involved at all?» I paused, choosing my next words carefully. «So far, they’ve left us alone. By launching an attack, we’ll be announcing our presence to those monsters. We drag Earth into a galactic war and risk untold human lives. Do we chance becoming dead world #63 for a bunch of aliens who hate us?»

«In my opinion, they’ll come for us eventually. We either fight them now or we fight them later,» General Jones replied. «The difference is, if we choose later, we won’t have anyone to stand with us. The Federation is not faring well.»

I grimaced. The Arxur’s sadism was bound to awaken unsavory sentiments, when it was plastered across the airwaves. How were we going to prevent widespread hysteria? My original plan was to break this discovery to the masses gradually, but with such a serious crisis, people deserved fair warning. After all, humanity’s existence hinged on the decisions that were made today. I hoped the public could handle the truth.

«If we’re going to do this, we need unity at home. People need to know what they’re signing up for.» I pressed a hand to my temple, trying to suppress a growing headache. «Release everything to the public, and let them make the decision. If there’s broad support for a war, then we’ll fight the bastards.»

Perhaps the revelation of aliens would make us set aside our differences, and face this threat as a united species. As far as I knew, Earth only had one chance to get this right.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 14
Memory transcription subject: Governor Tarva of the Venlil Republic

Governor Tarva,
Venlil Republic

Date [standardized human time]:
September 1, 2136

My visit to the research outpost was intended to last half a day. At my request, Cheln, my diplomatic advisor, had crafted a speech to show our solidarity with the UN. The whole afternoon was a joint ceremony in remembrance of the humans who sacrificed their lives in our defense.

At the end of it, I would send off the predators who partook in our first civilian encounter. The volunteers of "Doctors Without Borders" and "The Red Cross" would board the initial outbound ship, with their Venlil partners in tow. It was time for humans to receive a proper integration into our society, and that meant moving planetside.

That was a less concerning prospect than it would've been before our experiments. There were zero reports of human-on-Venlil violence during the past 10 days. Most of the complaints against the Terrans involved the predators trying to stroke our curly fur, which I found bewildering. That wasn't behavior I saw them exhibit with each other, so it couldn't be written off as a social custom. Perhaps a display of possessiveness?

But overall, the trial of our species living together was a pleasant success; more so than any scientists predicted. The predators had an uncanny ability to bond with anything, and that allowed them to forge close connections within days. My mind defaulted to thinking of Noah and Sara as part of my in-group, at this point. I never could've imagined, when this all started, that I would look forward to seeing them as I did now.

"So they're alive. Do you think they'll have good news?" Sara asked.

The ceremony had come to an abrupt halt, when General Kam informed the UN delegation of a pressing development. A Federation shuttle barged into Venlil territory, and raised a series of alarms. Its pilot claimed to be the missing patrolman Slanek. He kept repeating that his human companion needed medical attention, in a hysterical voice.

I would've kept it on the down low until we knew more, but Secretary-General Meier wanted everyone aware of the situation. He believed that if the change of plans wasn't explained, rumors would spread that the Arxur were attacking.

The UN leader's presence was unexpected. We had never met in person, or spoken beyond video messages. But it seemed when Ambassador Noah told him of my plans, he wished to attend the memorial firsthand.

Many humans flocked to the docking port as the news dispersed; everyone on the station was eager to welcome the arrivals. The crowd numbered several hundred, once Venlil were added to the count. Terran paramedics were on stand-by, and the media were swarming to report any developments.

I knew why the predators wanted to see the state of the captives. They were trying to decide if the Federation was an enemy. In the wake of my shocking admission, they wanted to know if co-existence was even possible. This was a good sign, if the Federation military were civilized enough to hear a predator out, and set it free.

"I'm hopeful, guys." I swished my tail reassuringly. "If the Federation let your 'Marcel' fellow go, maybe I was wrong. Maybe they can see you for the sensitive and wonderful species you really are."

"I greenlit the plan for a pre-emptive strike days ago." Meier's voice was slow and gravelly, flowing with a practiced cadence. "The generals suggested that we needed to hit the key Gojid launchpoints. I have no way of recalling our bombers, even if I want to."

"Damn it all!" Noah cursed. "I knew we were too hasty. The Federation will see this as an unprovoked attack. We're going to ruin all chances of peace."

I patted the Ambassador on the shoulder, hoping to quell his emotions. His brown eyes softened, and he gave me an appreciative nod. There was no sense in lamenting what was already set in stone. All we could do now was address the consequences together.

Proximity alarms shrieked, as our sensors detected an unknown vessel within bombing range. The UN generals switched them off, then granted permission for the inbound ship to dock. A few Terran soldiers lingered near their officers with assault rifles, in case of a trap. Their paranoia and suspicion had soared to new heights, since they learned the galaxy wanted to kill them.

I didn't have the heart to tell them that such deception was a predator's tactic. Playing at empathy would never be the Federation's modus operandi.

The exterior airlock creaked open, and a Federation shuttle descended from the inky backdrop. It followed the station's landing beacon to glide through the opening, and mounted its footings into the docking port with surgical precision. The craft wasn't big enough to fit more than four individuals, and that was if they stacked on top of each other. The soldiers relaxed, satisfied that an ambush force was ruled out.

It only took a few seconds for the port to repressurize, but I could sense the humans' restlessness. Anxious murmurs cycled through the crowd. Waiting, on the cusp of certainty, fueled the darker side of their imagination. The partition between the reception area and the dock receded, once the sensors determined it was safe.

A silver-gray Venlil poked his head from the spacecraft, which drew a few cheers from our people. A bandage wound its way around his ears, tying down the lone black tuft of hair on his forehead. The wrappings were soaked through with rich, orange fluid. That fresh bleeding suggested he needed medical attention himself.

The human paramedics exchanged looks, as there was no sign of their man. They shouldered their way past the Venlil. I could only see their backs, but they seemed to stiffen as they laid eyes on the interior. What had they seen that we had not? How severe were the human's injuries?

The predators toted a stretcher inside, and summoned a gurney to wait by the ship. Loud calls thundered above the chatter to clear a path. That meant Marcel was alive, but I had to wonder why he couldn't walk out under his own power. It also raised the question of how he incurred such a condition in the first place.

Sara pressed a hand to her mouth. "My God. What have they done?"

"I…I am more grateful to you than ever, Tarva," Noah breathed, shaken to the core. "I should've never questioned your decision. I see now what you saved us from."

Similar cries erupted from the onlookers, as the paramedics emerged with the captured human. Marcel's malnourishment was apparent at first glance. His skin hugged his bones tightly, and his stomach was a flat depression beneath his ribcage. I wasn't sure if it was the starvation, or the vicious injuries, that caused his breathing to sound so strained.

The poor guy's face was mashed to a pulp, bruised and bloodied. Whoever beat the human seemed to take particular offense to his binocular eyes. The way the sockets were turning black made my stomach flip. A metal band was fitted to his neck, and the skin beneath was marred with minor burns. Why was that choker still on him? Nobody had taken it off?

The Venlil almost seemed more incensed than the humans. The thought of the Federation doing that to their buddy sparked a… predatory rage. My own blood boiled at such a grave injustice. Noah was right; that would've been him if I allowed it. I was wavering on whether I wanted the humans to show mercy to my old friends after all.

"Stop filming this," I hissed at our media personnel. "Show some respect."

Meier crossed his arms. "No, film it. On the condition that you'll show it everywhere. I want everyone to see this. To document how the Federation treated one of ours. When we declare war on these bastards, I don't want anyone saying it's for no reason."

"Whoa, hold up. If they realized their mistake, and let him go…" Noah whispered. "Maybe they're sorry, and wish to make amends?"

"They didn't realize anything!" Slanek's horizontal pupils snapped toward us, as he overheard the Ambassador's comment. "The captain was going to kill Marcel, and they're still planning to bomb Earth."

"What stopped them from killing him? Did you talk them down?" I asked, in a soft voice.

"I tried, Governor. But they wouldn't listen! We escaped by the skin of our teeth, because of first officer Recel. He incapacitated the captain, and escorted us off the ship."

The Secretary-General frowned. "What happened to this Recel?"

"I brought him with us, sir. He's on the ship…I can't get him to come out. This isn't, er, exactly what I promised him."

My ears swiveled toward the shuttle. I thought I could detect the sound of terrified whines, amidst the commotion. Meier looked like he wanted to retrieve the first officer himself, and was about to start in that direction. Though the gray-haired human didn't exude hostility, I feared he might escalate Recel's emotions to a blinding panic.

"Let me handle this," I said to the humans. "Noah, Sara, you remember how hard it was for us…and there were only two of you."

Meier glanced at the astronauts, and fell back as their nods affirmed my words. I ducked into the spacecraft to look around.

Huddled beneath the pilot's chair was a Kolshian male, with a dark blanket over his head. It was a pitiful attempt at camouflage; it would be amusing, at a brighter time. The movement of the fabric, and the outline of his form were obvious giveaways. I imagine the human paramedics noticed Recel, but were too preoccupied with Marcel to coax him out.

Within closer range, the whines sounded more like muffled screams. I clicked my claws on the floor, so Recel would know the approaching person wasn't a human. The officer peeked out from under his tarp. His bulbous, orange eyes lit up with recognition.

"Governor Tarva!" Recel exclaimed. "You're…alive?"

"Of course I'm alive. What made you think I wasn't?!"

"It's just, er, nobody has actually seen you in months. And this station is infested with predators; I saw them through the window. Lurking, waiting."

"It's not infested, and they have good reason to 'lurk.' They were curious and worried, and now, they're rather upset. Hell, I'm upset too."

"Oh, please help me, Tarva. This is a nightmare, and I've done it to myself. I just want to wake up, you know? Get me out of here! Please."

"Calm down. Everything is alright now. Tell me, what is it that the humans are doing that's bothering you?"

"Slanek said there were 'just a couple', damn it. Two or three, I could tolerate but…looking at all those predators? Pure agony. It feels like my chest is on fire. I don't know how you bear it."

"I know exactly how you feel. It will pass."

"You can't know that."

"But I do. How about I introduce you to my first human friend? Just one of them."

"Just one. Just one, one!" Recel whined, rocking back and forth. "Okay. Just one."

The Kolshian was clearly on the brink of a nervous breakdown, but I decided to move forward with that tepid affirmation. This guy defied a superior officer, and sacrificed his career to save a human. That wasn't a risk that someone took without good reason.

There had to be some part of Recel that already accepted the predators' true nature. It was a matter of getting through to him, of bringing his logical mind back into the equation. Whether it was reason or empathy that struck home, it didn't make a difference.

"NOAH! Come here," I called.

The male astronaut hurried in, rushing to my side. "Is everything alright? What's going on, Tarva?"

"Hm. The first time I saw Noah, I thought he was feral. Can you imagine answering that hail?" I waved a paw in the human's direction, and Recel shuddered. "All of his teeth were showing, and those murderous eyes were like something out of a nightmare. He looked like the meanest, nastiest creature in the universe."

The Ambassador sighed. "Ah Governor, you always flatter me."

"Shush! I'm getting to the important part," I huffed. "But anyhow, the humans' words were about peace. There was such a disparity between that appearance and the things they said. My brain couldn't reconcile it."

"I'm just saying, Tarva, you could fake the occasional compliment." Noah shot me a coy smile. I had been around the predators too long if I could differentiate snarls, hadn't I? "Talk about my winning personality? My exquisite physique? Pretend you liked me?"

"I do like you! Stop fishing! At any rate…there was this collection of little things the humans did that made me think 'maybe.' The odd doubt. But looking at them dredged up all my worst memories, so I shut out that voice. I wanted them gone."

"Then why did you stop Sovlin from g-getting rid of them? What happened?" Recel stammered.

"I teared up just a little, and the first thing Noah did was try to comfort me. I realized that I never gave him a chance. No unfeeling creature would pick up on emotional nuances like they do. That's when I knew. When did it click for you?"

"It…he…the instant Slanek showed signs of distress, Marcel tried to protect him. It was something he said, that he only cared for the Venlil's safety." The Kolshian's eyes became distant, as though he was reliving the moment. "Even when the captain had a gun against his head, the predator was trying to soothe his friend. And I believed him, if just for a moment."

"You sensed it then, Recel. You know that nobody could fake it that perfectly."

"I know. But, I feel…"

"Forget about the feel. You're going to walk out of here with me and Noah. We'll find you a room, and I want you to rest up."

"And then?"

"Then, we're going to determine who is responsible for what happened to Marcel. The humans will decide what to do about it. It's your decision, but I'd like you to speak to them. You represent the Federation, as far as we're concerned."

Noah nodded. "As would I. We don't have to be enemies."

Recel rose on unstable legs and dusted himself off. Those first steps into the open were tentative and frightful; he coiled his tail around mine for support.

Venturing out through the sea of humans, many of whom were openly staring, must have been a daunting task. But he managed to hold back the scream which I sensed building in his chest. The officer lowered his gaze to the floor, and marched ahead through the chemical fever.

Perhaps this man was a spark of hope that not everyone would write humanity off on sight. I prayed that Earth could find other friends in the galaxy; and that our newfound ally would find the courage to prove that it was a possibility.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 15
Memory transcription subject:

Slanek,
Venlil Space Corps

Date [standardized human time]:
September 3, 2136

Nursing the human back to health became my obsession. The doctors were optimistic that Marcel would make a full recovery, but I was determined not to vacate his side. There was no way I was leaving his well-being to chance, ever again.

My claws tightened around the fork, stabbing into a block of tofu. The spongy protein folded into the prongs, and I brought it up toward the human's mouth. My gaze lingered on the pointy canines beside his incisors, which looked perfect for tearing flesh.

It felt unnatural, placing my paw so near to a predator's teeth, while offering it food. A pins and needles sensation danced at the base of my toes, which I promptly ignored.

"Slanek, I can do this myself," Marcel protested.

The predator was lounging in a hospital bed, propped up against some pillows. After a fresh shave and some washing up, my human looked more like his old self. A nose splint concealed the deformed appendage, and stitches mended the gashes on his cheek. Fluids and medication were distributed intravenously, which brought life back into his complexion.

I glared at him. "But I'm not going to let you. And that's that."

Marcel rolled his eyes, but allowed me to insert the protein between his lips. I scrutinized him as he chewed. It was wonderful to see him eating real food after his long hunger, but I didn't want to lose sight of the big picture.

Human medicine was primitive compared to ours, a school of medievalism. My vigilance was the only hope at preventing complications. All I knew was that Marcel's diet was essential to his recovery; it was my intention for him to consume every calorie the medical staff gave us.

I prepared a forkful of greens, which looked scrumptious and herby, and shoved it at him. The red-haired primate sighed. He tugged the plate from my stubborn paws, and set it on the bedside table.

"You gotta stop babying me. I'm fine, buddy, really." The human began to sit up, and grimaced as pain scorched across his ribs. "See? Good as new."

Tears welled in my eyes. "No, you're not!"

"I'm on the mend. This is the new normal, and that's okay. I'm tougher than you think I am."

"You're very strong, and resilient, and brave...but..."

"What?"

"I almost lost you, Marc. And it scares me how much that hurts."

"Aw. It's over now, Slanek. I'm never going to let anyone hurt us again, okay? Come here."

I curled up on the bed, and placed my chin on the predator's thigh. Marcel reached out with his nimble fingers. The same hesitancy that always flashed on his face, when he was worried about spooking me, surfaced. His hand hovered over the back of my neck for several seconds, and my heartrate skyrocketed. What was he doing?

My instincts despised the location of his paw, and the way his nails were aimed at my head. It was a slash away from my throat. Everything about that body language mirrored a predator about to pounce; no amount of trust could alter those ominous cues. My eyes blinked shut, and I summoned all of my willpower to remain still.

I felt a light touch on my ear. The human palmed the right one gently, then moved to the other. The breath I didn't realize I had been holding in escaped.

Marcel beamed when he saw me relax, and took that as encouragement to continue. His fingers darted beneath my chin, and ruffled the fur by my throat. The human's claws nicked my skin; they were rather dull, for a predator's offensive weapons. Oddly enough, it was more gratifying than painful.

A happy mewl emanated from my chest. I nuzzled against his side, and flipped onto my back.

"You're so cute!" he whispered.

Without thinking, I had exposed the most soft and vulnerable organ; my stomach. Marcel tickled my belly with vigor, which was quite the overwhelming sensation. I was embarrassed by my undignified squeals and laughs, but my control was slipping. I rolled around in delirium, thrashing and kicking.

The human had to catch me when I almost tumbled off the bed. He winced from the abdominal strain, but refused to drop me. Affection and warmth shined in his eyes.

"Am I interrupting something?" Sara stood in the doorway, amusement on her face. She stared at me, the blankets on the floor, then back at me.

"Actually, you were, but not what you think," Marcel chuckled. "What can I do for you?"

"You look better. We're all happy to see it," she replied. "But I just wanted a quick word with Slanek. Alone."

I tilted my head at the scientist, confused. Had the humans decided to blame me for my inability to prevent Marcel's injuries? Did they think he would be better off with someone stronger, and more competent at their civic duties? I couldn't fault them if that were the case.

My human released his grip, and gave me an encouraging wave. A paralyzing reluctance made me slow to follow Sara, so I dragged my feet to a secluded spot in the hallway. A mature individual would accept the consequences of their own failure; especially when that failure landed their best friend in critical condition, a whisker away from death. I can't let him go, though.

I slumped my shoulders. "Look, Sara... I am so sorry for what happened to Marc. My best friend was terrorized by a madman, and I was nothing more than a liability. I take full responsibility for everything, and accept whatever the UN has decided. If there is anything that I can do to make it right—"

"Slow down." The scientist raised a pale hand. "Nobody blames you, least of all Marcel. I think having you around is helping him immensely."

"You do?"

"It's obvious. He's trying to hide it, but I figure he's in a lot of pain."

"That's what I was worried about. So then, um, what is it you needed to speak to me about? Oh stars, is there bad news about Marc?"

"Perhaps. It's not clear yet. If I remember correctly, he was frightened of torture by aliens before this, yeah?" Sara waited for my nod. She seemed concerned about how to phrase her next words. "I think you need to be warned about how humans react to trauma. Our brains often have... difficulty processing it."

I studied her expression closely. "What are you trying to say? Is Marcel going to go insane?"

"That's not a polite word, Slanek. Everyone reacts differently. Marcel could be fine...and I hope he is," she said. "But after what he's been through, you must be prepared for drastic changes in mood and personality. He could become depressed, forgetful, irritable, or even hostile."

"Hostile?"

"Nightmares and flashbacks are common in these cases. That can incite all sorts of negative reactions."

My eyes widened in surprise. It had never occurred to me that humans relived their worst experiences as vividly as we did. When I imagined how their brains worked, I always assumed it was different. No wonder Marcel was in a prolonged fog, after watching the Arxur torture clips on the first day.

Why would a predator have such an overblown fear response, and cling to memories of prior threats? They were on the other side of that equation in nature. Even if humans descended from prey animals, they hadn't been that for millions of years.

I guess it proves humans are just people, like us. That their emotions resemble ours.

"You didn't say negative. You said hostile," I pointed out.

Sara shuffled on her feet. "Well, the memories trigger our 'fight-or-flight' response. Some people lash out with physical violence, though they don't mean to. I think that unlikely here, but it needs to be stated as a possibility."

My breath hitched in my throat, though I tried not to show my fright to the scientist. Physical violence? Being assaulted by a predator wasn't exactly on my bucket list. If a human lunged at me, without warning, I doubted I could keep my composure. It would be tough to brush that off.

The thought of Marcel, with his meaty hands clenched around my windpipe, stirred all of my subconscious fears. But I knew that wasn't him. My human hadn't tried to eat me, even when he was starving. This 'mindless killer' preserved my welfare, to his own detriment, and never displayed anything but kindness toward me.

As long as it was unintentional, I decided I could forgive him for spontaneous violence. Sara deemed it improbable, so in all likelihood, it wouldn't happen. The prospect of mental torture, that would drive Marcel to violate his principles, was more concerning to me.

"Why are you telling me this?" I questioned.

Maybe Sara thinks I wasn't being supportive enough. Or she'll teach me which signs to watch for. Human mannerisms are as alien as alien gets.

"I don't want you to fault Marcel, or to think it's proof that humans are evil. I know how frightened you Venlil are of us. If any of those symptoms would be too much to deal with, it may be best that we find you a more suitable partner."

My ears flattened against my head. Is that what the Terran scientific community believed we thought of them? That we saw them as interchangeable demons, and volunteered just to vindicate that conclusion?

That's right. We risked our lives, waiting for them to slip up, so we could say 'Gotcha!' I thought sarcastically.

There was nobody in the galaxy: human, Venlil, or otherwise, more suitable than Marcel. Being around him was pleasant and easy. I wasn't going to discard him the second a challenge presented itself.

"You want me to leave him, because he might be ill?" I hissed. "I don't want another 'partner.' I want Marcel, and I'll deal with whatever happens."

"No, no, we don't want you to leave. That's the opposite of what we want." Sara took a step back, trying to appear non-threatening. "But your feelings and well-being are important too, Slanek. You must not discount yourself, out of some sense of guilt or obligation."

"Obligation?! I love him! Did you consider Marcel's feelings at all? To even suggest that I should abandon him, right when he needs me the most...it's cruel! Heartless!"

"We are thinking of Marcel. Listen, he is in a fragile state right now. You are the main thing reminding him he is human. That someone cares for him. What would hurt him the most is to hear you call him a monster."

A furious growl rumbled in my throat. "I would never! Short of him eating my family in front of me, anyway. I hate that anyone would suggest otherwise."

"Then I'll leave you be." Sara's voice was measured, but there was pleasure in her eyes at my response. "If you need anything, you know where to find me."

I flicked my ears in acknowledgement, and scampered back toward my human's chamber without hesitation. After the mention of being pried away from Marcel, all I wanted was to have him back in my sight. What if he had an episode while I was gone? Once he was in my periphery, I could rest assured that he was okay.

Marcel had cleaned his plate during my absence, and was seated on the edge of the bed. His predatory eyes were staring into space, unblinking. There was the hint of a twitch by his lip, as if he were biting his cheek.

The human jumped a little when I leapt onto the mattress. I coiled my tail around his wrist, and noted how he slowly unclenched his fist.

"Slanek," he sighed. "I missed you."

Before, I had attributed his aloof moments to the primitive narcotics in the IVs. But in light of Sara's words, it was apparent that a different culprit was to blame. I felt ashamed of myself, for not picking up on the cues sooner. My preoccupation with his physical injuries caused me to overlook the obvious.

"What were you thinking about? Just now?" I blurted.

The human forced a smile. "You don't want to know."

"I do. You can tell me anything, Marc."

"Not this."

"Try me."

His gaze darkened. "I'm thinking I want to kill Sovlin."

"Get in line."

"I'm quite serious. I was fantasizing about it. Does that make me a bad person? A 'bloodthirsty' predator?"

"I'd shed no tears over his death. It's not fair that he got away scot-free. You're a good person, who is trying to process something terrible...and yes, has more aggressive instincts. You didn't deserve any of what he did to you."

"Thanks, buddy."

"You don't have to thank me. I should've asked about your mental health sooner. How do those memories make you feel? Are you able to talk about it?"

"I don't know. When Sovlin was about to shoot me, I felt...relief that it was over. Profound relief. I was ready for him to pull the trigger. I was only sorry that you had to see it. And that Zarn was kidnapping you because of me."

"Don't worry about me. All that matters to me is that you're here, and you recover."

"That's why I need you to let me push myself, Slanek. I heard we're going to war with the Gojids...and I want to join. Even if it's just to fly a ship or run logistics, I need to be cleared for action."

"But you're safer here. Why would you want to risk your life again, so soon?"

"To go after Sovlin, to deal with my anger, all of it. I have to do something, and I didn't know how to tell you. It's being idle that drives me mad."

"Fine. When are we leaving?"

The human blinked. "We?"

"I'm coming with you, if I have to stow away in your duffel bag. You can't get rid of me that easily."

Moisture glistened in Marcel's hazel eyes, and a low chuckle rumbled from his vocal cords. A silent vow formed in my mind, that I would protect him better this time around. Even if it meant shipping off to an active warzone, surrounded by trained predators with guns.

Something told me that I wouldn't be the only Venlil tagging along for the humans' war efforts. Though there was no formal declaration from the governor yet, I think we had chosen a side.

The fates of our species were intertwined, for better or for worse.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 17
Memory transcription subject: Captain Sovlin, Federation Fleet Command

Captain Sovlin,
Federation Fleet Command

Date [standardized human time]:
September 3, 2136

Worst-case scenarios cycled through my mind, as the Gojid ships formed a defensive wall around the colony. I tried to imagine how the people on the ground felt; trapped and aware of the impending assault.

This sea of dots spanning the blue orb's circumference was all that stood between the innocent and hungry predators. Any angle that was overlooked was an opportunity for the humans to break through. We would stop any missiles from penetrating our ranks by throwing our craft in the way, if necessary.

The only way a battle with a predator ended, was with all of them dead, or all of us dead.

The primitive nature of the human craft was our primary hope. A single hit should be enough to dispatch their ships. Hell, the station's lasers might be able to chew through more than one at a time. Our weaponry was designed to tear through Arxur armor, and the Terrans' defenses were negligible.

"Sir. The ships have reappeared just out of targeting range," Jemic barked, a tremor in her voice. I hoped the weapons officer could keep her wits. "On a trajectory course for the base."

The viewport locked onto the hostiles. I watched as they veered off onto multiple headings, and altered their course to avoid any intercepting ships we launched. A laser lanced out from the station, a streak of brilliancy across the void. The shot connected with a Terran bomber, and obliterated the predator craft in a flash.

Happiness fluttered in my chest, though it was tempered by nerves. It was encouraging that we had attained the first kill of the war.

The humans, in response, spewed plasma at the approaching Gojid ships. They seemed to hope that would ward us off, like brandishing a torch to keep a beast at bay. Weapons of that caliber couldn't deal more than minor damage, but I knew they had to preserve their main payload for their target.

It occurred to me that we had simplified the task of bombing the station for the humans. The predators were flooring it toward their stated target, and in many ways, my suggestions cleared the path. There wasn't a single sign of deviation, which boggled my mind.

The asteroid base dispatched as many ships as it could, and left its own defenses barren in the process. When given the choice, our commanders prioritized civilian lives over military infrastructure.

Things can be replaced. Stations can be rebuilt, I chided myself. Lives cannot. There are children down there.

I couldn't help but wonder, for a split second, if this was a lapse in judgment on my part. Where was that predatory sadism; the one Zarn said humans used on their own world? The last thing I wanted was to cost the Gojidi Union valuable resources. It was worse if some soldiers didn't make it from their barracks. Their deaths would weigh on my conscience for years.

But there was no way a predator could override their bloodlust, particularly while engaged in warfare! It was a matter of time before the humans rounded on our position. At least a few ships had to give into temptation, even if the majority could resist.

"Shoot the bastards! Blast them out of the sky!" I roared.

Jemic sighed. "I just said they're out of range, sir. We need to move closer."

"We are NOT abandoning our position. The second the planet is vulnerable, they'll pounce."

My mind yearned to fight the humans myself, but I had to remember the stakes at hand. We were consigned to watching, as though this skirmish were some spectator sport. Zarn was cheering each time a Terran vessel went up in a fireball, which earned strange glances from the nearest crew.

The predators weaved erratic patterns to avoid termination, but their spirals and zigzags weren't fast enough. Every crackle of the laser purged one of the vermin. The station's defenses were slow to recharge, but their effectiveness was dazzling. In fairness, it seemed a love tap could take out a Terran ship; their workmanship was rather flimsy.

Gojid craft remained hot on the humans' heels, and spit our own concentrated plasma at them. There was no breathing space for our attackers. The predators rocketed up to max acceleration, and towed a tighter line toward the base. It was wonderful to see our ships chasing the humans; how the tables had turned, from the natural order. The hunter was the hunted.

"Captain, the predators are showing no interest in the colony. I don't see the harm in taking a few ships to the battlefield," Jemic pressed.

"They're just trying to lose their pursuers. If they can bait us away from the colony's defense, that's what they want."

Her spines bristled. "I hate feeling powerless."

"As do I. Zarn, why don't you make yourself useful?" I gestured toward the doctor, who was transfixed by the battle. "Establish contact with Piri, if at all possible. Make her aware of the predators' tactics, so she can relay a warning to any nearby installations."

The Takkan returned an eager tail swish, and scrambled to reopen communication lines. My gaze darted back to the viewport. I looked just in time to catch a glimpse of a Terran fighter, taking a round to the belly. The plasma compromised its hull integrity, and reduced it to a fractured heap of metal.

There was no hesitation from the Gojid chasers, to bombard the incapacitated ship with fire. Nobody would be foolish enough to leave a predator alive; they needed to be taken out of the fight with permanence. As long as such a monster was still kicking, they could have a final trick up their sleeves.

The human vessels clustered back together, and opted to deal with the gaining pursuers one at a time. They peppered the closest Gojid ship with fire, and concentrated their strikes on its drive column. The patroller's engine went up in a colossal flare; debris was flung in all directions. Our other allies were forced to drop back, to avoid getting swept up in the blast's wake.

Stars… I hate humans, I seethed. They don't quit or retreat! I curse my ancestors, for not confirming their extinction centuries ago. This is going to be a tedious and costly war, even if we win.

The predators had endured a hailstorm of fire, and pressed nearer to the base all the same. No matter how many of their brethren were reduced to scrap, they persevered. Watching the humans' fearlessness, I couldn't help but envy their natural disposition. They shrugged off losses with that callous disregard for life they were so famed for.

We felt our casualties. That was the Federation's downfall against the Arxur. It was emotion that lost us the war. Predators saw only the mission; the kill.

"Captain, we have to do something," Jemic growled.

I flicked my ears. "It's too late. They're almost within orbital range."

While the Gojid defenses could deal with the humans handily, they wouldn't win the race against time. The predators could survive just long enough; pesky monsters. Sensing that their goal was within reach, our opponents found a final burst of speed. The lead bombers dispensed their payloads, and cylindrical missiles homed in on the asteroid's surface. I braced myself for the inevitable aftermath.

The Gojid patrollers lunged forward in desperate pursuit, but they were already too late. Explosions detonated across the complex, tearing through the expansive stone buildings. Flame enveloped anything in the explosions' proximity; smoke plumes bushed up within the artificial atmosphere.

Hangar roofs caved in, and buried any ships we failed to get off the ground. The powerful laser was out of commission too, since our orbital defenses were tucked in the center of the base. Bunkers and training areas were pummeled into submission. I wondered how many servicemen were trapped beneath the rubble.

The humans followed up their first volley with another barrage. There was no pause or emotion; though I don't know why I thought there would be. The subsequent explosions ensured that nothing was standing, and reduced any likelihood of survivors.

The horror on the bridge was a choking atmosphere. Amidst my grief, I couldn't help but feel responsible for this calamity. Our local garrison could have stopped them, if there had been a few more ships at our disposal.

Why are the humans not turning toward the colony? They're alive, and I think still have some bombs. They should come to us, any minute now.

The predator ships dipped away, but were unable to shrug off their pursuers. The Terrans branched off on individual courses; they knew we couldn't chase after all of them. Some of those vile creatures would escape…wait.

I shook my head in disbelief. They can't be leaving.

"The humans did exactly what they said!" My head swiveled in the direction of the voice. It was that unruly comms analyst from earlier. "They never intended to attack any civilians."

"They just annihilated a military base, and that's your reaction?" I snarled.

"None of the evidence suggests that they wanted to. We forced their hand," the technician growled.

I glowered at the scene in the stars, considering the predators' departure. What more evidence did one need, beyond looking at their faces? Their bloodstained history was just the icing on the cake, confirming what our eyes already knew.

The humans could be faking a retreat, to lull us into a false sense of security. The bombers were still within close range of the asteroid, and it would take them awhile to escape the system. Their strategy could be to double back, after we assumed they were leaving.

That, or our considerable presence by the colony dissuaded them from heeding their impulses. These creatures were more intelligent, and slightly more self-aware than the Arxur; they must have recognized that they were outmatched. That was a sufficient explanation, wasn't it?

I forced myself to lower my hackles. "What's your name, kid?"

"Rumi."

"Rumi? I respect your drive to question everything, even common knowledge, but this isn't the right cause to fight for. If humans were a species of any merit, do you think that the Federation would've dug up some argument to spare them? In decades of study?"

"I don't know."

"Think about it; that goes to anyone agreeing with the young man here. And yes, we did force their hand. We forced the humans to concede civilian targets, because of our overwhelming force."

"How so? We're in the wrong place."

"We're in the right place. Our presence deterred the humans from attacking anything else. Everyone should be proud of themselves today. We saved twenty thousand lives."

Rumi slumped his shoulders. "If you say so."

I imagine our allies had grown as restless as my crew. Seeing that the promise of the humans raiding the colony wasn't panning out, some captains may be tempted to pursue the fleeing ships. Sensors indicated that many were gearing up their drives, and that our meticulous formation was dissolving.

Now was not the time for this. The predators were still in system; all we needed was a few minutes of patience to save the colony.

I leaned over my microphone. "Gojid vessels, hold your positions! Do not let the humans bait you into weakening our defense."

"I'm not just sitting here, dammit." A voice pierced through our encrypted military channel. "We are going to attempt search-and-rescue, and render medical assistance to anyone alive."

My eyes darted about the viewport, searching for any signs of movement. A Gojid hospital craft had crept away from our ranks, and commenced a blazing run toward the base. Its course placed it directly in the path of an escaping human. Sensors read that the Terran ship had target-locked the vessel, and their weapons were charging.

"Turn back now!" I pleaded into the comms. "You won't be rescuing anyone if you're turned to slag. I'll escort you myself when the humans are gone."

The first responders pressed forward in defiance, and diverted their central power to shields. The fleeing predator hurled a plasma round, which deflected off our ship's nose. The medical transport seemed shaken by the contact, though it refused to turn back. The distance between them and those things was narrowing.

This was lunacy! What were those Gojid doctors thinking? I admired their commitment to saving lives, but they were setting up the exact scenario I feared.

"Abort!" I shrieked into the communicator, broadcasting the message on all frequencies this time. "Gojid medical vessel, turn back at once. The predators will destroy you."

There was no reply from the Gojid first responders. They were unarmed, which meant they stood no chance in combat. Worse, the Terran ship might've heard my plea, and realized what an easy target they stumbled upon. I waited to see the doctors blasted to bits, feeling pity swell in my chest.

On the bright side, at least it would drill some sense into Rumi, and whoever else was swayed by him. The expressions around the bridge were finally the ones I recognized from our face-offs with the Arxur.

For some inexplicable reason, the human ship hesitated. Sensors suggested that their weapons were powering down, and they were altering their course to avoid a collision. I was certain my eyes deceived me, as the primates allowed the medical ship to pass their position.

"What about that, Captain? What could they possibly gain?" Rumi hissed.

I chewed at my claws, rattled to the core. Allowing a vessel to survive, that aimed to resuscitate enemy combatants, was in direct opposition to the predators' goals. Why would those abominations exhibit mercy? That was the exact brand of illogical softness we were mocked for, by the Arxur.

But accepting any explanation that mandated emotion was out of the question. There had to be an ulterior motive at play. There just had to be! Like I told the crew, the Federation condemned humanity by unanimous vote; they wouldn't make that decision lightly. Perhaps I wasn't looking at the big picture.

The humans need the Venlil for now. They can't afford to alienate their lone ally, when they're so behind technologically, I soothed myself. Tarva must've sent someone to supervise, and so they managed to show restraint. They're biding their time.

Alarm flashed through Rumi's body language, as he saw me struggling to formulate a response. The doctor rolled his eyes in disgust, and turned to address us all.

"They wanted to preserve ammunition, when they realized the ship wasn't a threat," Zarn answered for me. "Humans are pragmatic enough to override their sadism, when it comes to their own survival."

"Quite possible." I managed to keep my voice steady. The predators were doing an excellent job messing with my head, if nothing else. "Whatever game the humans playing at, we know their true colors. We always have...and we always will."

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 21
Memory transcription subject:

Slanek, Venlil Space Corps,
First-Class Soldier

Date [standardized human time]:
September 23, 2136

Thanks to the destruction of Gojid military outposts, human forces were able to waltz through their systems without challenge. Piri recalled all vessels to protect their cradle-world, which meant the attack on Earth was postponed. With their border detection systems and complex defense network offline, their only play was to hold their core planets.

The rambunctious behavior of the humans, on the transport ride to the Gojid homeworld, struck me as odd. Their vulgarity multiplied by an exponential factor, once we were among the regular soldiers; the outpost visitors never made such explicit or demeaning comments. Even Marcel made some quips to his counterparts that came across as downright cruel, but they just laughed it off.

I was beginning to realize that these predators may have toned themselves down, so as not to exacerbate our fears.

How can they mess around at a time like this? Don’t they know what they’re walking into?

My human was ‘playing’ some ‘game’ with his new friend, Tyler, which was difficult for me to spectate. As I observed, my buddy’s on-screen avatar shot an enemy, while gunfire sound effects blared from the speakers. Marcel’s laser-focused expression became gleeful, and his counterpart cursed.

The screen shifted to a replay, which showed the bullet penetrating the avatar’s head from a side angle. The body dropped in slow motion, as though the game was glamorizing its demise. Why would the Terrans want to simulate murder and warfare, for fun? I hated seeing my friend conduct himself in a predatory manner. It was disconcerting, to say the least.

Come to think of it, the ruckus the predators were creating caused me discomfort, in general. I really wanted a hug, and for them to turn off that uncivilized game. However, I didn’t want to embarrass my Terran friend by collapsing into his grip; that would put him in an uncomfortable position. According to my recent reading, human males were taught not to display emotion in public.

Marcel grinned as Tyler called him obscenities, and my ears drooped against my head. I was hyper-aware that I was the only Venlil on this ship. I felt neglected and…alone, in this awful cage.

We’re less than an hour away from our destination, Slanek. You need to get yourself together.

I slipped away while the red-haired human was distracted, and locked myself into the lavatory. My snuffling echoed through the chamber, as full-throated sobs racked my body. Why couldn’t I just be happy that my friend was improving?

It was idiotic to think that Marcel needed me. There were too many rowdy predators here, and I was just going to get in the way. Whatever bonding had occurred between us, my species was too emotional and sensitive. I could never be one of his kind; it was more enjoyable for him to hang with his own people.

Maybe my human was bored of me, now that the alien novelty had worn off. Had I been suffocating the redhead, when I shepherded his recovery? My sentimentality must be grating on his nerves.

All we were to the Terrans was a burden. They had to be gentle with Venlil, and couldn’t be their true selves.

“Slanek.” A rapping sound emanated on the frame, and Marcel’s agitated voice trickled into my ears. Surprise tingled in my chest that he even noticed my departure. “Slanek, open the door.”

“Go away,” I growled.

Regret pulsed through my mind, instantly, but it was too late to take the words back. I didn’t want to hurt him, or push him away. What if this was what Sara meant, when she warned me not to call him a monster? I needed to let him make new friends, if that was what helped his recovery; even if it meant replacing me.

“I can’t do that.” The human tugged at the sliding door, making the frame wobble. “Don’t make me kick this down, ya big fluffer.”

I blinked away the tears, and tried to collect myself. My claws hooked on the locking mechanism, and began to unclasp it. Marcel pushed his way inside the second it opened, and knelt beside me. His hazel gaze softened when he looked at me; judging by the irritation, my eyes were red and puffy.

“Are you okay? Did I do something wrong?” he whispered.

I shook my head. “No.”

“The video games bother you? You think it’s senseless and violent. Predatory?”

“Yeah. But that’s not why I’m crying…at least, I don’t think so.”

“So you’re homesick?”

“Not really. Ah, don’t worry about it. It’s stupid.”

The human crossed his arms, and raised his eyebrows. The unwavering look he gave me stated, I’m not budging until you spill.

A tear strayed down my cheek. “You’ve been different ever since we got on this ship, Marc. I feel like you don’t want me here.”

Marcel recoiled like he’d been slapped, and stared at me in silence. My heart sank; the soldier wasn’t denying it. The human finally shook his head and chuckled, a stubborn grin clinging to his face. How could even a predator find that amusing?

A snarl tugged at my lips. “Don’t laugh at me!”

“I am going to laugh at you, when you say something that fucking dumb,” he snorted.

“How is it dumb? It’s like you’ve lost all interest in talking to me, or doing anything together.”

“Slanek, you’ve been avoiding me with a ten-foot pole. You haven’t so much as wagged your tail at me, and it’s suddenly like any contact with me repulses you. So I’ve been keeping my distance, and trying to figure out what I did.”

“Huh? Don’t you want your…‘personal space?’ I read a lot of books on human psychology to prep for this trip. They said you have an aversion to close contact. I didn’t want to pester or embarrass you in front of the other guys.”

“We have a problem with other humans in our bubble. But you? You’re fine, because you’re cute. Look, anyone that objects to me cuddling you is probably the type of person that kicks puppies for fun. So they can fuck right off.”

A chuckle trilled from my throat. All the predatory stressors compounded my emotions, and it hadn’t even occurred to me that I was the one who withdrew. Marcel was only respecting what he saw as my wishes.

I squinted at him. “You’re having more fun with the other humans, though. You look so happy…and I want you to be…”

“I’m just trying to get to know the guys. We’re going to be fighting alongside of them. I don’t want everyone to treat me like some charity case, just because I’m…” Marcel trailed off, pointing to his pink scars. “That’s all I’m known for, Slanek. I don’t want that.”

“That doesn’t define you. Anyone who thinks it does can ‘fuck right off’, to use your phrase.”

“You’re right. I’m sorry if I made you feel excluded, buddy.”

“I’m sorry too.”

“All is forgiven. So, now that we’re good…can I pick you up?”

As soon as he saw my ears flick, Marcel scooped me up in his arms. I felt joyful as he carried me to the couch, unashamed of our bond. The predator switched off the gaming console, noticing my sigh of relief; I wasn’t sure I wanted to be in his grip while he was focused on simulated death.

“C’mon man! We had one more round,” Tyler protested.

“I felt sorry for you. Mercy rule.” Marcel scratched my forehead, and the other soldier smiled at me too. Somehow, the expression looked much more ferocious on his lips than my human’s. “Besides—”

Our room was plunged into darkness, as the lights snapped out in unison. The transport lurched beneath my paws, and the long-limbed humans reached for nearby furniture to steady themselves. Gojid orbital defenses must’ve nailed us, which meant we entered their orbit.

In the dim lighting, the predators’ faces were cloaked in shadow; it bore a striking resemblance to our prehistoric beasts, lurking in the night. The only thing I could see was the faint glint of Marcel’s eyes, and the rapid movement of his arms. He draped me over his shoulder, while terror numbed my mind.

I could hardly even squirm in his firm grip; not that my body was obeying my brain’s commands. I wanted to protest, but couldn’t manage anything more than squeaks of gibberish.

Slanek, don’t pass out like you did against the Arxur. You’re supposed to be watching out for Marc, I scolded myself. Do you have to freeze, every time you’re in imminent danger? How are you going to make it in a warzone?

Another tremor pounded the transport, and the overhead ceiling creaked. The shields buzzed from the impact's dispersal, but some of the damage trickled through. This Gojid barrage meant an early departure for Terran soldiers launching to the surface; the main vessel wasn’t going to be able to get us as close as they wanted.

“I’m surprised the Gojids found us so soon,” Tyler barked. “What about the ships we sent ahead as decoys? To draw their defenses away?”

I lowered my ears. “I’m sure they predicted your predatory tactics. Ruses and deceit…that’s all you guys.”

Marcel’s fingers tightened around my stomach. “You don’t have to make it sound nefarious, Slanek. Everything we do isn’t predator this, predator that. We just want a tactical advantage.”

“Well, you’re a predator, whether you like it or not. I don’t mean it to be unkind,” I responded. “The Arxur are ambush predators too. We’ve been conditioned to expect them to use stealth, or lure us away.”

Tyler snorted. “We’re not ambush predators though. We’re persi…”

“SHUT THE FUCK UP!” I gaped as Marcel jabbed a heel into the other human’s boot, and caused Tyler’s words to break off. “Don’t you dare finish that sentence.”

“Ow, shit. I’m sorry, man. I wasn’t thinking.”

“Wait, you’re what?” I asked in a tentative voice. “Marcel, why did you stop him? You…you’re s-scaring me, roaring like that.”

My eyes had adjusted to the lighting enough to see my human gritting his teeth. I had been around the Terrans long enough to know that was no smile. It was too strained. He was terrified that immediate disclosure would freak me out.

What secret was Marcel hiding? Didn’t humans have to be ambush predators, primarily? All of our scientists were certain that was their only viable hunting strategy. They were slow, and their brains were their only advantage.

“Do you trust me, Slanek?” he whispered.

I nuzzled his shoulder. “Yes.”

Marcel turned into a hangar bay. “Do you think I’m an…abomination? Like Sovlin and Zarn did?”

“No. You know I don’t.”

“Well, I’d like to keep it that way. I’ll tell you, but not right now. Then, it can be our secret. Okay?”

“F-fine. But I’m not going to forget.”

My friend sighed, and scratched his fresh buzz-cut with frustration. I could tell from how his strides quickened that he didn’t want to convey that information at all. Something about this whole exchange unsettled me deep in my bones.

Wouldn’t any explanation of humanity’s evolution be a good thing? In their position, I would want to put as many scientific questions to rest as I could. It would help galactic leaders make an informed decision about Terran society and inclinations.

Marcel set me on the floor, and slipped a bulky harness over his shoulders. I scrutinized his body language, trying to determine why he wouldn't confide in me. If anything, not defaulting to ambush predation distanced humanity from the Arxur. What could be more heinous than stealth?

“Now, on the topic of trust,” the red-haired human began. “I’m going to strap you to my vest and sedate you. Everything will be alright, I promise.”

“What?” I scrambled backward, and collided tail-first with Tyler. “Why? You…don’t need to knock me out.”

Marcel cinched his vest straps. “You know we’re jumping out of a shuttle from the upper atmosphere. I don’t think you want to be awake for that.”

“W…you…wha…what? NO! I THOUGHT THAT WAS A JOKE!”

“We don’t joke about our crazy military shit,” Tyler chuckled.

My entire body quivered with dread, and my tail bunched up between my legs. Bile rose in my throat, a byproduct of the nausea racking my stomach. This was suicide!

Nobody in their right mind, or even the Arxur, would choose to freefall from the clouds. Tree-dwelling predators like the humans should have some fear of heights, or at least of slipping to their deaths.

Maybe that’s what kind of predators they were? Leaping from great heights onto their prey?

“You won’t remember any of it,” Marcel insisted, creeping toward me. “You’ll just go to sleep, and you’ll wake up on the ground. Leaving you here is not an option, okay?”

The Terran ship pitched to the side, as it was pounded by another enemy assault. The shields rendered a negligible difference this time, and the thunderous jolt made my molars rattle. I squeezed my eyes shut, and tried to think.

My options were to go up in flames, or to enter a drug-induced state of helplessness, as a predator dragged me toward the ground. The only image in my mind was myself as a splat of blood on the pavement.

What if the sedative wore off before our deaths, and my last moments were hurtling through purple skies at terminal velocity?

I just couldn’t do it, even for Marcel. I was going to tell the humans to leave me, and then figure out something else. As a Venlil, there was always the option for me to surrender myself. The Gojids would take me as a prisoner if I took a shuttle over there, alone…

There was a prick in my neck, and I yelped at the unexpected pain. My eyes blinked open to see Marcel stooped beside me, inserting a needle into my skin. The human already unloaded the entire syringe? With the tranquilizers flowing through my veins, I was going to be at the predators’ mercy.

A scream of horror came from my throat. “NO! PLEASE, DON'T! Marc…”

My eyelids felt impossibly heavy, and my vision shrank to a pinhole. The last thing I remembered was collapsing into the human’s arms, certain he was about to kill us both.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 23
Memory transcription subject:

Slanek,
Venlil Space Corps

Date [standardized human time]:
September 27, 2136

Waves of Gojid reinforcements arrived after the predators' initial takeover. The humans' strategic advantage was that they could be liberal when hurling artillery into enemy ranks. Our opponents were more hesitant, bearing the knowledge that civilians were trapped within city limits.

To their credit, the Gojids adapted to the novel predatory tactics quickly. To counteract the unmanned UN ships, the fresh troops carried out manual surface-to-air missile launches. That made precision strikes a more challenging affair. From what I heard, most Gojid politicians escaped to an unknown bunker location, which meant the Terrans were also thwarted on their main objective.

The humans resolved to hold their perimeter, exacting a heavy price in blood for every inch they were forced to concede. They took up guard at positions with open sight-lines, and made Gojid advances suicide. With neither side able to make progress, the situation became a stand-off. Our rivals must be steaming at their failure to reclaim any significant landmarks.

"Slanek, you need to eat something. You haven't touched your plate. We're on next watch," Tyler mumbled through a mouthful of food.

The blond human was shoveling brown crumbles down his gullet, one after the other. This person, that I knew and traveled with, was consuming meat. Real, actual flesh bits, like it was the most ordinary thing in the world. No wonder Marcel had taken Nulia away for mealtime, and told me I should eat alone.

I didn't want to be impolite when Tyler asked if I wanted company. The thought hadn't even crossed my mind, that he would indulge in such a savage feast. My appetite vanished as soon as I saw him bite into those rations. There were so many animal pieces, contaminating the entire meal. The queasiness in my stomach was swelling upward, like a thrashing wave at high tide.

He's eating the burnt skin and muscle of a dead animal. Crunching it between his fangs. Fucking hell, I cursed internally. This predator is swallowing those carcass shavings without hesitation. He's enjoying it, even.

Acid gurgled in my throat, and I spewed my stomach contents onto the ground. The human's blue eyes widened in alarm, and he rushed to my side. The flesh-eating beast patted my back, whispering soothing words. He dabbed a towel against my mouth, wiping off the vomit specks.

"It's okay, buddy," Tyler hummed. "I didn't realize you were sick."

How could this predator try to emulate normal behavior, after what he just did? All I could think was that he was a disgusting animal, and that he was probably breathing flesh particles onto my neck. It was all I could do not to kick my hindlegs into his carnivorous stomach.

I tried to spit the taste of puke out of my mouth. "I...want you to leave."

"Um, yeah, alright. Let me get Marcel first, and he can check on you."

I breathed a sigh of relief as the human exited the tent, and tried not to look at the meal remains he left behind. Most of these predators here ate meat, didn't they? It was a standard part of their diet; Marcel was the rare exception that refrained from such horrid consumption. I couldn't have the vegetarian back at my side fast enough.

My human returned with a sleeping Nulia tucked against his chest. The Gojid child had her leg fixed in a cast, and seemed to be in better spirits after a few days. Remarkably, her spines were laying flat on her back, despite being in a predator's clutches. Marcel rubbed the bristles, careless to the fact that they could extend and prickle him at any moment.

"Marc," I whined. "Please..."

His hazel eyes landed on the table. "What the fuck, man? You brought predator food around Slanek?"

Tyler glanced at his plate. "Oh...that's why he threw up? Shit, I'm sorry. Slanek, I'm real sorry, bro."

"Get the fuck out of here!" Marcel growled. "And for God's sake, take your shit-ass MRE with you."

The other human grabbed his food, and rushed away as my friend shot him a blistering glare. The redhead cupped a hand over Nulia's eyes as she stirred, so she wouldn't see what Tyler had been munching on. I don't think I was ever going to be able to look at that meat-eating predator the same. That savage display made my skin crawl.

I lowered my ears. "I'm sorry for making you yell at your friend."

"Shh, it's okay, Slanek. Let's go outside and get some fresh air," Marcel said. "You'll feel better. Then, we'll clean up that mess. Everything is going to be fine."

My mind began to settle once we wandered out beneath the starlight. The red-haired human tickled Nulia's nose, making her giggle. It was clear he took a shine to the Gojid child, despite the feelings he harbored toward Sovlin and her species as a whole. I didn't understand how his brain operated sometimes.

"If you're happy and you know it, clap your paws." The human sang in a low voice, shooting a glance toward me. The kid squealed and slapped him on the chest, which I don't think was the instruction. "If you're happy—"

Two bright orange flashes detonated on the horizon, striking the most-populated regions of the settlement. Marcel's song died out as he observed the explosions, and my own eyes widened with horror. I thought the Terrans were opposed to an orbital bombardment!

Why had these predators gone through the trouble of an invasion, just to do that? Were they lashing out because they failed to capture their desired political targets?

More bombs fell close behind, striking points across the skyline, with the undeniable intention of scoring casualties. Aircraft ripped through the sky, dispersing a trail of interceptors to avoid being shot down. They were searching for a flat stretch of land on the city outskirts. Most likely, they wanted to touch down a shuttle and dispatch ground troops.

The humans don't have aircraft like that, and they didn't land like that. Which means...

"All Terran forces, report to your extraction point. The UN fleet is engaging Arxur hostiles above-world." Terse orders carried over the radio, confirming my worst suspicions. "But, they have already attained orbital supremacy. Their intent appears to be glassing the planet."

Any sign of weakness was the Arxur's invitation to pounce. The sadistic predators must've sensed that something was off from the destruction of the Gojid border outposts. As they advanced to the core systems, the lack of resistance from patrol ships or FTL disruptors confirmed those suspicions. The Terran incursion left this system vulnerable to the true threat.

Fear coursed through my veins, and the nausea began to simmer again. Facing the grays after this miserable, irredeemable week was a dreadful thought. I felt like I was about to snap as things were.

Meanwhile, the UN soldiers in the camp grabbed their weapons. They held no such reservations about drawing reptilian blood. I suspected fighting the Arxur was the reason most humans joined the Terran reserves.

"Not good. We have to evacuate as many people as we can," my human grumbled. "But, I'm just going to get you two out of here. You're all that matters to me."

Marcel withdrew his hand as Nulia's spines bristled, but didn't seem angered by the blood spots dotting his palm. He balanced the Gojid child in his arms, and knelt to let me climb onto his back. The weight proved difficult for him to handle. The predator grunted with exertion, shuffling forward in slow steps.

The child's life comes first, obviously. We can't abandon her to a predator's whims like her mother did. Marc doesn't want to leave either of us behind, but it's too much.

I disembarked. It was uncertain whether I could run more than a few minutes, or keep up with a human's long strides. But Nulia had no hope, if left to her own devices; with her maimed leg, she couldn't walk on her own.

Marcel knelt back down. "Slanek, no. I am not going anywhere without you. Listen... I can handle this."

"Take the kid. I'll be fine," I managed.

My slender legs trotted after the departing Terran soldiers, trusting that I could follow their footsteps. Two hands grabbed me from behind, and I yelped in alarm. My head snapped around, teeth bared with the intention to bite my assailant. There was a moment of hesitation as I realized it was Tyler; the very human Marcel just chased out of my tent.

A shudder rippled down my spine. The last thing I wanted was for this flesh-eater to stick his grubby paws on me. But it seemed to be the best solution for Marcel's sake, so I decided to tolerate the unwanted contact.

My friend hesitated, seeing me squirm in discomfort. "You've got Slanek, Ty?"

"Yep. No man left behind. We all stick together," Tyler replied.

The blond predator shifted me onto his back, and he jogged off with Marcel close behind. The humans' breathing grew a bit more laborious, although I'd hardly call it panting. The predators ran for minutes without carving a dent into their stamina; there were merely a few beads of sweat on Tyler's neck. That was odd.

UN soldiers fanned out at the front of the entourage, on the lookout for threats. They were shepherding the vulnerable individuals behind them, rather than an "every man for himself" mentality. Terran medics were evacuating any wounded or captives that could stand, including their own hobbled soldiers. They had their fair share of human injuries to grapple with.

Some Gojid prisoners attempted to flee as soon as they were released. They appeared in decent shape, for having been in predatory custody. The humans made little attempt to stop them, watching them go with head shakes. The evacuation couldn't slow for fearful idiots unwilling to act in their own survival interest.

A decent percentage heeded the Terran warning about the Arxur threat, falling into the pack. Perhaps they felt indebted to the predators, since many were civilians who would be dead without human intervention. It was unsurprising to see that Marcel wasn't the only one carrying an alien child.

"MAWZY!" Nulia wailed. "Where are we going?"

"We're going somewhere safe, darling," Marcel panted, accepting the nickname. I think if I tried to call him that, his reaction would be quite different. "I need you to be brave. Think of it as a great adventure! Nothing can happen to you when you're with me, okay?"

I watched my human from my perch on Tyler's back. There was nothing adventurous about fleeing from an orbital raid. It was possible that nobody would make it off-world alive. A bomb could land atop the group right now and disintegrate us.

More Arxur craft descended through the atmosphere, eager to collect dazed survivors as slaves. Pummel the cities across the globe, fill a few transports with cattle, and then finish off the rest. This was a story I'd seen before.

"Why did so many of the Arxur shuttles get through, when ours couldn't?" I whispered, more to myself than anything.

Tyler sighed. "We...we did take control of the Gojid defenses. And we haven't learned how to use them."

My ears curled back, as an explosion rocked the city wall a kilometer away. I was relieved we had escaped the confines with such swiftness; a few minutes slower and we would be toast. The humans carved a path through the local orchards, which took up much of the land outside the settlement. Grain fields rested past rows of plump trees, and I figured Terran craft would crunch down atop the stalks.

At least we can land ships now. The sooner we're off this forsaken world, the better, I thought. I can't imagine how the Gojids feel, knowing their homeworld is all but lost. The Terrans must look friendly by comparison.

Agitated chatter spawned at the head of the pack, and the humans slowed their pace. My gaze locked onto the galaxy's apex predators, who were spread out in search of lone civilians. I had never seen one of the Arxur in person. It was merciful that we spotted them first, but they still stood between us and our presumed extraction point.

Their tough gray skin was taut and scaly, forming ridges along their spines. Their long v-shaped snouts were perfect for snapping up prey; serrated fangs jutted from their mouths, even when they were closed. Onyx eyes were dialed to slits, and tracked prey with jittery motions. Their bipedal plodding allowed them to lunge forward with unbelievable speed.

My eyes zeroed in on an Arxur soldier, tearing into an elderly Gojid's stomach. The poor guy was still alive, and his screams were audible from here. Younger specimen were being dragged away, to serve breeding purposes or toil as slaves.

"Monsters," Nulia cried. "Way scarier than Mawsle. I want to go home!"

Marcel covered her eyes. "Don't look, Nulia. We have to escape from the monsters. They...destroyed your home."

"FIX IT!" she sobbed. "Fix it now!"

"I can't. I wish I could."

The Terran soldiers leading the posse crept forward, and waved for the group to continue. The Arxur's nostrils flared as we drew within scent range. Something flashed in their eyes as they locked onto the humans. Was that...interest? Did they recognize the puny primates as predators?

UN forces opened fire on the grays, and tried to seek refuge behind the orchard trees. They were drawing the reptilians' attention to provide cover for our escape. We darted out into the open, and I prayed that the vessels circling overhead were friendlies. As if on cue, three ships with the Terran insignia alighted on the grain field.

Our human protectors were locked in a vicious firefight, at the edge of my periphery. A few of them were strewn out in lifeless positions. The time they bought us was a mere thirty seconds; we needed to be off the ground as soon as possible. The Arxur had wizened up to the diversion, and lobbed their shots at the civilian entourage.

It is times like these I wish I had the humans' narrow field of vision. I can see all of the terror and death happening around us at once.

Tyler pushed himself to his maximum speed, and dove into the open side door of a transport. I dropped to the floor and crawled toward the rear of the aircraft. The blond human asked if I was okay, repeating my name several times, but I ignored him.

My gaze was focused on the entrance, watching as several passengers climbed in. Dozens of people pushed into the craft, packing in on each other. The Gojids were eyeing any boarding predators warily, but after what they saw outside, they realized the humans had better self-control.

Wait...where was my friend? The engine revved to life, and I screamed at the pilots to stop. Oblivious to any inherent danger, I raced toward a window.

Marcel was shouldering a wounded human alongside a medic, while still clinging to the kid. Bullets sailed around him, but he refused to abandon his compatriot. He hoisted the half-conscious predator into the vehicle, then staggered onboard with the doctor.

My human collapsed on the floor, groaning. The expression on his face spoke of pain, and I hoped it was just exhaustion. I dashed to his side, and whimpered at the sight of crimson blood pooling around him.

"Mawsle, your arm is wet," Nulia said. "And sticky."

"Is it now?" he murmured. "Don't worry about it. I'm sure...sure it's fine."

There was another red mark on his thigh. My predator appeared to have been shot twice during the fray. Why did Marcel insist on playing the hero, every time the Arxur turned up?

These wounds hit non-vital areas at least, from what I knew about human anatomy. As long as the bleeding was stopped, he should survive. The spacecraft began to lift off, and I shouted for a medic.

The Terrans' efforts were undeniable, but the Gojid populace numbered a few billion. If even a hundred thousand made it off-world miraculously, it was simple math to figure the astronomical casualties. A great Federation power was down to a few colonies, and an endangered species overnight.

Perhaps most concerning, the Arxur knew there was another predator now. My eyes floated back to the window, watching the gray beasts shrink to the size of insects. I suspected tracking down the Earthlings just became their top priority.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 24
Memory transcription subject:

Governor Tarva,
Venlil Republic

Date [standardized human time]:
September 28, 2136

18 days. That is how long had passed since the minutes-long speech, and the human ambassador hadn't been outside of this room since. I tried to occupy Noah by teaching him alien games, and watching the happenings on TV. But while he never voiced his complaints, I could sense his agitation.

Chauson visited once a day, logging every aspect of Terran culture he could. The Zurulian prime minster appointed him ambassador to Earth, and the scientist was eager to squeeze everything from the opportunity. He subjected Noah to a myriad of personality tests, as well as asking him philosophical and ethical queries.

The chocolate-skinned human was happy to play along, since it distracted him from the waiting. When Chauson gave him a standard academic test in math and sciences, he was surprised to find Noah scored in the 80th percentile. That was much higher than expected, for a species that was hundreds of years behind our knowledge.

The Zurulian testified before the Federation assemblage today, sharing his novel findings. With any luck, he would be the final speaker. These discussions had dragged on far too long for my liking. At least that signaled it wasn't an easy, unanimous verdict to war with humanity.

Noah yawned, penning a final sentence in his journal. The predator had been logging his thoughts throughout this experience, but would not let me view a word. I would love to know his unfiltered opinions; his secretiveness rubbed me the wrong way.

"I'm tired, Tarva. Wake me up if the execution squad arrives," the Terran said sarcastically. "Good night."

I studied the dark circles under his eyes. "Good night, Noah. Sweet dreams."

The human tucked his notebook into a table drawer, and shuffled out of the living area. I waited for the sound of his footsteps to recede. Running water reverberated for a few seconds, before the spring of the bulky predator hitting the mattress reached my ears. My heartrate quickened, as the temptation to sift through his journal called me again.

Noah never has to know I looked. You know the aliens' fear has taken its toll on him. Ultimately, it'll help with being supportive and empathetic, right?

I took a deep breath, and counted back from 200 in my mind. Satisfied that the human was drifting off, my paws meandered over to the table. The drawer slid out without a sound, and I lifted the diary. There was nothing wrong with just a peek, surely.

I flipped open to a random page, and began reading the first entry my eyes landed on.

~Sept 17

An accidental smile sent Chauson fleeing in terror, and my heart is heavy with guilt. I'm surprised it took this long to happen. Tarva had to chase him down and explain what the expression means. The Zurulian has tried to accept me, and he shrugged off my apology. But he's afraid of us, deep down, like everyone is.

Why didn't I wear the mask? Why can't I fit in, anywhere?

When I look in the mirror, I've begun to see myself as a predator. If there is a future where humanity can be a healthy contributor to the galaxy, I don't know if I picture it anymore. We want it, but that's not enough. The simple fact of the matter is, nobody wants us.

Even the Venlil are still frightened by us. I feel like I'm walking on eggshells around them. Trying so hard not to break them, because they're fragile and innocent. Sometimes, I let my guard down, but that rarely ends well.

Tarva said straight to my face that she thought I was a nasty-looking creature. No matter how much I try to forget about it, through all the laughs and conversation, that is what she thinks of me. Any feelings of attachment are one-way, and I'd do well to remember that.

Yes, there is a shared history now, and the Venlil wish no harm upon us. But they cannot be normal around monsters. Perhaps a better man, a better species, would cut them free…and never show their face again. Instead, I'll just return to this lie, and pretend that we can make friends in the stars.

Dream on.

I recoiled, guilt rushing through my veins. These writings sounded depressed and bitter, unlike the optimist persona he projected. Was Noah's self-image that low, because of me? That comment that I made to Recel wasn't at all what I thought of him now.

Perhaps cabin fever had placed wild ideas in his head, and his outlook was cheerier before the speech. My claws tugged back through several pages, until I reached an earlier entry.

~Sept 6

Recel is a wreck from being near me, but what am I to do? Throw myself into space? The visor, the mask, none of it makes a difference. My face feels constricted already, and the nerves are making me sick to my stomach.

My indecisiveness, on what bits of humanity to include, might be the death of me: literally. The Federation will have a field day upon our arrival. I wonder if seeing me on television will be traumatic for small children? Perhaps I will be posterized as the face of the new enemy.

The questions the Venlil asked when I first arrived left me taken aback, and this will be worse. Governor Tarva is kind to help. Because of me, her species has lost every friend, and are left with a lot of primitive predators for company. Humanity disappoints on every front; the regrets must cross her mind daily. Yet she's too far committed now, so she sticks it out.

My speech feels pathetic and inadequate before I've ever given it. I don't know why it hurts so much, when I understand they're all just afraid. Predators aren't supposed to have feelings, not…

A pointed cough came from behind me. The human was standing with crossed arms, watching me with a livid glare.

"That's private, Tarva!" Noah snapped, and my ears lowered against my head. That was the first time I ever heard the ambassador raise his voice. "You can't just go through my things!"

"You were supposed to be sleeping!" I took a few steps back instinctively, flinging the book on the table. "I thought you seemed agitated. And I knew you wouldn't tell me what's wrong."

"So I tell you 'no' when you ask to read it, and you go snooping anyways?" he growled. "Well congrats, you've dug up some dirt on the predator."

"Noah…you know I'm so proud of you, don't you?" I whined, tucking my tail between my legs. "You have no idea how glad I am that we met. Your kind never disappointed me. Humanity are wonderful friends, that I am siding against the entire galaxy to protect."

"You're trying to do the right thing, Tarva. I appreciate your morality and compassion, infinitely. But let's not pretend anymore. You have to repress your instincts all the time around me, and you find my appearance loathsome."

"My initial reaction was negative, yes, but I find you quite endearing. I didn't personally request you to represent your species because I'm disgusted by you. I've done nothing but worry about your safety since we came to Aafa."

"You…you mean that? Really? You're telling me you don't still think of me as a predator."

"You're my kind and charming friend. That's what I see when I look at you. You are the predator… who convinced me to give humanity a chance. I don't think anyone else could have a personality bright enough to shine through that fear."

Couldn't Noah understand our skittishness was a part of us, just like some predatory traits were part of him? There were certain attributes that were difficult to accept, but surely humanity could see how hard we were trying.

The last thing I wanted was for Venlil instincts to have a detrimental effect on his mental health. Initiating contact should prove that there were few lingering fears in my mind.

I flung my paws around Noah's waist, and his breathing tensed up. There was brief hesitation from the ambassador; his stance emanated tiredness and frustration. The human wrapped his arms around me, after I curled my claws into his skin insistently, and relaxed into my comforting embrace.

The Terran ambassador withdrew. "Tarva, I am serious. Don't go through my personal items without permission, ever again."

"I know. Sorry," I muttered.

"Hm. It's impossible to stay angry at you." Noah shook his head with disdain. "You could get away with just about anything."

The human stretched out on the couch, closing his predatory eyes. The lines on his face eased, and I watched as his breathing slowed. My own eyelids began to feel heavy, listening to the harsh rumbling of his snores. The big guy was so gentle and sweet, so intelligent and reliable…

As I was about to drift off, the door to the diplomatic suite crashed open. Kolshian soldiers stood in the entryway; their eyes stretched wide when the predator snapped upright. Noah tried to collect himself, and raised his hands in confusion. Seeing that the guards were waving at him to come, he reached for his visor.

I glared at him, and snatched it away from his hand. I threw the metal at the wall, as hard as I could; it broke into two pieces with a satisfying crunch. Noah looked stunned, and apprehensive at the prospect of approaching the guards without it. He swallowed, then grabbed for his mask. My tiny claws scrabbled at his arm, and I shook my head in the human "no" gesture.

The Terran ambassador looked uncertain, but stood up from the couch. The wary Kolshians weren't attempting to blind him this time. A soldier barked the word "follow", and began retracing the path to the assembly hall. Heated discussions were creating a clamor inside the chamber; we could hear it from a hundred paces away.

The guards pointed at the podium, and Noah took obedient steps to the stage. Surprised exclamations rose from the crowd, as they saw the human in his uncensored form. Jerulim, the agitated Krakotl from the earlier meeting, was emitting furious squawks at those provocative eyes. I shot a blistering glare toward him.

"We apologize for the delay," Chief Nikonus began, in a cordial tone. "These are unprecedented circumstances, and we've struggled to reach any sort of decision. Has your treatment here been acceptable, Noah of the planet Earth?"

The human dipped his head. "Yes. Thank you for your hospitality, gracious Chief."

"Good. I'd never let anything like the Gojids did occur within my borders." The Kolshian palmed an indigo tentacle across his nostrils. "The Federation, as I'm sure you know from the television, has sought all sorts of counsel on this matter. We reviewed your data sharing, consulted our own records, and brought in numerous experts to testify."

"It looked like many of them had conflicting perspectives," I said.

"Indeed. Historians, xenobiologists, psychologists, zoologists, sociologists, lawyers, economists; we had them all. Several individuals who were trapped within Venlil borders testified too, and we had our own internal discussions. At last, we've tallied every vote."

The Federation could prove to the ambassador that some species did desire friendship. Any impartial observer would find humanity worthy of a chance, or at least derive reasonable doubt from their intricacies. My breath hitched in my throat, and I squeezed Noah's hand for support. The predator's palm was damp with sweat.

Nikonus cleared his throat. "Alright. The count of members who voted that humanity cannot be allowed to exist, or should be treated as a hostile party are…38."

I tilted my head. Should we be disappointed that the figure was so high, or relieved that the proportion was only a little over 10%? That was a lot of species ganging up on a single planet; plenty of threats for the predators to fend off.

"Take that, stupid human!" Jerulim chirped. "You're all going to be dead soon."

"There will be no commentary from the audience until I have finished reading the results!" the Chief spat. "65 members voted for no contact or relations with humanity, which entails total isolation of Earth."

I glanced toward the predator. There was more hurt in his eyes after that figure was read, than after hearing the ones who wished him dead. Knowing how much humans craved acceptance, they didn't want to be shunned. The rest of the options had to be more promising, didn't they?

Nikonus squinted at his notes. "74 species are undecided, with 52 specifying that they are awaiting news from the Gojid warzone."

Those are a coin flip. Some people might not take kindly to the fact that predators attacked a Federation homeworld. Then again, it will be apparent that human morality is leagues above the Arxur's.

"107 species vote in favor of a temporary truce, or working together where necessary to defeat the Arxur. Any violation of express conditions will lead to an immediate return to hostilities."

My ears perked up with hope. After cooperating against the Arxur, some Federation members might become ingratiated to humanity. It could bridge the gap to normal relations. Though I doubted we could call upon their assistance, in regards to the species maintaining contention with Earth.

"Who the fuck voted for that?!" Jerulim squawked.

"My species did, for one," the Kolshian leader replied. "Er, if that will be acceptable to the humans, of course."

Noah nodded, shuffling as if expecting to leave. "Yes, it will. We want the Arxur gone from this galaxy, and an enemy of an enemy is a friend to us. Thank you for your time, and giving us a chance."

"Wait, human. 11 members voted in favor of opening full diplomatic relations. This would involve forming trade, military, and border agreements…if you know anything of the sort. I suggest you ask Tarva for guidance, if those concepts confuse you."

The ambassador raised a hand to his mouth, no doubt hiding his bared teeth. Perhaps he was amused by Nikonus' assumption that predators would have no concept of negotiation. Primarily, I believed that Noah was moved by the fact that humanity would return with new friends. It was a tiny number, less than five percent, but it wasn't zero. That counted for something.

Overall, the results could have gone much worse. If the neutral, isolationist species were counted as in our favor, the majority of the Federation voted against humanity's extinction. Judging by the furious expressions sprinkled across the chamber, I wasn't sure every species was going to accept that.

"So many of you would side with them over us?!" Jerulim screeched. "Defend or appease humanity like they were a civilized species? Anyone who stands with predators is dead to the Krakotl."

The avian ambassador dive-bombed over the Chieftain's cubicle, and slashed his talons at the elderly Kolshian. Nikonus shielded his face with a tentacle, and nearby soldiers rushed to his aid. Jerulim flapped his wings in a frenzy, pledging that anyone who stood with humanity would share their fate. Had the Krakotl forgotten whose planet he was on?

Other ambassadors launched into shouting matches, and a few made violent gestures toward the human. I didn't want to know what the unfriendly ones were suggesting. Several individuals were trading blows, grappling right in front of the media cameras. A pair of Kolshian guards hurried us out of the chamber, before the predator could get swept up in the chaos.

Noah shared a glance with me, and I knew that tumultuous unrest stirred his own concerns. This vote could be the start of a major rift within the Federation.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 25
Memory transcription subject:

Governor Tarva,
Venlil Republic

Date [standardized human time]:
September 28, 2136

Armed Kolshians steered us into the docking area, where we landed upon our arrival. Our previous shuttle was outfitted with supplies, since the Chief granted us permission to return home on a pre-arranged route. The soldiers fell back several steps, and monitored the human for any threatening moves. One of them curled their lip at me, briefly.

Noah settled down on an empty crate, clutching a knapsack that contained his meager belongings. He met the soldiers' gaze without blinking. Staring was a contest of dominance, whether that was the intention or not. The Kolshians gripped their rifles tighter, and slunk back toward the entryway.

"You're gawked at all the time, Noah," I whispered. "Not saying it's right, but I don't suggest that smoldering stare-down as a response. It'll tickle their instincts in ways you don't want."

"I don't care how they look at me, but they're not going to look at you with disgust and hatred. If they want a problem, they can pick on someone their own size," he growled, loud enough for the guards to hear.

Aggression and protectiveness were not the persona to exhibit, on the verge of our first diplomatic encounter. The Federation representatives would see it as a predator cowing his observers. I appreciated his loyalty, but humans were a little too defensive of their friends at times. Those soldiers were entitled to their opinions.

"Thank you, but it's fine. A lot of people think I'm a disgrace to the Federation, and aren't happy that I imprisoned their people." I studied the guards' expressions, noticing how their scowls deepened at my words. "Nikonus didn't even discuss consequences for the Venlil."

"So you agree with them?! You had noble reasons for what you did. They can't find fault with that."

"Well, I've single-handedly fractured the Federation beyond repair. I guess that makes me a traitor to most folks."

"You're a hero to all of humankind, Tarva. 12 species in the galaxy who would even try to befriend us. We met what might be the only one who would try, before there was a shred of proof to our claims! Don't think we'll forget what the Venlil have risked."

I pressed a claw to my lips, and flicked my ears toward the doorway. The soldiers had snapped to attention, breaking their deadlock with the irate predator. That could only mean someone was approaching; the human needed to make a good first impression. Flattering us, at the expense of the rest of the galaxy, wasn't going to win hearts and minds.

A violet-skinned Kolshian padded into the hangar bay, clearly resisting the urge to grab his sidearm. His steps faltered once he was within pouncing distance of Noah, like a magnetic force was repelling him from the human. The familiar officer crept to my side, using me as a living shield.

How has he still not grasped that Noah doesn't have a violent bone in his body? Didn't our journey here prove that much?

The Terran ambassador grinned. "Recel! I was worried you were rotting in a cell."

The Kolshian rubbed his forehead. "I was, until the Commonwealth finalized our decision on humanity. Chief Nikonus agreed that I had a moral imperative to intervene, and pardoned me on all counts. I did receive a disciplinary mark for my methods, though."

"What do you mean?" Noah asked.

"While Nikonus agrees with my rationale...we can't have officers running around shooting their captains. I don't think I had time to go through 'proper channels', but whatever."

"I see. So you're free. Why did you come here, of all places?"

"Nikonus offered me an appointment as military liaison to Earth, and I accepted."

My eyes widened, as did the ambassador's dilated ones. I thought that Recel hated being around predators! By his own admission, living around humans was a nightmare for him, and he couldn't fathom prolonged exposure to them.

Noah stroked his chin in confusion. "You want to be around predator generals, and talk about war tactics? Don't you hate the thought of having one of us within a hundred miles?"

"Forgive me if I've caused offense, Noah. Seeing your chemistry with Tarva, I think we could be great friends." The Kolshian shuddered as he tried to meet the predator's gaze. "Others seem to adapt quicker and easier than me, but I don't want to give up. Truly."

"Do you think you can work past your fear?" I asked gently. "Have you identified what triggers such a severe reaction?"

"I enlisted on a starship when I was 9. I don't recall another way to feel toward predators. It may take an unreasonably long time for me to work past those behaviors, and it would take considerable coaxing from you all. I can't imagine what this is like from Noah's perspective; I'm not sure I'd have the patience. If you'd like a different liaison, I understand."

Sympathy flashed in the Noah's eyes. "Recel, we are willing to help you every step of the way. I just don't know why you want to endure those...feelings. It seems unfair to you."

"Humanity made me realize we are stronger than the sum of our fears. That there is something other than being afraid. I haven't got there yet, but I'm grateful for that. Can you accept my apology?"

"There's nothing to forgive. Your emotions are out of your control." The edge dissipated from the human's sonorous voice, replaced by a warm tone. "We'll figure this out together. No matter how long it takes."

"G-great. Now, there's other diplomats coming...so I'm going to m-make some preparations."

Recel skittered off to the farthest corner of the hangar bay, and began prepping a second shuttle. That was a smart idea, since it was unlikely the entire crowd would fit in a single vessel. Hell, I doubted some of them would want to ride in a tiny box with a human for days. The first officer was probably thrilled to charter his own ship, for that exact reason.

I watched the Kolshian shoot furtive glances toward us, and pondered why his species hadn't agreed to full diplomatic relations. Chief Nikonus didn't appear hostile to humanity, and displayed more fairness than I anticipated. The prospect of harm befalling Noah seemed to offend him, even. When my expectations were little more than a farcical hearing, a genuine debate was astounding.

I guess Nikonus didn't propose a full partnership, because he doesn't believe humans can reciprocate their cordiality in a meaningful way.

Nonetheless, I thought the Kolshian Commonwealth might come around as an ally. They had already seized the initiative by sending a military liaison. Even those guards were angered by my lack of accountability, rather than Noah's presence. Maybe it was just too large of a leap for most governments to make at once.

Our Zurulian ambassador, Chauson, skittered into the room. Something seemed to have been bashed against his head, and green blood trailed down his snout. The furry scientist looked unsteady on his feet, but it was a good sign that he wasn't shy of Noah in his wounded state. It violated every prey instinct, to wander up to a predator like this.

Noah squinted with concern. "Are you alright, Chauson? Please, let me take a look at that."

"What happened?" I gasped.

The Zurulian sighed. "A bunch of people rushed to leave the chamber when the fighting broke out. Someone clubbed me over the noggin; I didn't see who. Probably because I testified with a generous view on humanity. The pundits think I swayed some hostile votes to undecided."

"All that, for sharing a synopsis of human morality?!" Noah said. "I'm sorry. I never wanted you to be assaulted."

"It's fine." The scientist licked a foreleg absent-mindedly, smoothing out the brown fur. "I'll look tougher now, when I force you to take me to your planet."

"Ha! Even Tarva won't go to Earth."

"Why not? You haven't invited her?"

"Our...it's complicated, but Elias Meier, our leader, extended the invitation. Had an herbivorous banquet, live music, and a tour of New York City in the works. Tarva refused."

I swished my tail with indignation. "It's a different story after the experiments, Noah. You think I was going to wander into a city with ten million predator residents, less than a month after we met? Before anyone ever saw how you behaved in packs?"

Noah opened his mouth to respond, but snapped it shut as he saw Chief Nikonus leading a group of diplomats toward our ship. These must be the species that constituted the affirmative votes for open relations with Earth. None of them had been brave enough to make introductions yet; our Zurulian friend was the sole exception.

It didn't surprise me to see the Sivkits or the Paltans in the mix. Their centrally-located territories were far enough away that they thought they could keep humanity at arms-length, and control or minimize the interactions. Even predators wouldn't start that off the beaten path to gain a foothold. Us neighboring species were easier to invade first.

Then there were the Yotul, the latest "uplifts." Adapting to the galactic arena was difficult for a species that just discovered steam power. I couldn't imagine how the Venlil would've processed the Federation's vast knowledge in our infancy. Of course, if the Yotul's industrialism tipped us off to their presence, the Arxur might find them too. It was the lesser evil to flood them with information, and give them a fighting chance.

22 cycles after first contact, the marsupials tired of the derision from their counterparts. Most species dismissed them as primitive, with a poor scientific understanding, and little to offer as allies. The Federation military saw the Yotul as a liability, and wouldn't take their suggestions seriously. Gaining the backing of predators was a calculated risk, to coerce some respect from their peers.

So far, no surprises. The Thafki seek protection, since there's only about 12,000 members of their species left alive...well, not in captivity. The Nevoks and Fissans are trading juggernauts that don't want to go the way of the Gojids.

I squinted in apparent confusion. Was that the Mazic president among their ranks? Perhaps this was not the assemblage of friendly species, after all. It wasn't even a personal representative or aide; he was the only official dignitary I observed in the group.

Noah tensed, as he also spotted the beige-skinned mammal. I doubted my friend had forgotten who interrupted him at every turn. Cupo was rather outspoken against humanity, mocking the Terran ambassador for his eyes and criticizing simple arguments.

"Is the alien with the trunk just here to make trouble? The Mazic, you said?" the human whispered, echoing my thoughts. "Them and the Krakotl were the ones who couldn't stand my presence."

Cupo swished his trunk. "Your closing argument, about the hypothetical of friendship, was profound. We are, in fact, desperate enough that there is nothing to lose. Am I not welcome here?"

"I didn't mean for you to overhear that comment, Mazic; my apologies. If you desire diplomacy, I would not turn you away." Noah lowered his voice to its minimum, and pursed his lips in mistrust. "Damn Tarva. Those massive ears must be sharp."

I snorted. "No, your ears are just bad."

The human sighed. "That's hardly the worst thing you've said about us."

I studied the waiting crowd. While the injured Nikonus bore no intention of making the journey to Venlil space, he opted to send us off himself. There was more sharpness in his gaze than fear; he wasn't shaking or whining, the way Recel did. Though I appreciated the officer's efforts, perhaps there were better candidates to represent the Kolshians.

As for the newcomers, the Zurulian was prancing around the human in circles. Chauson couldn't contain his excitement; he was the only ally eager to get up close and personal with the flesh-eater. Meanwhile, the Sivkit diplomat looked like she was about to pass out, standing across from a predator. Logical talk of borders and distance didn't mean much when she was going to be trapped in its lair.

The Mazic president had the same suspicion in his eyes from the pivotal meeting. I don't think he trusted Noah's demeanor not to shift the second we took flight. There was a Dossur representative present, I realized, but the tiny rodent was hiding behind Cupo's bulky form. That size differential could only make the lumbering predator more daunting.

That makes my count 10 species, plus the Kolshians. Maybe the last one is running late for some reason...their representative might've had a panic attack.

"You're going to take the Yotul? I thought humans already invented the wheel," the Nevok representative sneered.

A few chuckles came from the gathering, and even the Kolshian chief struggled to maintain a neutral expression. The Yotul glowered at his critic, then fired a nervous glance toward the human. I suppose the general assumption was that predators would shun any species with weaker technology. It was tough to imagine that friendship was their end rather than the means.

If anything, I think supposed "weakness" roused the Terrans' protectiveness. Noah and Sara were most partial to us in our moments of vulnerability. Judging by how my friend's lips curved down, he wasn't pleased with the Nevok's humiliation of their peer.

"We have plenty to offer, Tossa!" the marsupial snapped. "Maybe these predators will be less stupid than you, and see that!"

Tossa flicked her ears. "Like what? Name one thing that makes you valuable...especially compared to the rest of us."

"For one thing, we're the only ones here who weren't around for that vote. You know, the one where you unanimously decided to wipe out all life on Earth. Even the Venlil have that baggage!"

Silence fell over the assemblage. Trepidation played at the representatives' expressions, as the fiery Yotul reminded them of their prior decisions. Perhaps I could afford to issue a formal apology on that matter myself, though it hadn't been my government that arrived at that conclusion. It must be tough for the predators to forget our role in their planned extinction.

"Humanity welcomes all parties, of all backgrounds!" The ambassador cleared his throat, irritation flashing in his eyes. "There's no need for divisive rhetoric, or to 'prove yourselves' by putting others down. We're a small group; we need to band together."

"He's right. There's too much at stake here. Quit acting like children," I growled.

"Gosh. On that unpleasant note... I must warn you that siding with us may put you at odds with your friends and neighbors. This is your last chance to turn back." Noah blinked in surprise, as every party lingered. That was a risk they already considered leaving the acrimonious conference. "Alright then. Let's board a shuttle, and get this show underway."

The UN would be delighted to receive a proper diplomatic envoy, but I knew I had to temper their expectations. There would be missteps along the way, and few species would act as casual as us. It took a long time to be comfortable around predators. Familiarity was the final phase of the adjustment period, which certain prey sapients might never achieve.

At least now, humanity knew where they stood with the Federation.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 27
Memory transcription subject:

Slanek,
Venlil Space Corps

Date [standardized human time]:
October 1, 2136

Our evacuation party was fortunate to skirt the orbital battle, and depart the system with a fair distance between us and the Arxur. The Terran transport unloaded its critically wounded passengers at a Venlil border outpost, while the rest of the posse trekked on to Earth. I wasn’t sure how the predators planned to deal with the terrified aliens upon arrival.

Marcel had been stabilized by onboard medics, and didn’t want to send Nulia to a refugee site run by predators without him. In fact, I got the feeling that he bore no intention of leaving her in a camp at all. Every Gojid on the vessel gawked at him yesterday, when he launched into a silly song about a twinkling star to put her to sleep.

Marcel was the reason I resisted the temptation to disembark, in the relative safety of a Venlil station. After every horror that befell him in space, I was uncertain if he’d ever return to the stars. Our separation could be permanent. The last thing I wanted was for our friendship to conclude with me showing fear and disgust toward his species.

If someone told me when I signed up for the humans’ first contact program that I would willingly go to their home world, I would’ve keeled over laughing. But I felt guilty over how my instincts ran amok on the Gojid cradle, and how quick I was to fault the predators for things they had no role in. Was my trust in humanity really that conditional? Were my prejudices still alive?

The mere sight of Marcel in the doorway had me in shambles, at our first meeting. Now, I don’t think about it when he snarls or picks me up. I don’t react to any humans’ eyes either, not even strangers or crowds. Maybe I’ve made more progress than I give myself credit for.

All sorts of bizarre ideas waltzed through my imagination, when I tried to envision Earth. I was the first Venlil to visit humanity’s home; not even the bravest scientists or diplomats would venture to the “blue marble.” It was a massive step, which might be a far cry from my preconceptions of society.

Landing on Terran soil would place me at the whims of their government, and expose me to the general populace. It would offer better insight into what the average predator was like, but was that a positive? I was woefully unprepared for what I had seen, mixing in with the UN military units.

As the spacecraft touched down, I tried to remind myself that it was too late to back out. This was not the time for second thoughts; my fright would only contribute to the other passengers’ panic.

“Gojid refugees, line up single file and prepare to exit the ship. Anyone who fails to follow the directions of UN soldiers will be hit with a tranquilizer dart, for your own safety,” a grating voice growled over the PA system. “Volunteers are handing out blankets, water, and dried fruit. If you require medication or special accommodations, approach the nearest human in a white coat or red cross insignia. You are safe here. Please do not panic.”

I snorted. Easier said than done.

The humans’ statements didn’t have the calming effect they desired; there wasn’t a single refugee that didn’t look petrified. One elderly Gojid collapsed with a thud, clutching her chest. The terror generated by this amount of predators could certainly cause a heart attack. Terran medics gestured for everyone to move back, and hurried to cart the cardiac victim out.

For the Gojids on board, it must appear they were being towed to a predators’ lair as cattle. Ferocious-looking soldiers with massive guns were corralling them into the open air. Who would believe a beast’s claim, that they would return anyone that wished to leave to a Gojid or Federation territory, as soon as they arranged terms with their government?

“Hi, Slanek,” Tyler said hesitantly.

The blond human took a timid approach, as if worried about frightening me. As traumatic as his table manners were, the big guy’s intentions were benevolent. He couldn’t help that his taste buds evolved with such a vile proclivity. Like Marcel explained, it was biology that was beyond their control.

I was aware that predators consumed meat by definition, and that didn’t negate everything I knew about their rich emotions. Humans weren’t like the Arxur, hunting living creatures; they cultivated cell samples in a lab. What was so amoral about that, other than the fact that it was appallingly gross?

It’s on the same level as consuming fecal matter. Don’t exactly want to share a table, or drink out of the same saucer. But it doesn’t have to shape my entire opinion of him. Out of sight, out of mind.

“Thanks for saving my life, Tyler. Sorry for freaking out back there.” I pinned my ears against my head, and saw his eyes soften at my scared expression. “It was a good idea on paper, for me to help humanity communicate with civilians. But I had no idea what I was signing up for. It was sensory overload, all the death, predation, and aggression.”

“It’s cool. I forget how much you guys hate predators sometimes. I know, Marcel doesn’t…but how could he?” the flesh-eater muttered.

Following Tyler’s sharp gaze, my own eyes landed on the redhead. I couldn’t help but notice the looks Marcel shot the Gojid adults throughout the ride. Clearly, his own species picked up on it too. This mission wasn’t the thrilling revenge jaunt he dreamed of.

My friend’s right limb was stuffed in a sling, while his dominant arm held the spiky child. He was clutching Nulia to his chest, like he expected someone to take her away. His hazel eyes were glazed over, as he watched the adult refugees stumble outside. A tear rolled down his cheek, which the young Gojid poked with a claw.

“Don’t cry,” she whimpered. “Why are you sad?”

The human pawed at his eyes. “I’m not. Just tired.”

The child tilted her head. “But you JUST slept for hours, Mawsle!”

“Marrrr-cel,” he enunciated, rolling the r sound with a reverberating growl. “You can say it, dear.”

“Mawah…sell.” Nulia hooked her claws into the corners of his lips, and tugged them upward. I gaped at her bravado, playing with a predator’s eating orifice. “There’s the happy snarl! Stay like that.”

Marcel flashed his teeth with genuine amusement. He glanced at me, noticing that Tyler and I were both watching with concern. The vegetarian struggled to his feet, limping toward us at the rear of the line. We shuffled to the exit as a pack, and my nerves surged through my veins. Warm sunlight struck my face, as I took my first look at humanity’s home.

The refugee camp was based in a decommissioned airport, judging by its appearance. Various structures had been converted to lodging, and tents dotted the runways. Humans were passing out supplies in what I thought was a former hangar bay. Doctors checked on any Gojids showing signs of life-threatening distress.

Camera crews were parked on the other side of a chain-link fence. A few predators shouted the word Venlil, trying to get my attention. For better or for worse, my image was as the first representative of my species here. I forced myself to straighten, and offered the most human-like wave I could muster.

UN guards manned the perimeter, allowing only cleared personnel through the gates either way. Alarm rocketed through my veins, as I spotted a ferocious, four-legged predator alongside them. The brown-and-black beast made the humans look cute and cuddly. I was sure its serrated fangs could puncture their flesh like pudding, but the primates seemed oblivious.

It sniffed the air with twitching nostrils, and eyed the armed Terrans with hungry pupils. I knew they had forward-facing vision, but how could they be that blind to their surroundings? How could the dangerous beast have drawn that close to them unnoticed?

My survival instincts leapt into overdrive. “RUN! PREDATOR! SAVE YOURSELVES! RUN, QUICK!”

Wait, Marcel can’t run. He’s going to get picked off first; him and Nulia are an easy target. The humans need to gun down the predator before it gets to us!

I bolted back toward the transport, overcome with a blinding terror. Tyler raced after me, closing the distance with long strides. He scooped me up despite my shrill, incoherent protests, and walked back to Marcel and the child.

“There’s a lot of predators here, Slanek,” Marcel sighed. “What, you’ve never seen a human before?”

I thrashed in Tyler’s grasp, trying to get him to put me down. My ability to formulate words other than “predator” or “run” was greatly diminished. A pitiful squeak escaped from my mouth, and I jabbed a claw at the monstrous quadruped. It was panting and slobbering over the humans’ boots! Were they the most clueless species in the galaxy?

Nulia screeched as she spotted the beast, and understanding flashed in Marcel’s eyes. He massaged the child’s neck, seeing her spines pop up. Why didn’t the human seem the least bit afraid? Why didn’t he call to the guards to shoot the predator?

“That is called a dog,” Marcel said slowly. “We domesticated them thousands of years ago…which means we trained them to be friendly to humans.”

Tyler grinned. “I have one at home! They helped us with hunting back in the old days, but now we keep them as p—”

“Companions,” my human interjected. “Dogs are loyal and obedient to us. They’re not sapient, but we have a close bond. Those UN guys have the ‘predator’ situation under control.”

I watched as a Terran soldier patted the dog on its head, and its tongue lolled out of its mouth. The human fished into his pocket, pulling out a cookie. He placed it into his hand, stretching his palm as flat as it could go, then offered it to the fanged predator. What was this madman doing? Trying to lose a limb?

The beast sniffed at the offering, and wagged its tail. Disbelief filled my chest as it snapped up the morsel, seizing the food without nicking the man’s hand. It barked at the Terrans, who were showering it with toddler-esque praise. Did that non-sapient predator understand their words?!

I can’t believe even humans tried to befriend that…thing. Conditioning dogs “to be friendly to humans” means they weren’t always friendly, I mused. And Tyler keeps one in his residence, like that is normal. How can he sleep with it around?

Tyler sensed that I calmed down enough, and placed me back on the ground. Was that how human hunting worked; co-opting other predators to do their dirty work? Marcel promised an answer once we were out of danger, but had yet to fulfill his vow. My outburst already drew a lot of unwanted attention though, so I decided not to say anything now.

One human took brisk strides toward us, flanked by a group of soldiers. His thinning salt-and-pepper mane, and crisp coat with a UN pin, looked familiar. Dear stars, it was the Secretary-General himself; I recognized him from our landing at the outpost. Was his entourage coming to arrest me for inciting panic?

“Slanek, isn’t it? Welcome to Earth!” Elias Meier leaned in, so close that I could feel his breath inside my ear. The air movement tickled the sensitive hairs, and I resisted the urge to paw at it. “Act natural and pose for the cameras for a moment. It’ll be bad PR for everyone if they think you’re afraid of us.”

The human official draped his arm across my neck, and I forced myself not to shy away. Why did the predators always have to grab for the vital areas? All he’d have to do would be to lock his elbow, to constrict my throat.

“I apologize for the canine presence.” The Secretary-General spoke the words in a booming tone, and I sensed that he was trying to tell the media that I hadn’t freaked out from the humans. “The dogs are necessary for security purposes.”

“Security from what?” I whispered.

Meier smiled, but did not answer. He slipped his arm from my shoulders, and gestured for us to follow him. I tailed behind the UN leader on shaky legs, terrified to traverse the checkpoint. Marcel and Tyler lurked at the rear, probably to seal off my escape route if I tried to run.

The dog was tethered by a thin rope, on closer inspection, but it seemed to be pulling the humans more than anything. Those awful eyes were watching me; its yellowed fangs were the size of my ear. I couldn’t stop hyperventilating. A predator like that could smell my fear, couldn’t it? What could the Terrans do if it lunged at me?

A tinted vehicle was waiting with a door ajar, and Meier flicked a hand toward the car. I didn’t need a second invitation to spring into the steel death trap. Marcel and Tyler squished in beside me, while the Secretary-General found a seat opposite us. The Gojid child was inconsolable after the dog sighting, sobbing into my human’s grimy uniform.

Meier raised his eyebrows. “Where are your parents, kid? They must be worried sick about you.”

“No they’re not!” Nulia wailed. “I called for my mommy and she never came back. She didn’t care if Mawsle or the bad monsters ate me.”

Marcel gave her head a gentle pat. “Your mother made a mistake, darling, because she was really scared. She loved you very much.”

Tyler nodded. “That’s right. You’re a good kid.”

Meier’s eyes lingered on Nulia for a moment. His thinly-veiled displeasure suggested he’d prefer if Gojid children weren’t roaming his planet. Evidently, he decided it wasn’t good PR to force Marcel to leave her behind either.

“Anyhow. Sorry about that mess, Slanek. I had no idea the Venlil were sending visitors, though don’t misunderstand me. We’re thrilled to have you here,” the Secretary-General said. “I’ll work out luxurious arrangements for all of you. If there’s anything you want, just ask.”

I cuddled up to my human. “T-thank you, sir.”

“Anything for our galactic neighbors. I’m pleased that you both returned alive, especially with how symbolic your connection has become here on Earth. Speaking of which…I have some positive news.”

Marcel leaned forward. “Positive news?”

“Sovlin has been arrested by UN forces. He’s being held in a clandestine facility for alien POWs, and is awaiting trial.”

My eyes widened, while my friend’s gaze narrowed. How had the Terrans tracked down the sadistic Gojid? Regardless of their methodology, I was relieved the captain wouldn’t get away with his wretched deeds. If the predators executed Sovlin, it would satisfy Marcel’s wish for his death. The anger boiling inside him was taking its toll on his kind soul.

“Take me there,” my human growled. “I want to see him.”

Secretary-General Meier exhaled, shaking his head in the negative. “That’s not a good idea.”

“So what? Pull some strings. I’m not going to do anything drastic,” Marcel said.

“And why would I risk the political fallout, if you did attack an alien prisoner in our custody? There is zero benefit to any party, and we aren’t prepared to host visitors there regardless. You’ll be able to see Sovlin in court.”

“C’mon! All I want is a short conversation, Meier.” The red-haired human’s expression was pleading, and his eyes searched the UN leader’s resolute face. “I’ll go along with whatever media strategy you want in return. You know I’m important to our propaganda efforts, at home and abroad.”

The UN leader stared out the window in thought. Was Marcel’s claim that he was that vital to the Terran narrative accurate? The Secretary-General crossed his arms with a resigned sigh, like he hated his next actions. A holopad found its way into his hands, and he began typing out a message.

“I’m sure I will regret this. I’ll let you peek at his cell from outside. You can enter only if Sovlin wants to see you,” Meier rumbled. “Understand?”

Marcel nodded. “Yes.”

My ears pinned back against my head. Those predatory eyes brewed with such a deep hatred, that it made me squirm. There was no telling whether the human could…or would restrain his aggression, once his tormentor was within grasping distance.

Whatever happened, my primary hope was that this confrontation would bring him peace, at last.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 30
Memory transcription subject:

Slanek,
Venlil Space Corps

Date [standardized human time]:
October 3, 2136

Accompanying Marcel to visit his tormentor was my overarching desire, but persuading the predator proved an impossible task. It baffled me why he believed this confrontation was something he needed to tackle alone. The worry I felt for my human was tremendous; I couldn't imagine how traumatic it was to encounter Sovlin, with the roles reversed.

Beyond that, it was terrifying to be stranded on Earth, without him to protect me. Whenever something frightened me, there was the comforting assurance that the vegetarian would fix it. I was beginning to understand that Marcel shielded me from the predatory side of humanity, to the best of his ability. Who was there to filter the stimuli around me now?

You need to get used to humans on your own, Slanek. Toughen up, I chided myself. That orphan toddler is twice as brave as you!

Nulia seemed anxious without her scarred predator; the poor thing must be fearful of being abandoned again. Tyler landed babysitting duty for the Gojid child, while her guardian was away. The meat-eater had finally retired to his room, trying to get both of them some shut-eye.

As babyish as it would have been, I wished I tagged along. Every shadow that danced on the wall seemed like a dog sneaking up on me. There was no chance of getting a wink of sleep, knowing I was trapped in a land of predators alone. How could any sane species leave their varmint alive?

With a frustrated sigh, I jabbed a claw on the remote. It was a bad idea to watch their television without supervision, but the boredom was stirring up the dark side of my imagination regardless. The screen opposite the bed flickered to life, set to a news channel by default. A stern-looking female had her intense, predatory eyes fixed on the camera.

"...ever trust the Federation?" she asked. "None of their information about predators has been correct. The continued survival of the human race is due to their astonishing incompetence; their fundamental lack of curiosity. You, your children, and your loved ones are vermin to be killed to them. These aliens take offense to your existence."

"Not the Venlil!" I yipped, knowing that she couldn't hear me.

"The UN ambassador and the Venlil governor never returned, from a summit where they tried to negotiate with these genocidal maniacs. At this point, we have to presume that Noah Williams was murdered. Maybe it's time to give the Feds a dose of the predators they're asking for. Is this why the Arxur turned on them? How were they really treated at first contact?"

That statement made my blood boil. How could any human argue with the mountain of footage, depicting Arxur sadism? It was an undisputed fact that the Federation uplifted those predators, gifting the means to blaze a trail of destruction. Hadn't the Terran soldiers returned with stories of the grays rounding up cattle, and snacking on living Gojids mid-battle?

Surely, no humans bought this outrageous line of thinking. This had to be a sensationalist take to garner publicity for her broadcast. That, or it was satire. I failed to see the humor, but then again, I always took a literal interpretation of things. Terran comedy could be pretty dark and tasteless, from the jokes I heard on my deployment.

"Nothing excuses cannibalism and xenocide, to those who will inevitably take my words out of context. I just don't see a reason to accept a bigot's narrative, without any critical thinking. Recent intelligence suggests ship movement in the Krakotl..."

The hotel door clicked open without warning, which startled me upright. What if it was UN security guards, coming to secure my room with a dog? That creature was going to be my nightmare fuel for months; I could vividly picture it ripping off a Venlil limb, with a toss of its ugly head.

My fear morphed to relief as I saw it was Marcel, who bore an exhausted look on his face. The predator's emotions must be depleted, after such a taxing journey. He flopped back-first on the bed, allowing the residual tension to ebb from his shoulders. I assaulted him with a hug, and ignored the groan as I knocked the wind out of him.

"Easy, buddy," the human grunted. "It's only been a day!"

I emitted a happy mewl, as he settled me onto his chest with his uninjured arm. The room's dark environment felt much brighter, with my friend to shepherd me. Nothing could harm me when he was around; not even a dog. The human tickled my chin with a low chuckle, and I rested my paws atop his stomach.

My eyes met his piercing gaze. "I was worried sick about you. How did it go? Are you okay?"

"I'm fine. I...I think I'm ready to move forward," he replied. "But I don't want to talk about it. Let's talk about something else, alright?"

"Sure. How about what kind of predators humans are?"

"Shit, Slanek. Do we have to discuss that now? It's 1 in the morning—"

"Yes, we do. You promised, and I think I deserve the truth. It's like you don't trust me, even after all we've been through together."

Marcel searched my expression, a mix of concern and affection in his eyes. The human seemed reluctant to answer. His fear of losing me was palpable, from how his fingers tightened around my fur. What could be so sinister that it would alter my view of him, after all this time? I trusted him with my life; if my stupid instincts didn't get in the way, I would take a bullet for him.

"It's complicated," he growled, after several seconds of silence. "Humans have employed every predation strategy in the book. Like Tyler said, dogs have helped us. We've set traps, used ambush tactics, fished, raised livestock...yes, I know you hate that word. But you asked."

I tilted my head. "You said you weren't ambush predators."

"We're versatile. Anyhow, what people claim we are, is one of the oldest hunting strategies known to mankind. It's called persistence hunting."

The human paused, as though expecting a dramatic reaction. My blank stare seemed to disappoint him; his lips curved downward even further. I could tell how much he disliked this topic, but we had already gotten this far.

Is that 'persistence hunting' phrase supposed to mean something to me?

"Continue? I don't get it," I pressed.

"Humans possess a high endurance, because of our sweating ability. We can run a lot longer...especially in the hot climates we originated in." Marcel closed his eyes, unable to meet my gaze. "We were never faster than our prey. We just had more stamina. We chased them until they stopped running."

A chill ran down my spine, as I processed the meaning of those words. Was he telling me that humans pursued their prey for hours... maybe even days? That they never tired, or gave up on a pursuit? Such an ordeal meant their quarry had an eternity to contemplate their demise. The victim spent their last day in a desperate, agonized flight. Their terror lasted much longer than the split second of an ambush.

My brain began to imagine running from a human, feeling the burning of my muscles and my lungs. The savage predator would draw closer, every time I paused to rest or dampened my pace. Knowing all the while that the second my legs gave out, my death was a certainty. There was no hope of escape, short of confronting the hunter.

What an awful way to go. Having your own body betray you, and languishing in a pool of chemical exhaustion. The predator would slowly approach, bloodlust in its eyes, signifying the end...I thought humans showed mercy? They conducted themselves like reasonable, kind, and feeling people; not relentless beasts that inflicted torment on the weak.

Tears streamed down my face, at the thought of my human partaking in that sort of predation. It felt awful, to think of him in that regard. If he was born a few thousand years ago, would he have chased helpless creatures through the scorching heat too? Was that what was coded in his instincts?

"Slanek? Gosh, you're shaking." Marcel rubbed my ear comfortingly. "Say something, please. Even if it's that you hate me."

Sadness seeped onto his expression, which knocked some sense back into me. It was painful to see how heartbroken he looked. I resisted the urge to swat his hand away, and attempted to regain my wits. The predator's honesty was admirable, when he foretold precisely how I would react. I knew, in my soul, that my human would never dream of harming me.

It was time to stop fixating on their heritage, as much as anything predatory frightened my instincts. Humanity left their gruesome past behind, and had proven themselves more than capable of empathy. My reactions were the product of a stupid, irrational phobia. I wanted to love them fully, without awful thoughts creeping into my head all the time.

"O...okay. P-persistence. Got it," I stammered.

The human blinked. "What?"

"I accept you, f-for whatever you are, because I care about you. No matter what."

The predator clutched me tighter, and restrained his own tears. It was important for Marcel to know that he didn't have to apologize for his existence. After wrestling with wretched self-doubts, my acceptance was essential for his mental welfare. Humans didn't need to alter themselves to prove they were worthy of our friendship.

"Thank you," he whispered. "Keep it between us, please. I'll get in trouble for telling you."

I flicked my ears. "Okay. That is an awful form of predation, which doesn't exist on our world, so I get why you avoided the subject. But Tarva deserves to know. She would still stand by you; I'm certain."

"I'd hope the governor would take heart, knowing the fruit our roots have borne. We just do the best with what we have in our toolset. Humans are survivors; whatever it takes, we have the resolve and the dedication."

"How is that encouraging in any way, Marc?"

"Maybe it will help you to realize the lengths we would go for you, our Venlil friends. And you'll know that we will hunt the Arxur to the ends of the universe; that there will be nowhere they can hide. We'll battle a scourge like that as long as our species survives."

Marcel's argument was persuasive enough, when he phrased it like that. The Terran pledge to liberate sentient farm worlds, and all of their military aspirations, felt much more feasible. An arduous war wouldn't daunt humanity like it did for us.

I suppose there was another positive to their hunting methodology, in that it wasn't a deceptive art. They had no reason to employ trickery, or extend a hand in a false friendship. This could be conveyed as a reason to trust humanity, if they played their cards right.

"You should get one of the UN people to 'tell me.' You'll need to be more tactful with most Venlil; framing is everything." I pinned my ears against my head, trying to keep a storm of negative emotions at bay. "I can think of a way to make your ancestry more palatable. Maybe just say you can withstand heat better, so you're desert pursuit predators. Or shift the focus to your recent cattle practices."

"Er, I'm not sure a close examination of factory farms is a good idea either. Never mind that. You took that better than I expected, by far, Slanek."

"I want to stop panicking, but I don't know how. My kneejerk reactions aren't what I really think, once my brain comes around. But sometimes...usually, I can't control it! You deserve a better friend."

I ducked my head, feeling shame roll down my spine. Despite my constant efforts, my brain refused to forget that these lumbering primates were predators. My subconscious reminded me at every turn that humans weren't like us, and that they could morph into feral beasts at any second. Marcel did deserve so much better.

All that time he wastes comforting me, and trying to calm me down. I'm a burden. A loser.

"Are you kidding? I got paired with the best Venlil." Marcel offered his signature snarl, which was menacing yet gentle. "I wanted to be a part of the first contact program so bad. Do you know how many questions we had to answer?"

"30? 50? How many?"

"200, plus an in-person interview, a background check, and a psychological exam. All of my communications were analyzed since first contact, for any red flags. What was your selection process like?"

"I volunteered."

"Um, right. I'm sure there weren't a lot of takers for your position," the red-haired human chuckled. "There was no guarantee that my partner would get past seeing me. You know from the stories around the outpost that some people didn't."

That was a true statement. Several Venlil fainted once in proximity of their penpals, and were taken to the infirmary. A smaller minority abandoned the program altogether, due to meeting their Terran counterparts.

I remembered how my fear had been almost painful that first day. It was no wonder a few Venlil found the humans too intimidating for cohabitation. Still, I couldn't imagine how those predators felt, being rejected on sight after weeks of chatting.

The worst horror story was a Venlil that panicked at a human stepping into her room, and leapt into self-defense mode. She grabbed the nearest sharp object, which was a pair of scissors, and plunged it into the Terran's shoulder. Her partner, while wounded, was able to wrestle the blade from her claws; the violence was not returned. The predator didn't press charges, for some reason, despite Venlil government's offer to prosecute.

Meanwhile, Marcel and I shared potato chips on our first day. Not the worst pairing he could've had, I suppose?

"Anyways. I talked to Lucy, you know, my fiancé, on the ride here. She wants me to come home, but I've gotten used to having you around." Marcel took a deep breath, scratching his stubbly scalp. "Ah, maybe it's not the right time to ask, after what I just told you."

"No, I'm calm now. Go on."

"How would you feel about living with us? You can come and go as you please. Any time you want to return to Venlil Prime, you don't have to stay. But we'll take care of all of your expenses, whenever you want to be here."

I gaped at him. The idea of a permanent residence with my human filled my chest with warmth, but Earth was as alien as any world could get. A trial period was all I could commit to, to see how I handled prolonged exposure to a predatory environment. Would the UN...or technically, the regional government be okay with my staying?

"Er, I'll think about it. Does that mean you're going to receive a military discharge?"

"No. But I've requested a transfer home, so I can live planetside. I'll only be involved with the defense of Earth, should that be necessary."

"And what about Nulia? She needs you more than I do. She'd be devastated if she ends up in a camp, alone."

"Don't be ridiculous! We're going to adopt her. I already spoke with Meier about the necessary paperwork, and he's going to contact the American State Department. They're starting from scratch on that one, I think."

The Gojid child would be elated. I wondered how being raised by predators would impact her development, but I knew she'd grow up in a loving environment. It was obvious the human considered her to be his own daughter, and would care for her accordingly. There wasn't a more touching tale, than to witness these pursuit hunters rescuing the children of a species that swore to destroy Earth.

"Sounds like you've got it all figured out... Mawsle," I whispered.

"Why, you fluffy little shit!" The human glowered at me, while I feigned ignorance. "Don't you dare start that, too! I can and will rescind my offer."

I wagged my tail. "Too late. No takebacks."

My family back on Venlil Prime would say I was suicidal to accept; but the more I thought about his proposition, the more enticing it seemed. Navigating humanity's diplomatic hurdles, helping a predator raise a prey child, and protecting their planet from harm could be my new calling. Maybe one day, Earth would even feel like my home.

At any rate, free rent sounded pretty darn good to my ears.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 31
Memory transcription subject:

Governor Tarva,
Venlil Republic

Date [standardized human time]:
October 3, 2136

In a half-day, our ship would reach the edge of Republic space, and we’d be able to transmit communications back to our UN contacts. The Terrans had been slated to open an embassy on Venlil Prime, a few days after our original departure. That meant they would have a full diplomatic staff on world, and would be available to help humans abroad.

Many Terran nations requested their own embassies, so they could conduct their affairs as separate entities. While I liked the predators, I wasn’t giving out an absurd 198 embassies, versus every other species’ singular site. Humans were welcome to bicker amongst themselves about who could send their own diplomatic corps, and how to divide the turf, if they must.

I had no interest in making their discordance my business. My focus was on smoothing over both of our relations with the Federation. It was also a priority to stabilize my friend’s mental health, especially after weeks of isolation and boredom. Learning how the human mind coped with stress would be useful down the road.

After careful consideration of the astronaut’s mannerisms, I decided there was no major cause for alarm. All of our research showed that humans were highly social creatures. Ambassador Noah perked up just from having new conversation partners at hand.

A few days to unwind, in the company of his own people, and he’d be begging to get back into the field. He only needed to “recharge his batteries”, as the Terrans said.

Noah’s excelled in quite an uncomfortable position. Volunteering with the belief that he would be a martyr. Standing in as a representative for his whole species. That kind of pressure has to pile up.

“…in conclusion, the International Space Station proved that humanity can cooperate in the stars.” The predator was finishing a story I’d heard before; he had a rapt audience in our Mazic passenger. “That scientists see our beautiful Earth differently from above. The ISS was our first foothold off-world. It paved the path for lunar colonies, and set a precedent of joint exploration.”

“So then, why has your planet still not united under a single banner, Noah? You do not care for distant members of your species without a, shall I say, stellar view?” came the scoffing response.

When President Cupo’s question reached my ears, I was concerned that other diplomats would voice similar concerns. The Mazic still seemed leery of the human, despite being thrice the weight of the predator. No offense to Noah, but I’m pretty sure the beige prey-animal could knock him out with a stamp of his flat paw, easily.

Humanity’s internal divisions were a disquieting issue, to the galaxy as a whole. The newcomers seemed to be trying to work up the courage to ask about it for days. With the external threat of predation in our formative years, prey species had to maintain unity. Cooperation was our bread and fruit spread, so to speak. Indulging in petty squabbles would’ve gotten us killed.

I’d seen several exit interviews with various leaders, before we left signal range of Aafa. Many dissenters cited Earth’s disputes as proof that the predators were incapable of cooperation. It was their main evidence that the primates were still warlike and disagreeable.

“Humans evolved in a lot of small tribes, which later became nation-states. These each have their own distinct culture: beliefs, music, stories, cuisine, and languages,” the Terran ambassador replied, leaning back in his seat. “It would be losing a part of our heritage to renounce that…and because of our differing viewpoints, we don’t always agree on how things should be done.”

Cupo flared his trunk. “But why can you not maintain your practices, under a common entity? You claim freedom of beliefs are a core value.”

“It would be like you unifying with the Nevoks. You may like each other plenty, perhaps you are even allies, but you would not abide by the same jurisdiction. We have common forums, alliances, and trade agreements…so Nikonus was quite mistaken, in thinking we do not speak the language of diplomacy. We work together when it matters.”

It didn’t escape my notice that Tossa, the Nevok representative, was watching with interest. The Sivkit, Zurulian, and Yotul occupants were also observing the exchange. None of them were being subtle, with how their ears were swiveled toward the predator. The other Federation diplomats had flown with Recel in a separate ship, too daunted to embark on a human-infested vessel.

Cupo was just the only one bold enough to voice what they all are thinking. Now, the floodgates are open, I thought. I better be ready to intervene, if Noah gets overwhelmed.

“Predator Noah, please forgive my impertinence.” Laulo, the Yotul diplomat, spoke in a measured tone. The uplift had given the human a wide berth, but at least was able to meet his startling gaze. “Do humans still fight wars when you, um, disagree?”

“Sometimes. One always hopes those quarrels can be resolved with words. Rest assured, a common threat, like the Arxur, should place any of our lingering disputes on the back burner.”

The Federation representatives looked baffled by that answer. As I learned early on, the national affairs of Earth were a complex matter. It was imprudent to deal with any nation individually, since that could be construed as favoritism. Most of the humans’ rhetoric was posturing, but they were always locked in jealous competition.

It was strange how human tribes perceived their interests as separate. They had much more in common than divided them, and they even seemed to recognize their folly when asked. It was one of several areas I had pointed out to renowned neuroscientist Ilja for closer study.

“I suspect a human’s temper can run much hotter, much quicker than ours,” Chauson offered, in a matter-of-fact tone. “None of my research suggests their end goal is loss of life. It is just the result of aggression. Their predatory inclination is to deal with a perceived threat through violence, rather than fleeing.”

“Er, not fully accurate, doc. Humans have a fight or flight response,” Noah growled. "We can panic or freeze, just like you. It varies from person to person, and what temperament they have. Some of us are wholly incapable of aggression.”

A contemplative silence fell over our entourage, and Chauson scribbled something in his sketchbook. The last tidbit was news to me too. I assumed aggression was part of every predator’s natural makeup, since that ferocity facilitated their ancestors’ survival.

Were there really some humans as timid and anxious as us? That cowered at threats like Venlil?

If so, it was obvious Noah was not one of those humans. While the ambassador was skilled at masking his emotions, hostility seeped through whenever he saw the Venlil threatened. Its source was almost paternal. The look in his eyes at first contact, when he watched the grays tormenting our pups, was apoplectic.

Lots of compassionate humans were angry when they saw those videos. I wish we were home, so the Federation could meet the volunteer doctors and aid workers. It’s been too—

A rattling noise hummed through the ship walls, jolting me out of my thoughts. This time, it was more insistent than its previous occurrences throughout the journey. There was no reason a ship which deployed a year ago should experience issues, but it roused some worries nonetheless.

“Hey, Tarva? Not to stir up panic, but is that grating sound normal?” the Terran ambassador asked.

Something felt…off with the shuttle, since it took flight. The predator’s unease validated my suspicions. I was inclined to propose further investigation, even though we were one territory away from home. The last thing we needed was to be stranded in space, with a bunch of skittish diplomats and an inoperable ship.

I tilted my head. “No, it’s not. I’m going to run a ship diagnostic, just to be safe.”

Laulo raised a peach-colored paw. “It’s coming from the cooling shaft. We should take a look there.”

“As if you know,” Tossa scoffed. “I’d hardly trust your ilk to fix a sailboat! The printing press is a novelty to you primitives.”

“Were your ancestors born with spaceships?” Noah glowered at her, and the Nevok froze under his ocular intensity. “I didn’t know we were graced by the presence of a species, who were endowed with divine knowledge!”

Tossa quivered, her icy fur raising along her hackles. “W-we found our way on our own. We d-didn’t have everything handed to us!”

“The Yotul would have learned on their own, with time. You interfered in their natural development, so that they could join your war!”

“Are you daft, predator? The Arxur don’t give a grain stalk about natural development.”

“And neither do you, with your insensitive and tone-deaf comments. How the fuck did you become a diplomat?”

Laulo looked aghast at the predator’s vehement defense of his species. I think he assumed that the ambassador didn’t know the Yotul’s origins, but it was obvious the human had done his homework. The marsupial was likely surprised that the Terran would side with him. Especially when he was accustomed to verbal beatdowns from fellow diplomats.

It was apparent that Noah had lost all patience with the vitriolic rhetoric toward the uplift. Tossa’s condescension, singling the Yotul out at every turn, rubbed my friend the wrong way. However noble his outburst, the last thing we needed was for him to alienate an influential ally. The Nevoks could be a crucial supplier of resources and ship parts to Earth.

Axsely, the Sivkit representative, was sobbing from the primate’s raised voice. She had yet to speak a word to Noah, only introducing herself to the rest of us while he was asleep. A shouting match wasn’t the way to calm her nerves either.

“Stop it, both of you!” I hissed. “Every second we spend bickering, the Arxur win. Let’s be respectful to each other, alright?”

The human drew a shuddering breath. “My apologies, Governor. I’m not the type to stand idle while someone else is mocked and bullied.”

“It’s not mockery, predator. I’m merely stating facts,” Tossa said.

“My name is not predator. It’s Noah, Ambassador Williams, or if that’s too fucking difficult, I’ll settle for human!”

“Uh, sorry about that,” Laulo muttered.

The human snorted. “You’re fine. At least you used my name.”

The Nevok curled her lip. “Predator is just a word, which does describe you. You’re too defensive, Noah.”

“So you can pronounce it! Fascinating.”

Despite my best efforts, the two of them were still at each other’s throats. Whoever managed Terran relations with the Nevok Imperium, it couldn’t involve Noah in any way. The human was so incensed by his counterpart’s attitude, that he hadn’t noticed Axsely balling up into a fetal position. I believed he would’ve backed down if he realized the fright his ire had caused.

“Not another word!” I swished my tail in frustration. “Noah, you are coming with me, alone, and that’s not up for discussion. I’m going to run a diagnostic, and we’ll see if Laulo’s intuition is correct.”

The Terran ambassador opened his mouth to argue, but then followed my pupils toward the sniveling Sivkit. His expression softened, replaced by a worried furrow of his brow. That agitation might’ve undone any progress with the Mazic too. President Cupo had inched away from the human, and was trying to comfort Axsely with soothing words. The timid female was unresponsive, rocking back and forth.

At least our Zurulian friend seemed to enjoy that, I mused. Chauson was trying to be the ship stenographer, during that whole exchange!

Noah lowered his gaze, and strode over to me with dejection. The predator risked a glance over his shoulder, making eye contact with Laulo. The marsupial mouthed his gratitude, and the Terran’s posture relaxed. He gave the Yotul a slight nod of acknowledgement, before shuffling into the cockpit.

I hovered by the ship computer, pulling up the troubleshooting module. It would take several seconds to complete a cursory scan, which would give Noah’s temper time to blow over. I hoped that nothing was amiss with the vessel. The implications of a defect would be unpleasant.

“I didn’t scare you, did I, Tarva?” Noah murmured.

I snorted. “No. I’m just trying to stop Earth’s foreign relations from imploding on week one. For the sake of argument, let’s say you piss off the Nevoks. The Federation will parade them around, using them as proof that you can’t be allies with humanity.”

“And then, we lose the undecided votes.”

“Exactly. There is too much at stake, for all of us.”

A soft beep indicated that the diagnostic was complete, and we returned our attention to the computer. A holographic avatar of the shuttle zoomed in to the ship’s underbelly. It highlighted a long pipe in blinking red; an autogenerated note indicated that cooling fluid was leaking. The shaft was nestled right next to the warp drive, so it didn’t take an engineer to figure its purpose.

That part of the ship was only accessible from the exterior; fixing it would require a spacewalk. My immediate suspicion was that someone had tampered with the vessel. Mainly because the pipe leaked just enough, that it wouldn’t cause immediate alarm…or breakdown in range of the Kolshian surveillance team. But who would have sabotaged us? What was their motive?

“So it was the cooling system,” the human said calmly. “Stop the ship. I’ll get a vac suit, and try to patch her up.”

I flicked my ears. “No. You need to stay here and keep an eye on everyone.”

“Why?”

“I suspect foul play. Deliberate damage. If it’s one of the species on board, they could be trying to lure you off the ship. That way, they can take all of us out, without having to fight a predator.”

Noah squinted in confusion. It was refreshing that the ambassador didn’t panic at the first hint of danger; his reaction was cool and calculating. The human lacked a full understanding of the situation, and I suspected he disliked the uncertainty more than the peril.

“That makes zero sense. Who would do such a thing?”

“I don’t know. That’s what I want to find out. If our vessel went missing in no man’s land, with all of humanity’s allies on board, you know who would foot the blame.”

He frowned. “Always me, isn’t it?”

I flicked my ears in acknowledgment; Noah shook his head in disgust. Unfortunately, humanity had no shortage of enemies within the Federation. The two of us needed to talk it over, and work out anyone who could have a possible angle. Ruling out the five species on board was our top priority, since they would be an immediate threat.

Of course, it could be someone on Recel’s ship. I wonder if they ran into any trouble, or if this was only targeted at the human, I thought.

“I don’t know where to start.” I slammed a paw on the console, stressed at the prospect of ship-wide interrogation. “There could be any number of parties involved; someone inside or outside our group. An ally or an enemy. How do we even begin to narrow the field?”

“Let’s start with who we think it couldn’t be,” Noah growled. “Can we clear anyone on this ship? Someone we can account for, or are almost certain they’re fine?”

“I trust Chauson.”

“Really? I don’t know about him.”

“He’s never been unkind to you, which is saying a lot.”

“That’s exactly why he’s suspicious, Tarva. He’s too nice. What if he’s up to something?”

“The Zurulians were the only ones to reach out before the vote. Also, as you know, we do an awful job controlling our instincts. Chauson couldn’t fake not being afraid of a predator; he pranced up to you while his head was dripping blood.”

The ambassador tapped his foot a few times, and a touch of relief flickered in his brown eyes. It saddened me that mistreatment was so commonplace for him, that normal interaction triggered alarm bells in his head. The Zurulian scientist was the only person I’d seen attempt to squash his instincts, in his first meeting with a human.

If we trusted Chauson, bringing him into the loop might not be the worst idea. Three minds were better than two, and he was intelligent enough not to jump to conclusions. Besides, someone needed to mend the cooling shaft damage. I would volunteer, except that with my technical knowhow, I was more likely to make the warp core spontaneously combust.

The fewer people know the true reason for our predicament, the better. Let’s hope Chauson can keep his mouth shut, when asked.

Sharing my suspicions with the entire ship would only incite panic, and lead to in-fighting and accusations. Knowing how paranoid some species were about predators, they would find a way to blame Noah. Because obviously, the nefarious human would cripple his ride home, after weeks of imprisonment, for some illusory goal. It made perfect sense, if you didn’t think about it.

I sighed. “Do not tell anyone, anything, other than that we’re fixing a minor problem. I’m going to fetch Chauson.”

The human nodded. If anyone could sniff out deceit, it would be an observant predator like Noah. One way or another, we were going to get to the bottom of this debacle. I suppose it was too much to ask, for these introductions to be smooth sailing, and for Earth to attain some genuine allies without any hiccups.

When I ascertained the responsible party, they were going to receive some harsh retribution, courtesy of the human-Venlil alliance.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 42
Memory transcription subject:

Slanek,
Venlil Space Corps

Date [standardized human time]:
October 8, 2136

The humans instructed me to place a wraparound headset over my ears. I was impressed with how they had modified their technology with Venlil in mind, though I hoped I wasn’t the only one who would get to use it. The earpiece fed simulated audio of alarms and hits; it also allowed Sara to speak to me directly.

“Slanek, I’m going to talk to you throughout this exercise. In time, I hope you will learn to do these things yourself,” she explained, in a melodic voice. “Thoughts guide our actions. By changing your thoughts, you can unlearn negative behaviors.”

I tilted my head. “But that’s the problem. You can’t control your thoughts.”

“Well, not with that attitude. You didn’t develop your thinking patterns overnight,” Sara responded. “It takes time, effort, and understanding to make a self-adjustment. Mind if I ask you a few questions, before we begin the simulation?”

“Go for it.”

“When was the first time you encountered a predator?”

I failed to see the relevance of the question, but I decided to humor the human. If she thought delving into the origins of predator phobia would further her understanding, it wouldn’t hurt to play along. The more background info she had on me, the better subject I would be.

You saw the Arxur on TV, but that doesn’t really count. Mother tried to shield us from those atrocities, I recalled.

Encounters with predators were uncommon on Venlil Prime, though occasionally, one slipped through the cracks. Teams of investigators in armored vehicles would travel out to the site, scorching any area with evidence of a hunter’s presence. There was no way we would leave them alive to reproduce and terrorize our settlements. Extermination officer was an occupation that paid well, but all the money in the world wouldn’t be enticing enough for me.

“My parents took me for a walk in the local pasture, and there was a dead rodent on the sidewalk. Lots of blood. There were larvae all over it; news cameras turned up within minutes.” A shudder rippled down my spine at the memory. “The anchors said a predator might be on the loose. The entire neighborhood was placed on a curfew by local police. Schools were closed indefinitely.”

Tyler couldn’t hear the other end of the conversation, but he shot me a baffled look. The human’s eyebrow arched up his forehead, as though he couldn’t believe what he was hearing. I think the words he mouthed were, What the fuck?

“Tell me more about that. Did they find out what happened to the dead animal?” Sara inquired.

I gritted my teeth. “It died of natural causes, according to the autopsy. Everyone was relieved that there was no imminent threat. But that was the week I learned about food chains…and our place on it.”

“How did that make you feel?”

“Scared. Powerless. I just couldn’t believe there were animals that based their existence on k-killing.”

“I can tell this is difficult for you, Slanek. If I may, what conclusions did your childhood self reach about predators?”

“Predators had to be cruel and unfeeling, to be able to stomach such violence. To eat that rotting corpse I saw.”

“The Arxur must have cemented those beliefs. I take it that was your initial feeling toward humans?”

A horrified gasp came from my chest, as I realized what I just said about predators. It had slipped my mind that I was talking to one, while I was focusing on the emotional residue of that experience. There was the thoughtlessness Marcel teased me over.

“I’m sorry, that was too honest. I didn’t mean to say you’re—” I squeaked.

“Relax. I’m not offended.” Sara’s voice was reserved and soothing, like the rustle of leaves in the wind. “I want you to be transparent with me; especially about how humans make you feel.”

“I don’t like to think about humans being predators. It’s jarring to equate you with, uh…”

“The animal in the field. With eating ‘rotting corpses.’”

“Yes.”

The scientist was silent on the other end of the headset, and I caught some light scraping sounds. She must be taking notes from what I was telling her. I hoped I hadn’t said too much; the humans wouldn’t admit they were offended, even if they were.

“You did great, Slanek. Thank you for sharing that with me. What I am going to ask of you now, is to try to put yourself in the predator’s shoes,” she said. “Come up with as many reasons why an animal might choose to hunt as you can: beyond being cruel, violent, and unfeeling. We’ll talk about it at tomorrow’s session.”

I focused my eyes on the floor, ignoring Tyler’s inquisitive stare. Did flesh taste so good that it was addictive? It was tough to think of a single other allure to predation, other than biological impulse.

Even with humans, I assumed they had those aspects within them due to their brutal hunting methods. The difference was that I believed they had another side, and that there were enough positive attributes to outweigh the repugnant ones. Besides, they found a way to sate their cravings without harming other creatures.

Maybe that’s something I should ask Marcel. He might know the answers Sara is looking for.

I breathed a weary sigh. “I don’t know if I can do that, but I’ll try.”

“Good. Now, we’re going to start your mission. The goal of this exercise is to stop any hostile ships from reaching orbital range of Earth. I’ll be here for guidance as needed.”

The screens glowed to life, and Tyler clenched his fist around the firing trigger. The image of Earth in the background was hyperrealistic, down to the orange glow dotting the continents. Swirling clouds idled across the oceans, and the inky backdrop framed the planet in serene radiance. It was a breathtaking sight, even in a simulation.

I searched for enemy contacts on sensor data. Craning my neck, I tried to get a visual on a fast-approaching vessel from our left. The blinders were inhibiting my sight line, so it was difficult to ground myself. At least it rendered me impervious to the virtual explosions and conflict taking place in the distance.

My breath hitched in my throat, as a plasma beam sailed meters from our hull. This felt too real and dangerous. The stress of decision-making was enough to make panic seep in. I was frozen as usual; what was I supposed to do? I couldn’t even remember how to engage the targeting systems.

Nonetheless, inaction was unacceptable. My trembling paw slammed the steering column and veered the ship toward the hostile. My diminished vision blurred; my heart was pounding so hard that it felt like an earthquake in my chest. Every instinct declared that facing an aggressive foe was too perilous.

I feel like I’m going to die. Like I’m flying into my doom…and it’s not even real.

Meanwhile, Tyler was impossibly collected, as he aligned kinetic munitions with the target. How could humans push through the chemical fog with such ease? It was as though their instincts compelled them to run headlong toward danger, rather than gallop to safety.

“Slanek, deep breaths. Count to five as you inhale, then count to five as you exhale,” Sara’s voice growled.

I took a few wheezing breaths, attempting to comply with her orders. Through the lightheadedness, I could see the opposing craft enlarging in the viewport. A horrified gasp escaped before I could contain it; this was all happening so quickly. There was no time to think.

Everything on screen froze, including the hostile that was just magnified. I slumped my shoulders in shame; the humans were going to can the experiment on day one. I was a hopeless cause. Helping them was never going to be within my capability, no matter how much I wanted it to be.

“Talk to me!” The scientist’s voice sounded urgent over the headset, which jolted me out of my daze. “Rate your fear on a scale of 1 to 10, with 10 being the worst you’ve ever felt.”

I blinked in confusion. “Um…7?”

“We can work with that. Everything is going to be fine. This feeling will pass,” Sara said. “What thoughts went through your mind, as you started to feel afraid?”

“I just… I know I can’t do this. I’m not a fighter, and I never will be. My instincts can’t handle stress or danger.”

“What I’m hearing is that you don’t feel that you can control your emotions. You’ve decided it’s not possible already.”

“Humans are special. I have to face what I am.”

“What you are is a good pilot. Remember, the enemy is just as vulnerable as you.”

“It d-doesn’t feel that way. Never does.”

“Focus on your target and get the shot off. Everything else doesn’t matter; you can complete that one thing. One step at a time.”

Squeezing my eyes shut, I allowed my breathing to fall back into a calm rhythm. It was within my power to press a few buttons, wasn’t it? There had to be a way to override my instincts, the way the humans kept their aggression in check. Marcel had squared off against nine Arxur vessels in an inferior ship, and we survived. This was nothing.

“Hey, we can do this, Slanek. You’re not alone here. Remember that!” Tyler growled.

I flicked my ears in appreciation. The sandy-haired human didn’t have much heart after learning Earth’s insurmountable odds, but he was still trying to be supportive. Bravery felt a little less difficult, knowing that fearless predators had my back. Humans were survivors, and that meant I was in good company.

You’re not doing this by yourself. You’re on the predators’ side; not the Krakotl. They’re the ones who should be afraid.

I believed in humanity’s strength, even if I was uncertain of my own. Newfound determination swelled in my veins as the simulation resumed. The blinders were there for the purpose of directing my attention to a single task. It was a matter of just acting, and not thinking at all.

The opposing ship barreled toward us, racing closer to Earth. My aviation knowledge kicked in, and I verified the target on sensors. All I contemplated was the intake of my breathing, while my claw jammed down on the missile switch. Projectiles homed in on the sleek bomber, tracking its evasion attempts.

My human partner sent a flurry of kinetics close behind. It was prudent to take advantage of any disruption to shields. The missiles rocked the imaginary opponent, and Tyler’s well-timed rounds tore through its armor. The seamless teamwork was invigorating, for a moment. The predator bared his teeth at the thrill, and I almost mimicked him.

Instead of allowing the follow-up options to overwhelm me, I asked myself what humans would do. They would go for the kill, and not give the enemy any recovery time. Persistence hunting taught them how to be relentless; maybe I could learn from that cruelty as well.

“Leave my friends alone!” I hissed to the screen. It was easy to channel my outrage at the unprovoked assault on Earth. “Nobody hurts my herd, ever again.”

I navigated the ship nearer to our nemesis. My anger at injustice was warring with the voice that told me to turn back. The resolute snarl on Tyler’s face was enough to keep my paw on the accelerator. Just this once, I wanted to be the predator; to pounce on a weakened enemy.

My heart was racing, while I unloaded a devastating salvo into their flanks. Orange tendrils burst from its metallic shell, and damned the fictitious crew to the vacuum. The simulation faded back to white, with a ‘mission success’ declaration.

“You did it!!” Tyler cheered, forcing a grin. “That was all you, Slanek.”

I leapt up from the pilot’s seat, wagging my tail. As the Federation often reminded us, Venlil weren’t supposed to have a fighting bone in our bodies. How had I managed to kill an enemy…and emulate Terran intensity? Had the humans changed me?

An answer to Sara’s earlier question popped into my mind. An animal might choose to be a predator, because it refined their species into something stronger. Hunting mandated discipline, and lessened the brunt of fearful instincts. Maybe it was empowering to be the one dealing the damage.

Sara cleared her throat. “I told you that you were a good pilot. That exercise should give you hope for what we can accomplish.”

“But it was only one ship, guys,” I pointed out. “That’s nothing compared to the Krakotl invasion.”

“We’re going to increase the duration and number of enemies every day. You’ll be taking on an army in no time.”

The exhilaration of success fizzled out, as I processed that daunting prospect. The scientist sounded hellbent on pushing me well past my instincts’ limit, when all was said and done. Every day was going to be more of a struggle than the next. If nothing else though, her questioning had forced me to consider my fears in a new light.

“Oh buddy, I’m so proud of you.” Marcel must have snagged the microphone. His rumbling voice fluttered into my ears. “You’re going to turn those birds to space feathers. They’ll never see it coming.”

“Thanks, uh, but…I don’t know about that.”

He chuckled. “You’re stronger than you think you are. The attacking skills are there, as we all saw. You nailed that fucker, even with Tyler button mashing and getting in your way.”

This time, the tall copilot leaned close enough to hear the headset chatter. He threw up his hands in exasperation, then turned his glare at me for giggling. There was hilarity in the expression that once would’ve had me on the floor, begging not to be eaten. I knew humans well enough to recognize the difference between jest and malice.

Tyler waved a fist at the camera. “Slanek and I are gonna win this war, while you’re still on your ass eating Doritos.”

“Nah, are you kidding, bro? I’ll be up there, stopping you from snacking on too many crayons mid-battle.”

“What can I say? That’s a true predator’s diet.”

I appreciated that my friends were able to make light of a dark situation; that was their method of coping with the unpleasant. There wasn’t a more resilient species in the galaxy. With their example to model, maybe it was possible to mold me into something a little more vicious.

The survival of these alien predators was what was important, I reminded myself. My progression was a secondary objective that would complement Terran aims. If Earth was to be lost, the spiteful defenders would take as many enemies with them as possible. No battle waged against humans was ever as easy as it looked on paper.

Regardless, I had faith the Venlil Republic wouldn’t hang our allies out to dry.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 51
Memory transcription subject:

Captain Kalsim,
Krakotl Alliance Command

Date [standardized human time]:
October 17, 2136

Dry air buffeted my face, as we disembarked amidst tall grass. The shuttle crash was bound to attract attention from the humans. I imagined this place would be swarming with troops, if it was anywhere near a military base. We had no idea where we were, or how many predators were in the area.

My breaths were strained as the three of us hauled Thyon's body across a savanna. Sparse trees dotted the vast plain, and a few beasts roamed the landscape. None of the orange predators zeroed in on us, but they were definitely something to avoid. I couldn't see any bipedal human shapes, but it was a matter of time before we ran into one.

It's much easier to fly than to walk. We need to find some place to leave Thyon. A place to shelter…and to sleep would be nice.

On our left, a bank of clay and sediment led down to a small pond. I was thirsty, but given that there were more bright-colored predators bathing in it, I'd stick to our rations. With how tired I was, I didn't feel up to exterminating any threats now.

"This place is infested with predators. Only a few artificial structures," Zarn grunted.

I studied the doctor's grimace. "I don't think humans cull their predator population at all. This is what happens when you don't have extermination officers."

"Can you imagine living on a planet like this? What an uncivilized world."

This alien hellscape could be host to all kinds of nightmarish murder-beasts. The vicious creatures around us had lean, nimble forms, and fangs that put the sapient primates to shame. Most humans were unlikely to set up shop in predator-territory. It could be a very long walk to civilization, from this wilderness.

After a brief pause, we began the laborious trek toward the far-off tree line. The expanse seemed to stretch for kilometers, with no sign of the nearest settlement. This region's heat was punishing, making me want to collapse in a puddle. No wonder the humans' fur had evolved away.

"We need to put this dead weight down. This Farsul intruder is going to get us all killed!" Jala spat.

I glared at her. "I don't leave my crew members to die. There's wild monstrosities everywhere, and the humans could do anything if they stumble across him."

"So what? The rations would be better spent on people who can walk and fight."

"Lives are not trading chips, Jala. Haven't you killed enough people today? I'll leave Thyon when there's an appropriate spot, hidden and secure."

A cave, or any kind of cover, would be a welcome sight. There was no locale devoid of predators to stash Thyon. Leaving him in the open, to be gnawed on by a cast of beasts, wasn't an option. It was unclear how much energy any of us had left; our flock might have to camp among the demons soon.

I was relieved to spot a breaking point in the grass. There was an uneven dirt path, which had faint vehicle marks in its silt. That meant Terrans did stray to this region, from the safety of a metal cage. At least we could communicate with human predators; an isolated one could be threatened into giving us supplies or shelter.

Zarn looked to me with watering eyes. "Kalsim…captain…"

The Takkan doctor heaved some strained breaths, and placed Thyon on the ground. He bent over, trying to catch his breath. Fear was swelling in his amber gaze. The realization that we were stuck on Earth, amidst livid humans, was settling in.

"Humans have definitely visited this place." Jala scanned the red arch in front of us, with the prototype visual translator. "The writing says 'Ranthambore Tiger Reserve'…I'm guessing those orange predators are 'Ranthambore tigers?'"

Alarm awakened my senses. "Reserve, you say…like an area set aside for a specific purpose. The humans intended for this predator growth to happen, Jala?"

"I think so."

"That is peculiar. Why would they want rival, stronger hunters on the loose?"

Even the sociopath seemed stumped by my question. Such animals were not conducive to modern living. Maybe the humans wanted whatever prey the tigers prioritized for themselves, and snatched it away from them once the hard work was finished.

It didn't make sense. There were much easier ways to feed their hunger, than by stealing from ferocious fiends. I was certain a species with guns could hunt without assistance.

"They like the chaos and the violence," Zarn panted. "This human war tribe could want to keep out dangerous visitors, especially their own kind. We might be in the most vicious nation on the planet!"

I didn't know what the truth was, but I was going to assume it wasn't anywhere close to that. The doctor lacked crucial understanding about humans. Their society was too structured for a state entity to stoke chaos intentionally. It must be something more philosophical in nature.

Given how many galactic religions were organized against predators, it could be that Terrans saw hunters as deities. The Krakotl's farming goddess, Inatala, brought plants to the universe to feed her children. Predators were considered a perversion of her natural order, who turned to Maltos, the god of violence, out of greed. Our reality was the eternal struggle of good and evil.

I strayed from the faith once I became an extermination officer. The priesthood had a way of twisting the goddess' teachings; none of it matched with their written beliefs. Maltos wasn't an inhibitor of empathy, but merely an agent of destruction. We had seen that predators were violent and greedy, while not without some positive qualities.

"I think this is some kind of worship center," I decided. "Maybe somewhere to pray surrounded by carnage, for hunting success. Or for the expansion of war."

Jala chuckled. "A religion devoted to bloodshed? How interesting."

"It is interesting, actually. This is why I wanted to preserve their culture…because we understand their kind so little. We've become enthralled with violence and killing ourselves, in trying to be pure."

The doctor curled his lip. "A brutal race doesn't deserve any legacy for their culture. I'm enthralled with the punishment of the wicked, not killing itself."

"Your motives are rich with hatred. It poisons you," I hissed. "Now, let's get moving…before the sun finishes setting."

The group hobbled away from the reserve in uneasy silence. There was no telling where the road led, or what animalistic carnage lie ahead. A more spiritual Krakotl would see this as a temptation by Inatala. I had never intended to get up-close-and-personal with human territory; our mission was supposed to be impassive. Distant.

This is a test to my soul, regardless of divine presence. We must face Earth's horrors, without surrendering our values.

As we progressed past a clump of trees, my hearing detected a faint sniffling. It was accompanied by sporadic gasps, so I figured it must be a predator crying. Jala cued in on the sound as well, and drew her sidearm. The female Krakotl looked eager to kill or mock the beast.

Sympathy tugged at my heart, and perhaps a bit of regret. If a human was mourning the devastation we caused, what right did we have to disturb it? Something told me I was outvoted though, so I raised my weapon. The flesh-eaters were too dangerous to leave on the prowl, while we were out in the open. If a single extermination was necessary to safeguard my people, so be it.

I gestured to set the injured Farsul on the grass. "Zarn, watch over Thyon, and alert us if any other predators are approaching."

"I can't wait to see your extermination skills in action," the doctor chuckled.

Jala clicked her beak. "His skills? Kalsim is soft on the humans. But don't worry, I'm going to crack its skull.

"I expect you to be as silent as possible. We don't want it to know we're there, until we have it cornered. Also, let me ascertain some information before you off it."

"What if I want to scare it?" the sociopath drawled.

"The human is not in a stable state of mind now. It could go into a fit of rage on a whim. Let's not push our luck; we just need its shelter."

The female Krakotl curled her neck in disdain, but took cautious hops forward. My feet glided across the leaves, and I took care to avoid any twigs. A fabric dome, supported by stakes in the earth, was established amidst a clearing. A single human was stretched out on a blanket; it appeared to be watching videos on a handheld device.

Terror swelled in my chest, as my instincts urged me not to approach. The feeling subsided upon drawing closer; secondary observations swayed my emotions. This primate was of a lesser stature than indicated in Noah's data dump. Its skin seemed untouched by aging, and its register lacked the booming growl of males we had spoken to.

If I had to hazard a guess, this human was an adolescent. Perhaps it was crying because it lost its parents; that would explain why it was alone, and had wandered to predator-infested territory. My thoughts began racing with unpleasant images. It took a great deal of effort to push them away.

I stopped a few paces from its blanket. "Put the electronic device down, and slide it to me. Don't even try to alert any…fellow beasts."

The human startled, and pointed its tear-stained eyes at me. Its lips parted with alarm; it flung the device toward me like it burned to the touch. Video footage was still playing on the screen, as predator anchors described the loss of life in a city called Bengaluru. I wondered if that was the kid's home.

"P-please, take whatever you want. Just leave me alone," it whined.

That begging was rather unbecoming of a predator. Maybe it hadn't become desensitized to bloodshed yet. I focused my gun barrel, careful not to keep my grip too close to the trigger.

"We just want to talk," I lied. "What's your name?"

The beast swallowed. "Arjun."

"And your age? You don't look like a human adult."

"I'm 12. Uh, we're not grown-ups 'til we turn 18."

Jala traced her gun barrel across its furless chin, snickering as it shied away. The fear in its gaze twisted my heart; the little beast still had years left of adolescence. It looked harmless, helpless, even. I knew that was deceiving, but it still had an effect.

Little predators become big predators, and reproduce exponentially, my mentor's voice said in my head.

I stared at the shaking primate. "Hey, eyes on me, Arjun. Why are you out here?"

"Dad thought it was a good place to hide. He said you wouldn't target the parks first," Arjun croaked. "If this is the end of the world…we could spend the last day outdoors. Together."

"Alright. I know humans care for their children. Where is your father now?"

"My, uh—my dad is a wildlife photographer. He wanted to get some animal shots with the space battle overhead. It'd be a damn good picture, if we…"

"If you survive."

The predator bobbed its head emphatically, and more tears streamed down its face. The kid's distress was apparent. It would be merciful if I limited the scope of my questions. I didn't want to prolong its suffering; Jala couldn't be allowed to botch the job or make a mess.

Gosh, what if there was a way to curb a human's full-grown instincts? Pulling the trigger on Arjun…that extermination broke my heart already. It would grow into something terrible, but now, it was innocent. It wanted its father.

I struggled to steady my voice. "You're doing great. Can you just tell me what this place is? We were curious about the predatory 'wildlife.'"

"National parks are like an animal sanctuary. We preserve species that are threatened, or have lost their natural habitats."

"Why?! Those orange…tigers are menaces. They'd eat children like you!"

"Tigers don't bother you unless you bother them. They're majestic animals. Lots of people tour this place, and there's resorts, campsites, hiking..."

Disbelief flooded my veins, at the idea that humans wanted to stay in such a dangerous venue. To think that the locals went out of their way to preserve monsters! Arjun's tone had been reverent, but not religious. Did predators find thrills in challenging superior counterparts?

I cleared my throat. "Thanks. That's all we need."

"Finally, the talking is over. So I can kill it?" Jala trilled.

"Er, well, it—"

Its binocular eyes pleaded with me. "No! I helped you."

I stared at the colorful leaves on the ground, avoiding its gaze. The reds and oranges reminded me of a raging inferno, sparking across a pool of gasoline. The little pups squealed through it all, and their frail silhouettes writhed in agony. I felt like I was watching my handiwork from the truck bed again.

When they looked at you with those big eyes, you wanted to help. But you didn't. You wouldn't.

I couldn't help but feel that our mission had been wrong. The thoughts of how the predators tugged at my talons, playfully, was still a vibrant memory. Looking at Arjun, it was impossible not to recall that first extermination. Younglings didn't deserve merciless death.

"Captain Kalsim?" Jala squawked.

I blinked. "Leave the predator alive. It's not a threat."

"Not a threat?" Zarn's voice made me startle, as I found him looming over my shoulder. "It's an offshoot of flesh-eating barbarians. What kind of extermination officer are you?"

"Doctor, I told you to wait with Thyon!"

"Well, I was worried you'd do exactly this, predator-lover. Jala, you don't have to listen to him. Kill that thing!"

Arjun was curled up into a ball, shielding its head with an elbow. The female Krakotl's eyes twitched, and I could sense her temptation. I had to reel in the rebellious sadists, before I lost control. Admitting my actions were borne from sympathy would be suicide.

"I'm no predator lover! How dare you?" I roared, shoving my beak in Zarn's face. "I'm a skilled extermination officer, while you're someone who sits on the sidelines. Talk is easy."

The doctor stiffened. "You just said—"

"That thing is the only bargaining chip we have. Humans value their children, so keeping it as a prisoner is the logical choice. Maybe we can make them trade us a spaceship. Food. Medicine, you arrogant fool!"

The Takkan gulped nervously, and slunk back a few steps. He stole a glance at Arjun, before swishing his tail in defeat. Jala also scrutinized my enraged form. I met her stare for several seconds, goading her on.

She lowered her weapon. "Using their kids against them. As a shield, maybe! I like it."

"I knew you would." I exhaled a silent breath of relief, and turned to the doctor. "Sedate this human, Zarn, like you did with Marcel. Adjust for weight. I need sleep, and I can't watch a ravenous predator."

The Takkan nodded, and filled a syringe with a light sedative dose. I watched which vial he grabbed, making sure he wasn't loading it with poison. The physician handed it over to me for administration. A quick jab plunged the needle into the human's neck; hopefully it was only a light pinch.

It should knock Arjun out for a few hours. When I was rested and able to think again, I would be able to deal with the predator. There was no telling how long it would act obedient.

The greater challenge would be restraining my companions from tormenting the child. We'd failed to eradicate the Earthlings, and its continued survival was simply an admission of failure. There was no reason for a stranded crew to dole out needless death.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 60
Memory transcription subject:

Captain Sovlin,
Federation Fleet Command

Date [standardized human time]:
October 20, 2136

The feeling of teeth in my shoulder produced a sharp pain. The joint was about ripped from the socket, as I was dragged across the asphalt. I wriggled in the predator's jaws, punching its snout to release its grip. The stabbing of my long claws drew blood, and it tossed me onto the ground with a shake of its head. My body slammed against our metallic shuttle; all I could see was stars.

The pounding of my heart was a nauseating experience. This must be what my family felt as they were toyed with, before being turned into a screaming meal. I couldn't give these Arxur cattle fiends the satisfaction of screaming or crying. Maybe it was worth some sort of plea, to get them to spare the Harchen.

The sole option that crossed my mind was to invoke the humans. They were the only ones the grays had a remote respect for. If the primates had directed the Arxur Dominion to this vulnerable civilian populace, perhaps they would abandon anything the Terrans allegedly claimed.

"S-stop!" I squealed. "I'm a human slave, on a mission to expose t-the Federation's lies. When they killed your c-cattle like you say...they w-want...want to get t-the details for you!"

To my amazement, the gray paused in its stalking position. "The humans did claim the Gojid homeworld, and we recognized their stake. I can smell them on your fur. But where are our fellow predators, if you're their property? They wouldn't set you free."

"T-they have my family," I sobbed, with fake despondency. "I'll do whatever they want...even if it's harmful to the Federation!"

Confusion flashed in Cilany's eyes. The Harchen reporter knew my family was long-deceased, so that lie wouldn't fool her. I didn't understand why the prey reptiles hadn't made a run for it yet. There were no good options, but stalling the Arxur gave them a small window of escape.

The bloodied predator flashed a snarl. "Clever. But why are you on this world? With those who attacked Earth?"

"These Harchen are p-priority assets for the humans. I don't ask questions...but I'm s-sure it's for a good reason. Let us leave, please."

The grays conferred for a moment, and inspected a smoking section of the shuttle hood. I couldn't believe they were listening to any of my bullshit. There was a brief flicker of hope, that we might fall under Terran immunity. Plopping myself upright, I nursed the wounded arm with a ginger touch.

Talking to them is revolting, but the Arxur just confirmed that this assault is retaliation for Earth. Cilany was right. What have the humans done?!

"We'll let you leave as a token of good faith, slave. We mangled your engine though, so you'll need to find another way off world," the Arxur spokes-monster decided. "But the Harchen stay. I think you are disobeying your orders, to save our enemies."

The prey reptiles scampered back into the stairwell, only to find themselves blocked by a laughing gray. A single beast must've landed on the roof, cutting off any escape. They intended to flush the Harchen out into the street, one way or another. My eyes widened in horror, as the grays herded them into a cage.

"Stop! T-the humans want these four as media tools, really," I pleaded.

The vicious predator snorted. "The humans want all of them dead. On that matter, it just so happens our interests align."

I wondered whether the Terrans would enjoy the sight of the panicked Harchen reporters, sealed together in a degrading heap. My imprisoners would despise this raid, wouldn't they? The cage door slammed shut, and the Arxur gestured for me to scurry off. It would be easy to save myself, but I couldn't watch cattle be hauled away.

My gaze darted over to my gun, which had fallen into the dirt. Odds were, I could only get off a shot or two, before the grays mowed me down with prejudice. I had to try something to rescue these Harchen, no matter how suicidal. It was a matter of waiting for the Arxur to lose focus, and accepting that I was about to die.

"Is there a problem?" a throaty snarl echoed from my right.

Carlos stomped across the road, clad head-to-toe in protective pelts. A flashlight was mounted to his helmet, and his binocular eyes hid behind a glass visor. A massive gun rested across his muscular forearm. I was never so elated to see a flesh-eating predator in my life.

But what the hell is my guard doing here? I don't even know that he won't leave the Harchen to their fate. Or worse, laugh about it.

The human stopped a few paces from the Arxur posse, and crossed his arms in a formidable stance. The talkative gray, who must be the unit leader, sized up the omnivore. It narrowed its eyes with blazing ferocity, challenging Carlos' will. I didn't know how the UN soldier faced that stare.

The reptilian predator bared its fangs. "Your slave wants to help these Harchen escape. It is using its subjugation as a cover, claiming this is done on your orders."

Carlos' pupils flicked to the cramped cage. "You heard Sovlin and his true orders correctly; he's an obedient servant. We want to send a message to the Federation, and these are the right individuals for the job. Simple."

A relieved sigh escaped my lips. I was grateful that the human backed me up, after I deviated our flight path to recruit Terran enemies. He might take these Harchen prisoner or even execute them, but he wouldn't eat them. His kind wasn't like the grays. At worst, I could reason with him, and make sense of the questionable things he might do.

"Why can't you find another 'pet?'" the gray hissed. "We did all the work, and we claimed this batch. These prey are of no particular importance...no different than thousands like them, with the same qualifications!"

Carlos shuffled closer. "Our personnel selections are made off of data, simulations, and the best strategic minds on Earth. Are you questioning our judgment?!"

"Yes. I am."

"Say it again, you fucking coward!"

"I am questioning the judgment of weak, naïve primitives. You haven't a clue what you're doing, or what it means to survive in this galaxy!"

The human rose up on his toes, and pressed his slender nose inches from the Arxur's maw. The gray straightened, as Carlos tried to match its height. It breathed a deafening snarl at the UN soldier, but he wouldn't back down. Defiance glowed in the primate's eyes, despite being outclassed.

"I could snap your puny neck with a single bite!" the Arxur roared.

Carlos jabbed his gun barrel into its stomach. "And I could blow your intestines apart, with a single finger. But we're on the same side, so why don't we work this out another way?"

"Hmmph. A contest of strength. You fight me one-on-one, without those overcompensating weapons of yours. If you win, you can have these Harchen."

"I'm game, if you'll agree not to bite. Unless you think you're too weak to fight without...overcompensating fangs?"

"Oh, let's do this. I'm going to beat the snot out of you, human!"

The Terran soldier backed away, and tucked his rifle off to the side. He raised his clawless paws in front of his face, forming white-knuckled fists. What was to stop the gray from executing him, now that he was disarmed? Luckily for Carlos, it was itching to release its aggression.

The Arxur lunged at the human with a blunt swipe, which was barely dodged. It lashed out with a tail sweep, knocking the guard off his feet. The monster whirled around with quick jabs, which the primate blocked with an elbow. Carlos rolled out of the way, and scrambled back to a standing position. He looked slow and toothless compared to the reptilian, not managing a single swing of his own.

Carlos scurried backward, and tried to deflect the oncoming barrage. Sweat glistened on his olive skin; tears showed in his artificial pelts. The Arxur aimed a jab at his abdomen, but the human danced away on nimble feet. While he was focused on the claws, it swung its snout at him with force. The truncated maw nailed the guard right in the chest, and sent him flying backward.

The poor guy is getting his ass handed to him. Why did he think this was a good idea to negotiate? Damn humans and their aggression.

Carlos sucked in a wheezing breath, but hopped back to his paws. The gray charged at him once more, and the human pummeled it in the nostrils. It shrugged off the punch with a snort. The UN guard attempted to deliver a kick, but the reptilian caught his frail leg. It snickered as the human flailed, hopping on one leg.

"This isn't even a fight." The Arxur tugged the primate's ankle, and knocked him onto his rump. It dragged him through the dirt for several paces. "We may treat you like equals, but you don't make demands of us. You don't intimidate anyone."

Carlos kicked its clasped paw with his other leg, wriggling free. "You...haven't...beaten..."

"Stay down, weakling. I've kicked the shit out of you. Know when to admit defeat; basic humility would do you good."

The human began to rise, only to be nailed across the mouth by a tail lash. Crimson blood bubbled on his lip, and he spit the liquid into the dirt. He rolled onto his back, watching as the Arxur gloated in its victory. His hand darted to his head, wrenching the flashlight off his headgear. He shone it inches from its left pupil.

The Arxur shrieked as the brightness flooded its gaze, blinking. Carlos popped back up on wobbly legs, and staggered in grappling range. The human drove his knee into its stomach, before tackling it with all of his weight. He rolled off to the side, and wrapped an elbow around its neck. The gray struggled to break loose, but its oxygen supply was dwindling.

"Game, set, and match. Tap out," Carlos gurgled.

The gray palmed at the human's elbow with feeble swats, its hideous eyes bulging. Carlos released his grip with a toothy snarl. It coughed several times, caressing its throat. The creature struggled to get back to its feet, and the Terran helped it stand.

"You...cheated," it sputtered. "No weapons."

The UN guard shrugged. "I didn't use a weapon. Just an illumination device."

"You broke the spirit of our sparring, which is cheating to my eyes. You show little respect to your allies, and you're lucky I like irreverence. Take the damn Harchen; it's a whopping four cattle."

The Arxur slunk off with narrowed gazes, as their leader hobbled away. True to their word, the demons left the Harchen's cage behind. The relief that flooded my veins was indescribable, though my hammering heart wouldn't pipe down. I raced over to the human, and flung my arms around him with choking sobs.

Carlos stiffened, and pulled my paws off him. "Uh, yeah. Don't do that, man."

"S-sorry. I'm just really grateful for your help," I muttered. "What are you doing here?"

"Keeping an eye on you, obviously. We were concerned about your little pit stop, and followed you down here. I would appreciate if you'd not go around calling yourself a slave in the future."

"It was improvisation. Can't argue with results."

"Speaking of improvisation, you put the whole mission at risk with this little stunt. The fuck were you thinking?!"

"It was supposed to be a brief, easy trip. I wanted someone I knew, a friend, on the team. I've dealt with enough people who hate me in recent weeks."

"Whatever. Let's get your friends out of there. Hope they understand we're the only ride out. If they run off, I'm not going to stop the grays from nabbing them next time."

The human unclasped the cage door, and watched as the Harchen tumbled out. Cilany inspected the predator with petrified eyes. Her comrades seemed repulsed by Carlos' lumbering form too, squealing as they returned his stare. The journalists' eyes darted to the side, as though they wanted to run.

"D-did you tell the Arxur to attack us?" Cilany blurted.

Carlos narrowed his eyes. "I don't know; that's above my clearance level. If we did, it was likely to deter your forces from attacking us. The UN wouldn't want this to happen."

I slumped my shoulders. "Not even people like Samantha? Wouldn't she want the Harchen to feel the same losses as Earth?"

An indignant cough came from an abandoned vehicle behind us. Upon closer inspection, the female human was stretched out behind cover. A thin rifle barrel with a glass ornament was propped on the ground. She must've been monitoring the interaction the entire time, and watching Carlos' back in case his confrontation went awry.

"I don't believe people deserve to die for what they are. That's the Federation," she growled. "If an individual renounces their government, I'm sure Earth would welcome them with open arms. Now the ones responsible, complicit, or indifferent—"

Carlos cleared his throat. "We parked a few blocks away. Somewhere we wouldn't be visible to the whole world, Sovlin. Stick close guys, and follow us."

The human retraced his route with delicate bootsteps. His rifle was ready if any Arxur crawled out of the woodwork, and Samantha fell in at his side. The predator guards forged the path for the Harchen journalists, ignoring their hesitance. It was remarkable to see the vengeful primates, aiding a species that partook in the attack days prior.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 74
Memory transcription subject:

Governor Tarva of the Venlil Republic
Venlil Republic

Date [standardized human time]:
November 28, 2136

It shouldn't have been complicated for species to denounce the Federation's actions. The issue was that some saw the gene rewrites as merciful, and couldn't pinpoint the moral conundrum. The United Nations opened their doors to former omnivores, launching genetic research and sharing biology lessons. As the Venlil always did, we placed our full support behind the predators' actions.

Launching the lab-grown meat initiative proved easy, with some quick thinking from Terran diplomats. Human refugees worked the operation, and passed it off as a desperate attempt to feed Earth. It was announced later that the predators were selflessly handing over their food supply, in a deal they brokered with the Arxur. I wasn't involved at all, so the political blowback might pass over me.

If this exchange goes smoothly, humanity will be able to say that they rescued millions of Venlil.

Using frozen cell samples from Earth, we'd churned up enough meat for the trade. It was a sickening process, but I reminded myself of the cause. The Terrans facilitated the release of Arxur prisoners from the cradle as well; our side of the bargain was upheld. I was stuck waiting anxiously for the results, with Noah and Sara.

Hospitals across the habitable zone were prepping for the influx of patients. Many humans volunteered to help the rescued Venlil, but they were ordered to wear full concealment gear at all times. We didn't want the former cattle assuming they were transferred from one predator's custody to another.

Sara squeezed my shoulders reassuringly. "Your people will be here any minute. We have no reason to assume that Isif will betray us."

"I don't know about trusting an Arxur," Noah growled. "True herbivores like the Venlil must have a lower status than ever, with the recent news. The Dominion could decree that they belong as cattle."

I took a shuddering breath. "Noah is right. Why hasn't General Kam communicated anything? Did the grays attack us?"

With uncanny timing, my holopad buzzed in my grip. It appeared to be the Venlil military frequency, with the right encryption and validations. My prosthetic tail bunched up with anticipation, and I tried for a placid expression. News of a successful rescue would be a welcome sound.

The face that flickered onto the vid screen was no Venlil though. It was the scaly visage of an Arxur, with slit pupils directed on camera. Fear rippled through my veins; I wondered why we were being contacted by a reptilian. It took a substantial effort to soothe myself, reminding my brain that the predator couldn't attack through a holopad. Once I got my bearings, I used a chipped tooth to identify the creature as Isif.

"C-chief Hunter?" My voice sounded more like a question, but I managed to gasp out the words. "Was there something wrong with the parcel? T-the humans meted out the allot—"

The Arxur leaned back. "No, everything went smoothly. The liberated cattle were sent to an abandoned colony, where your people picked them up. Your transports are approaching Venlil Prime now, so I would make preparations."

"Okay…good. How did you access this c-channel? And why?"

"Study and observation. Venlil ships have poor security protocol. I mean no insult, it's a simple fact. Anyways, I wished to thank you for your cooperation."

The reptilian growled with discomfort, avoiding eye contact. It was clear he'd never extended gratitude before. Assuming he spoke the truth, it was a relief to hear that everything had gone according to plan. I was nervous about announcing the result to the public; the humans needed to dress the news up with a meticulous brush.

"I j-just wanted…to free my people. No sapient creature deserves to live like that," I stuttered.

Isif curled his lip. "I have never liked what we do. The news from Aafa, you know what I'm referring to, is a gut punch. Some in the Dominion are moving the goalposts to what qualifies as a predator, but not everyone is alright with eating 'true sapients.' Not my words."

"You don't seem torn up about your diet."

"I already believed that we were eating 'true sapients', Governor. I must dissociate myself from such matters. When there is no choice, responsibility cannot be assigned. It did surprise me that the Arxur are not the first victims…but it does not impact my judgment."

"Victims? The Arxur?"

"One can be both a victim and an oppressor. Your kind, my kind, we are alike in that way. Life is complex."

The Arxur scanned the camera frame, noting the humans in the background. Outrage flashed in his eyes, as he saw the obfuscating gear. Nobody forced Noah and Sara to hide; the United Nations agreed that freed cattle wouldn't befriend predators. They chose to help the traumatized souls despite those hurdles.

"I confess, I had another reason for this call. Secretary-General Zhao is not a man of words," Isif growled. "I knew if I contacted Tarva, I could cut through the red tape. Get on the line with UN diplomats, yes?"

Sara shrugged. "I'm a scientist, who happened to be on the first contact team. My expertise is biology and environmental science, not politics."

"I'm the Venlil ambassador, but only because I led the first contact mission. No one expected to chat with extraterrestrial life. I'm not trained for this either," Noah agreed.

The Arxur lashed his tail. "Noah and Sara…I know of you both, and I do not care about your experience levels. Humanity's handling of the subjugated worlds is shaving scales back on Wriss, not in a good way. Claiming Tilfish territory as your jurisdiction, and demanding that we stand down?"

"The Tilfish surrendered to us," Noah retorted. "The Arxur shouldn't be attacking anyone on our side."

The Chief Hunter flared his nostrils, and threw a sideways glance at me for support. I offered a submissive tail swish. The last thing I wanted was to get involved in a dispute between humanity and the Arxur. That said, I was surprised that the United Nations hadn't allowed their carnivore "friends" to finish the glassing. Sworn enemies weren't worth a deadly confrontation with the grays.

Isif's eyes narrowed to intimidating slits. "Let me restate the issue. I am in charge of only one sector, and by taking Sillis, you pissed off another Chief Hunter. One who's not as forgiving, charming, and flexible as myself."

Noah jabbed a finger at the screen. "Tell that commander conquering a surrendered state is the human way. We do things differently."

"Try again. I need a convincing reason not to ignore your tactless decree. We could finish the orbital campaign, regardless of human presence. For the life of me, I do not see a reason to spare someone who attempted your extinction. We should kill the Tilfish, and the Harchen too."

"Glassing resources, that could be under our control, is just wasteful. Whether you want a planet for food, precious metals, labor, or fuel, conquest keeps everything at your disposal, forever. We are willing to provide the Arxur with compensation…a slice of the pie."

"Not to mention, the Tilfish are former omnivores. The more data we have on the Kolshian's 'cure', the more we can learn about the Arxur's history," Sara chimed in. "We can protect ourselves, in case the Federation attempts to use biological warfare again."

The Chief Hunter scrutinized the humans for several seconds. Earth needed to discover a way to reverse the modifications, if only to safeguard themselves. Helping altered species recover their natural state was a bonus.

"Duly noted. I will convey your desire for a larger, sustainable catch," Isif said. "Take care. Good luck with your rescue, Governor Tarva."

I flicked my new tail. "I l-look forward to our next conversation, C-Chief Hunter Isif."

The Arxur ended the transmission, and I fell back into Noah's strong arms for comfort. With the cattle en route to the hospital, I had to pull myself together quickly. Anything that would shatter the impression of safety had to be concealed. The humans understood this program was about those poor souls…millions of them.

We've never done anything on this scale. Reintegrating these broken Venlil might be more difficult than the exchange part.

Multiple transports docked at the drop-off area of the hospital. Venlil medical professionals barked orders, with an assertiveness that might've come from humans. Even the rescues without visible injuries were brought to a hospital room, for check-ups and therapy. Noah and Sara checked their gear, as we heard gurneys rolling down the hallway.

The Venlil pair that were rolled into our room were a sorry sight; sympathy stabbed at my heart. Their fur was mangy and matted, soot-colored from grime accrual. Both of their eyes were glassy, unresponsive to any stimuli. I could see brands torched into their neck, similar to the script I'd seen on Isif's keyboard.

Noah and Sara rushed to lift each Venlil onto a bed. The first patient screamed at their touch. The predators flinched from the noise, before massaging her neck with calming intent. They hoisted the rescue onto the mattress, affected by her pitiful bleats. The two Terrans fluffed the pillow, and swaddled her in a blanket like a baby.

"You're safe now," Sara whispered. "We're coming right back."

The humans walked to the other rescue assigned to us, a male. They made sure to approach head-on, forgetting that our peripheral vision was expansive. The Venlil shook as they picked him up, digging his claws into Sara's hair. The Terran scientist disregarded the poking sensation, and stroked his pinned-back ears gently.

"This is home, Venlil Prime. We can reunite you with your families." Noah spoke in a higher voice than normal, trying not to growl. "We're going to help you. Can you tell me your names?"

The male rescue shuddered. "One…f-five…"

"No, that is not your name. You're not a number; you're a person. With hopes, dreams, and a future."

"I t-think I…used to b-be called…Glim. Glim."

The Terrans dipped their heads, and Sara scrawled the name on his bedside chart. She retrieved a water glass, tensing as Glim lapped the liquid like an animal. I sprang into action, offering water to the female Venlil. She was rocking back and forth in the blankets, teary eyes sealed shut. It must be overwhelming, to return to society after so long.

I retrieved a brush, and began to untangle her curly fur. It reminded me of how I used to comb my daughter's neck, while her father packed her lunch for school. Forcing that memory away, I got to work on the testy knots. The rescued Venlil went stiff as a board, sinking back into a listless state.

"You can rest if you want. You're safe, really," I murmured.

Her eyes reflected the harsh, artificial light. "I k-know you. V-venlil ambassador T-tarva. I know you…"

"Yes, I am Tarva. I'm the homeworld governor now. I'd love to hear your name."

"Haysi. W-we met…you probably don't r-remember. I ran the Venlil Museum of History, used to ask you for F-Federation grants. Yes…that's right. It's like t-that was someone else."

That did strike a faint recollection from my mind. Noah's breath hitched, belying his concern. Perhaps that was in reaction to her strained voice, which sounded raw from disuse. Her words lacked the warm cadence of the Venlil dialect.

"Haysi, I'm glad that we met again. That person was you, not anybody else," I said. "I'm sure the Museum would love to have you back, when you get better. You're going to get better."

It was touching to see how patient the predators were, with empathy on par with my own. Sara followed my example, untangling Glim's pelt. A wash would do the two Venlil good, allowing them to feel sapient again. The Arxur had stripped these poor souls of their dignity, and a little grooming might return some normalcy.

Noah knelt by Glim's bed, squeezing his paw gently. "What was your old profession, buddy? Maybe we can get you back in the field too."

"D-dangerous…how I got captured," the Venlil stammered. "Colony work, I t-think."

"We're starting our own colonies now. Sent out a few ark ships after, er, never mind. Do you remember the specifics of your work?

"P-preparing untamed areas for habitation. Extermination officer."

The human ambassador jerked back, like Glim had struck him in the chin. Sara paused at the brushing task, and processed the new information. If this individual was someone who killed predators before his capture, there was no reason to think Arxur mistreatment changed his stance. I could imagine Glim's absolute horror, when he realized who he was speaking to.

For a second, I thought both humans were going to abandon the assignment. The two of them would feel uncomfortable, at best, caring for a predator-killer. It would make sense if the Terrans requested a transfer, and found someone more suitable to work with. Noah took several deep breaths, before rising to his full height.

"Extermination officer, huh? That's a controversial profession, these days," the human said.

Glim squinted. "Controversial? W-why?"

"Oh, don't worry about it. We'll fill you in on recent events later, but there's no need to rush your readjustment."

The extermination officer seemed unsatisfied with that answer, but he didn't press Noah further. It was a positive sign to see a spark of interest, however fleeting. Curiosity would give the rescues back their agency. But I could only imagine their reactions, when they discovered our close alliance with predator neighbors.

Predator neighbors who were supposed to be dead. And were written off as warlike monsters.

"Who are you? W-why do you cover your face?" Haysi squeaked. "I don't recognize you."

Sara cleared her throat. "We're, um, Gaians. This mask is a cultural thing, as is the attire. We made first contact with the Venlil Republic four months ago."

"You discovered FTL on your own? Before the Federation found you?"

"Yes. Sort of."

Both Venlil studied the 'Gaians' with confusion. Any intelligent being would notice the pieces weren't adding up. As much as I wanted to welcome the former cattle back to our society, the humans presented a challenge. It was difficult enough for normal Republic citizens to tolerate our unique friends.

I hoped the Terrans could find a way to keep the truth under wraps, for the time being.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 76
Memory transcription subject:

Captain Sovlin,
United Nations Fleet Command

Date [standardized human time]:
November 28, 2136

The human fleet maintained their positions, while the Mazic homeworld sat in a precarious spot. Our hail was still transmitting, though the enemy hadn't picked up. An evacuation transport soared out of the atmosphere, scrambling civilians to safety. The Kolshians nailed the spacecraft with plasma, and aimed it just right to take it out of commission. It seemed that they weren't trying to decimate it, after all.

Captain Monahan's nostrils flared with agitation. "Federation coalition, you fire on civilian targets again, and our ceasefire is over. We will not tolerate such actions."

A violet Kolshian blinked onto a holoscreen. "You're not going to sacrifice the Mazics, for victory and glory? Are you actually clever enough not to show your heartless side?"

"I question who the heartless ones are, when you're the ones threatening a civilian populace. I couldn't care less about victory; we're here to save lives. That's what humans stand for."

The enemy commander paced back and forth, unfazed by the visual of a predator. His crew was a homogenous blend of Kolshians, rather than including aliens. The emerald surface of Khoa was visible in their viewport, along with three target locks on the sensor readout. If I didn't know better, I would think the Commonwealth officer didn't know what to do.

He waved a tentacle. "Damn it. We never wanted to kill them; we wanted to kill you. This fight wasn't supposed to happen like this."

"Tell me something I haven't heard before," Samantha grumbled beside me.

Tyler glowered at her. "Silence!"

Luckily, my guard's quip wasn't picked up on the call; one wrong word could end in catastrophe for the civilians. I was relieved to hear the Kolshians didn't want to initiate the bombing. At least there was some morality among their ranks, however low the bar was. The Terran captain took the incendiary statement in stride, and curved her lips down.

"Well, why don't you fight us then? What is it that you want?" Monahan demanded.

The Kolshian's eyes bulged. "We want you to stop gaining power, predators. Nikonus is right; you show no restraint in your wars. Your aggression is the Krakotl's, a hundredfold."

"And your solution to this perception is untampered aggression of your own? I guarantee, if you bomb Khoa, you're going to give more species reasons to leave the Federation. You can't undo millions of deaths. That blood will be on your conscience forever."

"Then back off. You won't; you're too proud."

"I can't do that. Especially given your history of changing species, irreversibly."

"So which city should I bomb first, predator? I hear Tlinio has a high industrial capacity...shame it's a bustling civilian hub too."

The predator captain had her hands behind her back, but I could see her nails digging into her palm. That indignation was something I shared, hearing such callous threats against the planet. It reminded me of the Arxur's disregard for civilians; the Kolshians might've studied hunters a bit too much. Bartering with lives was dishonorable.

Monahan bared her teeth, and slanted her eyebrows. "That's your prerogative. But when humanity reaches Aafa—and we will, we'll glass one Kolshian city for every bomb you drop here. Blood for blood. Should we start with the School of the Flora, or do you have a substitute in mind?"

"You—"

"Shut up. If you surrender now, we'll treat your lot under our rules of warfare; as prisoners with fair treatment. Trust me, because of those unrestrained wars you saw, you want us to apply the Geneva Conventions. It's going to be a bad day for you if we decide those are no longer applicable."

I recalled my lawyer's explanation, regarding the UN's prohibition of torture. I was curious what other crimes and devices the Earthlings banished in those agreements. It was a safe bet that contraptions humans thought too depraved for use, were beyond the realms of our nightmares. All predators were prone to unfathomable cruelty; that was why I'd been able to torture Marcel with such viciousness.

Humans are capable of everything the Arxur have done. They choose not to...but nobody wants to see them go fully unhinged.

Fear flashed in the Kolshian commander's golden eyes. The intensity in Monahan's hungry gaze brought extra weight to her threat; it was like staring into the countenance of death. That unyielding scowl was an assertion of dominance, whether done consciously or not. I found it difficult to shrug off her animosity, though it wasn't directed at me.

"I'd r-rather die than see any of my men surrender to you. As for Aafa, you wouldn't flaunt your cruelty while masquerading for the prey," the Kolshian hissed.

Monahan bobbed her shoulders. "You're confused. Either we're aggressive predators that can't control ourselves, or we do show restraint. Pick one."

"I...you're twisting my words! Alien freak."

"I have no time for petty insults. What is an acceptable way to get you far, far away from this system? That's what we all want."

The Commonwealth officer sported a stricken expression. Hatred sparkled in his eyes, and he stole a glance back at his bridge crew. No captain wanted to watch their subordinates die. I always felt responsible when my plans went awry, and casualties ensued; decisions traced back to the commander.

The Kolshian saw in the underlings' faces, how much they longed to escape from the predators. The prospect of being hunted by humans terrified them; Terrans were too methodical to outwit. The Arxur could get sloppy due to their food aspirations, but the primates treated war like a mathematical equation. They sought the simplest solution to render the enemy dead.

"Let 1500 of our ships leave, and don't attempt to pursue them. A few hundred of us will stay behind," the enemy leader decided. "You so much as scan us, I will order Khoa bombed with the remainder."

Monahan straightened. "A smart decision. You don't want to lose so many ships, with all the souls aboard. The UN will allow you to flee; that's acceptable to my parameters."

Onso scoured the viewport, as ship activity picked up around the planet. The Terran fleet opened avenues for enemy departures, and made no efforts to engage them. The more hostiles we cleared out of the area, the lower the maximum casualties were. This was a step in the right direction, as far as I was concerned.

The Yotul shook his head. "Should I prepare for pursuit? We can't just let those bastards leave."

"I'll wait for the captain's orders, but I imagine we'll honor our word. It sets a good precedent, to be able to negotiate," Tyler answered.

Carlos shot a glance at Sam. "I know what you're thinking, but it would be nice to have options on the table. Maybe they'll even start letting us surrender, giving us sapient rights."

The female human snorted. "Dream on. They like us better dead."

"Sometimes, I think the Federation likes us better dead too. But the truth is, they don't care about us at all," Onso spat. "Did you know they offered to destroy our railroads and steamboats?"

My eyes narrowed, at the uplift's distortion of events. The Federation weren't my favorite faction anymore, but clearing out obsolete technology was helpful. I didn't understand why the humans were giving him sympathetic looks. Disgust crossed Tyler's expression, and Carlos wrinkled his nose as well.

I chewed at my claws. "Well, you don't need them anymore. You're stuck in the past, Onso. No reason to keep relics around."

Onso curled his lip. "That's what they said! They called it a celebration, as they demolished our shipyards. Maybe we still like the things we built."

"But the Federation's tech is better. Is this about pride?"

"Pride is not seeking your own identity. Fuck you!"

Carlos swatted my neck. "Erasing someone's culture and beliefs is a form of genocide. I'd think you of all people would understand that, Sovlin."

Tyler glared at me, before storming off to comfort Onso. The mention of my name was enough to make his blood boil; the wedge between us hadn't been dealt with. My wrongdoing wasn't his fault, and it had never been my intent to disrupt his work. When the current crisis was resolved, I owed the tall human an apology.

The fleeing Kolshians had put some distance between themselves and Khoa, while rushing to escape the FTL-disruptors' range. I imagined they were looking over their shoulder for pursuing predators. None of them eased up on the accelerator, since being the herd's straggler was a death sentence. But the humans resisted the urge to chase; they rarely succumbed to hunter desires.

Terrans can conduct themselves like normal people, despite their deficits. It never ceases to impress me.

"It's beautiful, isn't it?" Captain Monahan turned her back to the camera, gazing at the stars. "We never had to fight. We could work to make something better."

"Quit it with your lies. Counting colonies, 34 worlds have been wiped out since we met you. And you've been here for four months," the Kolshian muttered.

"We didn't start, or even bomb, any of those. It's not our fault everyone keeps attacking us, and abandoning your defenses."

"You're in kahoots with the Arxur...pulling the strings even. You wouldn't attract them if you weren't rotten to the core. Humans enjoy killing, for all your empathy."

"I enjoy stopping bad people from hurting others. Nobody else has to die today. Certainly not innocent hostages, because you hate us. On our honor, we'll let you all leave unharmed."

The Kolshian shifted with discomfort; it was clear he mistrusted the human's proposition. Several of the ships he left behind were making a break for it, without waiting for orders. Flighty captains weren't going to give the predators time to change their mind. It left a sour taste in my mouth, to see the enemy getting away.

"On your honor?" The Kolshian flailed with exasperation. "What good does that do me? Predators deceive."

Monahan snorted. "So do 'prey'...look at you. I haven't lied to you once, nor has the human race. Please, think of the Mazics."

"I...I'm not a murderer. I don't want to kill children...herbivores. Shit, your trick is working. We'll leave."

The video feed switched off before the human could respond. The Kolshian ships glided away from Khoa's vulnerable surface, maintaining their formation. The Terran fleet honored the non-aggression pact, rather than confronting the enemy. The predators were here to save their allies, first and foremost.

The human crew offered a rousing applause for Captain Monahan, which took the aliens by surprise. I was accustomed to the predators' noise level, after living around them for months. Bringing a Terran nearby was a fast way to dismantle peace and quiet.

The poor Fissan on comms bucked in agitation, and the Venlil observers covered their sensitive ears. Onso delighted in the ruckus, however, with his primitive sensibilities. The Yotul began yipping and jumping around, like an animal. Monahan allowed the cacophony for a moment, before shouting orders to pipe down. Silence overtook the bridge in an instant.

The Terran captain sighed. "Let's not pat ourselves on the back yet. This was a good day for us, but I promise, the Mazics won't look back as fondly. Comms, hail Khoa."

The beige mammal on screen answered with immediacy. His eyes were frantic, as though he'd fallen over himself to respond. Upon closer inspection, I recognized the older male as President Cupo. The Mazic leader seemed alarmed to be at the predator fleet's mercy. Their defenses were laid bare, and the poor guy was frazzled from the assault too.

"Greetings," Monahan said politely. "Do you require any aid? We're happy to assist with search and rescue. There's a civilian hauler immobilized in orbit, for starters."

Cupo flared his trunk. "N-no, thank you. We can handle it. What payment can I offer you, humans? We'll give you whatever you want."

"Payment? We don't want anything from you. Humanity came to your aid because we're allies. You're part of our 'pack' now, as I imagine you would put it."

The Mazic was silent for a long time. Something resembling regret flickered in his gaze, though it was gone a second later. The leader composed himself, and turned back to the camera. He appeared isolated, in a vast bunker with only a single aide.

"I never trusted humanity. I wasn't willing to risk my people to help Earth," Cupo said. "Even with Cilany's revelation, I only committed resources to your team because I saw the Federation was a sinking ship. Now, you protected us, and I am...sorry. Please, let us repay your aid."

The Terran captain chuckled. "All is forgiven, President Cupo. Your choices were relatively tame, compared to the genocidal maniacs in the Federation."

"Oh human, I stood beside those people for years. It was wonderful, all herbivores working together, in perfect harmony. How did nobody see the truth? I should have."

"Don't blame yourself. We all see what we want to see. Just like people read evil into us, and cherry-pick our worst moments. Because that's what they're looking for."

"You've had to grovel and scrape for every friend you have, human, but not anymore. The Mazic Presidium will never forget your heroism. I'll set aside my best scientists to support your colonization efforts, and you can have the pick of our abandoned worlds. Unless you mind being so close to us."

"Not one bit. The United Nations would love to cooperate going forward."

My ears swiveled away from the dialogue, and I padded away from the sensors station. Pronounced footsteps followed at once, and a shadow fell over my form. Without looking, I knew it was Tyler lurking behind me; he was stalking me with predatory intent. Fear pulsated through my ribcage, and my spines bristled to the point of discomfort.

Swallowing, I ambled into the mess hall and swiveled around. The sensors officer's chiseled jawline was rigid, suggesting the human wanted to bite me. His teeth were ill-suited for that, but the subconscious tell was there. Those blue eyes glittered like ice, scorching into my vulnerable areas.

I cleared my throat. "Sir, I'm sorry for my initial behavior. I panicked when you said Slanek, and I didn't want to disrupt—"

A fist rammed into my snout, before I could flinch. Tyler's punch carried phenomenal power, as his calcified bones connected with my skin. I caressed my bleeding nostrils, and the human snaked an elbow around my neck. His knee lurched up into my stomach, knocking out the breath.

I doubled over, but the predator's grip kept me from collapsing. Pain overwhelmed my senses, and my conscious mind relished it. Control was slipping away, however, as instinctive panic suppressed my faculties. It took the last of my lucidity to refrain from swiping back.

Tyler tightened his hold on my neck, before hurling me into a cabinet. I slammed against the upholstery, crumpling in a ball. The human marched ahead with effortless strides, and hovered over me. My heart was on the brink of bursting, seeing his malicious snarl.

"This is what it feels like to be physically beaten, and powerless to fight back. You did that to Marcel for a week!" the Terran officer spat.

"I...know..." I coughed out the blood that trickled into my mouth. "I h-hate...myself for it. Only...didn't k-kill myself...so h-humans could have justice."

The predator watched me crawl on the floor, before extending a rough hand. I accepted his paw, allowing him to pull me to my feet. Rather than resuming the slugfest, Tyler helped me to a chair. He retrieved a paper towel from the sink, and pressed it to my nose.

The primate stepped back. "You want to die?"

"Sure, but I'm a c-coward." Tears swelled in my eyes, and rolled down in rivulets. "Turns out I'm terrible at getting myself killed, and...at picking out the monsters who hurt my family. It w-wasn't Marcel, but any predator sufficed."

"Shit man. Did you ever get treatment for PTSD? What you went through was pretty fucked up. You should've never been in a commanding position to begin with."

"T-treatment for what? That didn't translate."

"...I see. You should talk to a therapist; I know a good one. It's what Marcel would want."

Tyler decided our spat was finished, and left me to nurse my wounds. Was mental treatment what Marcel would really want for me? My thoughts harkened back to my cell on Earth, and the red-haired human mocking my inability to cope. I was beginning to believe that he realized self-contempt was the worst punishment. Didn't he want me to live with this misery, until death's sweet release?

But Tyler knows him personally. If he says Marcel would want to help me...

With Khoa's rescue, I saw that humans stood for the preservation of life. Perhaps that extended to someone like myself, despite my past. It terrified me to explore my predator side; losing my identity had been devastating. How could anyone grapple with their entire life being a lie?

There was one certainty, one absolute truth, in my universe now. It was that humans were the only ones that could stitch this galaxy back together.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 78
Memory transcription subject:

Slanek,
Venlil Space Corps

Date [standardized human time]:
November 29, 2136

The extermination office featured a modest array of cubicles, past the lobby. There were more employment opportunities than hunting predators. Call centers had to be operational around the clock, and another set of pencil-pushers checked web reports. Other workers researched infestations, identifying potential culprits and their method of survival. These briefings prepared the officers for a job's challenges.

The humans peered around the entrance, before a brave few slid into a cubicle. No gunfire was unleashed at our appearance, so the rest of us took positions. Marcel produced a pocket-sized drone, and the device silently soared into the air. It glided over rows of cubicles, searching for any heat signatures.

The miniature robot stopped near a window, and zoomed in on two Tilfish. The predators crept forward, with the same silence their ancestors used to hunt creatures twice their size. Dino mimicked their focus, as its handler whispered something to it. The dog seated itself, and I took my opportunity to distance myself. The gun felt light as a feather in my grip; it stayed pointed right at the hiding spot.

Marcel poked his gun over the cubicle wall, and his comrades also shoved scopes at the Tilfish. Their mandibles clicked with terror, surprised by the primates' stealth. They bent their heads in a gesture of submission. Large predators shouldn't be able to approach without audible cues, yet humans could suppress their footsteps so well.

"Please don't shoot us!" an insectoid clicked. "We're just IT workers...we surrender!"

Marcel jerked his gun skyward. "Stand up. Walk toward the window."

The Tilfish scuttled back, though their compound eyes lingered on the predators. My human shouted demands to turn around, but the enemy hesitated to comply. Something was odd about their posture, and I couldn't chalk it up to fear. Their appendages seemed folded to conceal an object.

Marcel approached to search the workers; his hazel eyes were narrowed to slits. The Tilfish's thoraxes twitched, poised to strike out. Without any consideration, I lunged at one of them. The insect I tackled bucked under my grip, and kicked its cohort in the process. I clung on for dear life, reaching for whatever was in its clutches.

The humans noticed the downed one was wielding a gun; that "IT worker" was scrambling to right himself. Multiple bullets incised the hostile's exoskeleton, before he could enact his plans. Marcel pointed his firearm at the one I was riding, but he couldn't get a clean shot. The Tilfish had latched on to my forepaw, which prevented me from dismounting.

I screeched, as the Tilfish slammed me against the wall. Adrenaline surged through my veins like a drug. My free arm shot toward his lens-like eyes, and I sank tiny claws into the smooth flesh. He howled in pain, loosening his grip on my other paw. My body crashed to the floor with a thud, knocking the wind from my lungs.

The predators pumped the Tilfish full of lead, before he could try anything else. Some blood splattered onto my fur, painting yellow splotches across my chest. Every muscle in my body quivered, as horror washed over me. I crawled back toward the humans, and struggled to my feet. Several primates helped wipe the blood off, checking me for injuries.

"Slanek, for the love of God, why did you not shoot those Tilfish?" Marcel grunted.

I straightened my head fur. "W-well. I saw them reaching for a weapon."

"I understand that. My question stands."

"I...don't know. L-let's get moving."

Terran soldiers swept the room, verifying that other Tilfish hadn't stowed away. We progressed to an interior stairwell, which led to the upper floor. The armory was tucked by the landing, but it had been emptied of guns and flamethrowers. The exterminators found a use for every weapon in their possession.

I hugged the wall alongside Marcel, using his presence to ground me. Every instinct suggested to hyperventilate, and dwell on the bloodshed I'd kickstarted. But giving into those thoughts wouldn't facilitate my survival; it would hinder the UN's mission too. These Tilfish needed to die, because they were a threat to Earth. There was nothing else to consider.

These rebels were the strongest advocates for joining that genocidal raid, I imagine. They're responsible for billions dead.

The predators were hesitant to climb the stairwell. There had been dozens of life signatures in this building, so the bulk were waiting on the top floor. Per the tactics UN training drilled into me, this was a chokepoint. It was advantageous to defenders, and forced assailants to cover multiple angles. Grenades weren't a viable option, with their tendency to roll back on us.

"Is there another way up?" I whispered.

Marcel shrugged. "We could just blow this place to kingdom come, but the brass doesn't want collateral. There's no telling if there's hostages 'til we sweep the premises."

"I'm surprised you didn't suggest dropping out of the sky. That is the human way, as I recall."

"Intel suggests this faction has surface-to-air capabilities. Attaining a ladder is possible, but the roof is likely booby-trapped anyways. These fellas seem to want us to come to them."

"Why?"

"I don't know. They're basically a cult, and they're cornered. They could be planning to take us down with them."

My human turned his gun skyward, and inched back-first toward the stairs. He popped off several shots from a sharp angle, which connected with one Tilfish. Judging by the alarmed chatter, there were six or seven defenders perched above us. The insects leaned over the railing, and rained fire on the redhead.

Tension crossed Marcel's scarred face, as he ducked back under the alcove. The humans waited for the enemy to deplete ammunition, knowing they weren't conservative in its usage. My friend peeked back out, and was joined by a pair of comrades. The trio offered suppressive fire, as the Terran troops hustled up the stairs.

I swallowed my nerves, which reminded me what an easy target I was. If these humans could bear the risk, so could I; this was about trusting their plan. My feet sprinted up two stairs at a time, and I joined our squad mid-way up. We had a better line of sight from this angle, which allowed us to bombard the Tilfish.

One human dropped beside me, and another released a strained yelp. This charge was a strategical blunder, but it was the lesser evil of our options. We were hoping to scale the incline as quickly as possible. Though I was too frazzled to aim, I got off several blind shots. Whether or not my bullets contributed, the exterminators were gunned down in seconds.

Panting heavily, I labored up the rest of the stairs. The predators tended to our wounded, lugging both to the top. One's binocular eyes were glassy, suggesting they were already gone. My eyes shot back to Marcel, who was the first to engage the Tilfish. Relief clamped at my heart, when I saw him hobbling up behind me. His brazenness could've gotten him killed!

Marcel tested the door. "Easy now. We're going to sustain losses, Slanek. We can't let that distract us...we all know the risks."

"I didn't say anything?" I squeaked.

"You didn't have to. You wear your emotions all over your face."

I rubbed my temples, trying to fight off a nagging headache. Dino bounded up the stairs, and began sniffing at my legs. The dog's presence was the last straw, in a situation that was stressful already. Why couldn't the damn beast leave me alone? Wasn't it enough that I was in imminent danger from bullets?

The humans departed the stairwell onto the second floor, and a slew of gunfire welcomed them. I bolted away from Dino; getting shot was preferrable to his creepy drooling. This appeared to be some sort of break room, with lounge stools, tables, and a mini-kitchen in the area. The Tilfish had condensed the lounge chairs into fortifications, and upturned tables for cover too.

Our position was a barren bottleneck, which was by design. Glass shattered to my left, as the window was nailed by errant bullets. Shards glinted on the floor, and reflected the sunlight pouring in. I suddenly wished I had goofy paw coverings, like the humans. My feet weren't fleshy like theirs, but pads wouldn't stop me from impaling myself.

Guess the only place to hide is by the cabinets to my right. Already lots of humans cramming in there though; need somewhere less crowded.

Keeping as far away from the broken window as possible, I scampered across to the opposite end of the room. Bullets whizzed past my head, and took out several humans who tailed me. A handful of us reached the other side, where an arch opened up into a parallel corridor. Further down, there were a set of doors marked with a "Biohazard" symbol. I assumed that was where prey remains, and predator experimentation were housed.

Bootsteps closed in on my position, rough and unsteady. Marcel dived through the archway, flashing his teeth at me. He huddled against the wall, and predator chemicals caused his eyes to dilate. The vegetarian sucked in several breaths, while Tilfish gunfire peppered the plaster around us. I risked a brief glance at my paw pads, which seemed clear of glass.

UN soldiers retreated to the stairwell, as bullets decimated their position. My side advance was secure against a support wall, for now, but the firefight had ground to an impasse. The Tilfish exterminators needed to be flushed from their shelter, before we incurred more losses.

I propped my gun up against my chest. "Those bastards think they can hunker down. What about grenades now?"

"I thought you'd never ask," the Terran chuckled.

Several soldiers readied grenades, calculating the perfect moment to strike. Human predation was methodical, a far cry from mindless chasing. Their discipline kept their units functioning as well-oiled machines. If I was opposing them, efficiency would be more frightening than an animalistic frenzy. Terrans were much less likely to make mistakes than the Arxur.

I was grateful to be on their team. If first contact had gone differently, the Venlil would have been the first ones fighting them. We would've never had the exchange program, which meant I'd still see humans as monsters. What fate would befall Earth, had Sovlin gotten his mitts on the Odyssey astronauts? My friend would be dead too, and...I might've helped kill him.

I shook my head, not wanting to think about dreadful causalities. The predators clattered explosives across the floor, which arrived at the Tilfish fortifications. Marcel wouldn't let me carry grenades, since my throwing ability was negligible. Human arm torsion was effortless, in contrast; hunting with spears forced their ancestors to evolve precision.

Enemy screams followed the grenades, as the detonations tore any shelter apart. This time, I understood that humans would capitalize on the chaos. My legs propelled me back into the room, forsaking the corridor's refuge. A few Tilfish retained their guns, but most hostiles languished on the floor. Buttery blood washed across the tile, with spatter reaching up onto the walls.

The Terrans strode up to the barricades; Dino darted into the heart of the action as well. The dog subdued any Tilfish who were rising, while the humans' picked off writhing targets. UN soldiers admired the heap of bug corpses, poking a few to ensure they were dead. Our ranks sustained some damage in the fray, but we got the better end of the bargain.

Marcel shuffled into the corridor. "So, that door we saw. I've learned the Federation warning symbols, and the last thing we need is them springing some 'cure' on us. Are they testing bioweapons here?"

"Highly unlikely. Consider where we are. It's marked biohazard because of predator contamination. You are predator contamination, lots of it, so I doubt you care."

"You never know, Slanek. Contact with some animal's saliva might turn me into a superpredator, with claws and horns."

"I'd be more worried about that with Dino than you. You ready to end this?"

The redhead nodded. I mulled over how their teasing behavior had rubbed off on me; sarcasm had never featured in my lexicon so regularly. It did seem like a healthy way of expressing stress, especially in extreme situations. Bantering with my predator distracted me from the nauseating fear.

Upon closer inspection, the biohazard door was left ajar. Marcel nudged it with his foot, eliciting a mournful creak. The human made gagging noises, and tugged his shirt over his nose. I wasn't sure what his reaction pertained to, given my lack of smell. Was the air laced with some poison?

"Bleh! That acrid smell..." Marcel coughed.

My gaze darted to the floor, and the source of his discomfort revealed itself. A thin coating of brownish liquid amassed, like a wading pool. The gasoline was discernible upon entry, even with blinders on. Did the exterminators think humans would trample through a blaze zone? Most sapients avoided burning alive where possible.

I swished my tail with disgust. "Petrol. There must be a few Tilfish camped inside, waiting to set it off."

"I don't have time for this. Playing timberwood's not on my agenda." The human's teeth protruded with malevolence, as he acquired a match. "How about a little role reversal? Surprise, fuckers!"

After lighting the object in his hand, Marcel dropped the spark into the gasoline rim. Orange fire snaked across the liquid, and leapt onto any secondary fuel: walls, furniture, and Tilfish alike. My human turned his back on the inferno, and strolled back to the stairwell. While the exterminators achieved their self-immolation plan, we needed to double-time it out of here.

The UN troops jogged past the break room's body trail, and skipped down the stairwell. Their longer legs allowed them to retrace their steps quickly. I lagged behind them a bit, but my friend circled back for me. Marcel scooped me up in strong arms, ignoring his own exhaustion. The human was a good herdmate; he always looked out for my welfare.

I know he'd never leave me behind, come stampede or high water.

It was a quick journey, cuddling against his muscular form. We hustled past the cubicles and the lobby, before bursting into fresh air. The blaze had gained intensity, as it battered the upper windows. I spotted Tilfish silhouettes thrashing about, enveloped by smoke and debris. Perhaps it was unwise that the professionals made their workshop flammable by design.

"Guard each exit," Marcel barked. "Those exterminators'll either burn alive, or they'll try to evacuate. Unless they come out surrendering, shoot any you see."

Dino's quadrupedal form was visible among our ranks. The dog strayed from its handler, and opted to harass me again. In a rare moment of bravery, I shoved its snout away. It offered a pitiful whine, before curling up at my feet nonetheless. Its brown eyes never left me, as it thumped its tail a single time.

Why wouldn't it leave me alone? It was for Marcel's sake that I didn't chase it off with my gun. I hated that mutt, just as much as the humans adored it. Once we cleared the neighborhoods of rogue patrols, this mission would be complete. I couldn't wait to achieve victory, so I could get myself far away from the feral predator.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 79
Memory transcription subject:

Governor Tarva of the Venlil Republic
Venlil Republic

Date [standardized human time]:
November 29, 2136

Venlil resources were spread thin, with millions of rescues taxing our resources. Volunteers worked to exhaustion, and human refugees chipped in as much as anyone. The predators' assistance was appreciated, but we had to monitor their interactions with the former cattle. I was certain they didn't mean any harm. However, the primates often didn't realize how terrifying their basic mannerisms could be.

All it took was one Terran reacting with aggression, or lifting their mask at the wrong time. If their secret got out within this facility, I could imagine how the rescues would take the news. Would a former exterminator like Glim accept that our closest ally was a predator race? Could Haysi grasp the Federation's misdeeds, after studying our idyllic relations in history?

Hey, just so you know, one of every ten races are flesh-eaters, I imagined myself saying. Oh, and our neighbors are predators; we're allied in their war against the Federation. With the Arxur too.

This was a delicate situation, regardless of outside intervention. A large chunk of these Venlil were raised in captivity, and lacked any understanding of our modern society. Their language and higher thinking functions were rudimentary at best. The Arxur hadn't exposed them to other aliens, or offered any welfare services.

"Governor? It's your move," Sara said.

Haysi was laying on her stomach, inspecting the "Jenga" tower. The former historian had come out of her shell; it was good to see her taking an interest in the Terrans' culture. Noah and Sara kept their answers vague, which failed to sate her curiosity. The humans brought this block game with them today, and used it as an introduction to their recreation.

My claw tapped a loose piece near the center, and I coaxed it out of its spot. The tower quivered a bit, which sparked my nerves. The Venlil rescues leaned in with interest, alertness in their eyes. Satisfied that the structure would hold, I set the plank atop it.

Noah rubbed his hands together. "Wonderfully done. My turn!"

"Dear stars!" Glim flinched back, and shot the human a wary glance. "H-how did your voice go that deep, Noah?"

"Uh, I have a bit of a cough," the ambassador muttered, clearing his throat. "Making it very throaty; I apologize."

Noah avoided turning toward Glim, which would indicate binocular vision. The predator's emotions were invisible under his mask, but the Venlil exterminator's confusion was apparent. Male humans' speech had a growling texture, which added weight to their voices. This was in stark contrast to our squeaky pitch.

The UN ambassador jabbed his hand forward with no tact, and yanked a piece from the bottom. The Jenga tower toppled over, crashing to the floor. I suspected Noah had lost the game on purpose, to distract Glim. The astronaut excused himself, and sped out of the room. He realized how close he was to blowing his cover.

Glim tilted his head. "You Gaians are a strange species, Sara. Noah did not seem sick to me, this entire time."

"Ah, Noah tries to play tough. I bet he's doctored himself up on cough syrup," the Terran scientist responded.

"Something about you bothers me. It might just be that I can't read you. If you aren't comfortable taking your masks off, I'd like to at least see an anatomical diagram of your species."

"I'll look into acquiring that for you."

"Will you?"

"That tone. What are you implying, Glim?"

The male Venlil pinned his ears back, and swished his tail with irritation. I feared that he'd already guessed the "Gaians" were predators. However, the fact that he was irked, rather than afraid, suggested he might not have the answers yet. The former exterminator's attitude was worsening by the day though.

It's positive that his spirit hasn't been crushed, but he's becoming a problem. Maybe he needs to be isolated from humans.

"I heard from my family for the first time in years, yet you're limiting contact to pre-recorded messages. You won't let us watch TV for entertainment, or have access to the internet," Glim growled. "You avoid every question we ask you. There's something you don't want us to know."

Sara raised her hands. "That's not fair—"

"This isn't fair! I'm still in captivity in my home, here with my own people. Dodgy aliens seem to be running the show. You won't even let us go outside to get a breath of fresh air!"

Haysi was listening in silence. "Sara. T-the museum. I w-want to…visit."

Alarm coursed through my veins, as I knew we couldn't honor their requests. Humans appeared in every form of media, including fiction, and were a popular subject on our internet. Outside of these walls, Glim and Haysi would encounter Terran refugees. Millions of them remained on Venlil Prime, so they could be walking around unmasked anywhere.

Sara adjusted her facial garb. "I'm sorry if you feel that our restrictions are unfair. We have no idea what your timetable is to readjust, and we'd like to take things slowly. Better safe than sorry."

"Sensory overload might awaken negative emotions, and slow down your recovery. Discussion of the war is everywhere too," I chimed in. "Maybe you two recover faster than others, but several of your counterparts are shattered. Our goals are set with the average Venlil in mind."

Haysi narrowed her eyes. "H-how did you even free us anyways, Tarva? W-why would the…grays let us go?"

"The Gaians negotiated your release."

"What could the Gaians have that t-the Arxur would want?"

"Strength," Noah's voice rumbled behind me. "Resources."

Glim's pupils snapped back to the doorway. Noah returned with a bowl of fruit, and made a point of grabbing a piece. He raised his full-face mask just enough to eat the food, though his canines were still obscured. The two Venlil studied his furless chin, and his snack choice. The exterminator seemed to relax a little.

Consuming plants should halt predator suspicions, for now. The Terran ambassador offered the fruit to the Venlil, who snagged a few pieces for themselves. He waved a berry-picking hand, and ushered the rescues back to their room. It was a clear attempt to avoid further questions; we had to find a way to give them some of what they wanted.

Haysi hugged Sara, as the scientist tucked her into bed. The female predator patted the Venlil gently, returning the affectionate gesture. The historian had no clue who her caretaker was; compassion was a trait we once reserved for prey. Until we met humans, we assumed predators were incapable of empathy.

Glim shied away, when Noah tried to adjust his blanket. The exterminator's skeptical look had intensified, following the ambassador's answer about the Arxur. Strength the grays would respect was something to be feared, and not a quality prey should possess. Likewise, the only resources that interested the Dominion was food.

"What d-did you mean by strength and resources?" the male rescue stuttered.

Noah withdrew to the doorway. "We defend ourselves, and we're proactive about it. We can find a scientific solution to anything…manufacture anything, even the unsavory stuff the Arxur want."

"The Arxur w-want cattle…to eat…and killing tools."

"We did what was needed, to get you back. We're going to protect the Venlil from now on."

Haysi whined. "You c-can't protect us from them. Nobody can. Y-you're naïve."

Noah shoved his hands into his pockets, but pride exuded from his posture. There was a hunter's grace in his stride; the way he strutted, arching his spine, asserted dominance. Even with the mask on, I could sense his vicious snarl. The human wouldn't stand for Earth's prowess being called into question.

"Oh Haysi, we already beat the Arxur once. The Federation's only victory, in hundreds of years, was because of us," Noah stated. "Have some faith."

Sara shook her head, slashing her hand in front of her throat. I scurried up to him, and tugged at his wrist. My beloved needed to adjust his behavior, because that speech wasn't prey-like at all. Usually, Noah was more sensitive to our sensibilities. Perhaps it was Glim's profession, goading him into boastfulness?

I dragged the human down the hallway, out of earshot of the rescues. Noah allowed himself to be maneuvered; there was no way I could move him, without his cooperation. After checking my periphery, to see if either Venlil followed us, I took a deep breath. It was important that I used a hushed voice, to avoid prying ears.

"Why would you tell them that?" I hissed. "Your species found FTL months ago, and now you're telling them you singlehandedly defeated the Arxur. How will they conclude that primitives did that?"

Sara crossed her arms. "Tarva is right. These Venlil aren't ready for the facts. Remember what sort of reactions we get, from normal people? The exchange programs? Aafa?"

Noah sighed, throwing his hands in the air. "Maybe we should get the truth over with, instead of dodging their questions and locking them up. Glim was an exterminator. Any deceit will make him double down on his pre-existing beliefs."

"Hold your horses. I know they're going to find out eventually, but they've been here two days. You'd be compromising the identity of all of our people."

"Glim and Haysi are strong-willed. We could break it to them, in pieces. They deserve to know who Venlil Prime's closest ally really is."

"And w-who is that?" a voice squeaked behind us. "Who…are you r-really?"

The Terrans swiveled around to face Haysi, an instinctive reaction. Their uncanny tendency, to look right at a target, tipped off the historian. It was the sign of narrow vision, to snap around a full ninety degrees. I could see fear flash in her eyes. She had realized the truth, or at least part of it.

Haysi backed away, tail drooping between her legs. Sara raised her hands, and took a careful step forward. The female Venlil shrieked, before bolting down the hallway. I could hear her nails scrabbling on the tile, as she slipped in haste to get away. The sounds of crying were audible too, amidst the screams.

The poor thing just realized she hugged a predator. Oh dear.

I positioned myself in Noah's path, stopping him from following. "Don't chase her! You're just going to make it worse."

The ambassador cursed. "What do we do? We can't just sit around. She's going to start a panic!"

"I'll notify the Venlil doctors, and get someone to calm her down. We should check on Glim now. He must've heard the commotion."

"Yeah, Haysi wasn't exactly subtle," Sara said. "Come on, Noah. We don't need both our patients freaking out."

The humans raced back into the hospital room. Sara gasped with horror, and Noah's breathing accelerated to a panicked pace. Catching up to the primates, I saw that both beds were empty. Haysi was obviously long gone, so our goal was to minimize the damage. Glim was nowhere to be found either, though.

The Terran astronauts started scouring the room, since we hadn't seen the exterminator exit. They crawled on the floor, searching under the beds first. Under different circumstances, it would've been amusing to see a human wriggle under tight spaces. But at the moment, my sole thought was locating our Venlil charges.

My gaze landed on the walls and the ceiling, browsing for any clues. A food cart had been moved right under an air duct; the grate was pried open too. A clump of gray hair floated down onto my face, and I shouted for the humans' attention. Glim must've used this passage to mount an escape.

Sara whistled. "Dang, we got a little Houdini here. If he wasn't an exterminator, I'd be impressed."

The predators couldn't fit into the crawl space, and I wasn't planning to go in there myself. We must operate under the assumption that Glim fled the premises. There was no telling where he would go, and family were his only known associates. Perhaps we should start with relatives' residences, or extermination offices.

"We have to find Glim. He's a danger to himself, and any human he comes across," I said. "The world has changed since he's been gone."

Noah ripped his mask off. "This is a fucking disaster. It wasn't supposed to go like this!"

"Let's keep our heads. What's done is done," Sara offered. "Tarva, do you want us to call in a UN manhunt?"

"Manhunt? I thought you d-didn't hunt sapients."

"It's an expression. For a search party, to capture a deviant."

"I s-see. If you think it will bring him in safely, do it. I c-can ask the public for help too."

Noah sighed. "That's a good idea. We'll do what we can. I'm sorry."

The two predators wandered off to make calls, while I fiddled with my holopad. The hospital lockdown should have been tighter, but I never intended to imprison these people. They were supposed to be eased back into the citizenry, and learn the truth gradually.

Human volunteers had signed on to give each rescue proper care, rather than to complicate matters. Perhaps their involvement was unwise, but we couldn't handle the cattle influx alone. It seemed like a good idea, to give the predators a worthy cause. Most Terran refugees wanted something noble to occupy their day.

The predators needed to track Glim and Haysi down, and bring them around to our side. Hopefully, in time, both Venlil would understand the humans were here to help.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 84
Memory transcription subject:

Chief Hunter Isif,
Arxur Dominion Sector Fleet

Date [standardized human time]:
November 30, 2136

My shuttle descended on our spy station, piloted by automatic landing functions. This was the same clandestine facility that Secretary-General Meier approached prior to Earth's attack. Perhaps the Dominion should've relocated the outpost, but the brass scoffed at the notion that any prey would dare to strike it. I knew that the Terrans wouldn't hesitate to hit us where it hurt, though, should we ever clash.

Stations like this one were essential to sectorwide command and intelligence. The rig had its own state-of-the-art FTL comms network, which had been painstakingly routed back to Wriss. The relay functioned across hundreds of light-years, by leeching off Federation infrastructure as well. I was careful not to tip my claw when I communicated with the humans; I trusted them to watch their own self-interest foremost.

The Federation don't bother establishing costly networks, because it's the first thing we wipe out. I don't need to give the humans vulnerable targets.

The shuttle dropped onto a landing pedestal; I wasted no time disembarking. Ceremonial armor clung to my form, and a decorative sword had been placed in a scabbard. It was time to act out Isif the fanatic. Some low-ranking grunt had refused her Gojid rations, and then ejected the food out an airlock. The Dominion wished to make an example of her.

Guards bared their teeth as I strutted into a central holding area. The prisoner was dangling from wrist-restraints, bleeding from several gashes. It could be my head on a pike, just as easily; there was reason I treaded with such care. Those ungrateful humans, who reclaimed the very worlds they told us to attack, were making me regret my risks for them. Earth wasn't bargaining from a position of strength.

"Your death will be swift and decisive." I shoved my snout into the inmate's face, and stared right into her pupils. The Arxur guards watched with amusement. "Live like prey, and die like prey."

I scanned my form into the virtual interface, and watched as several holograms popped up around me. Chief Hunter Shaza was a welcome attendee, since I needed to stop her from reclaiming Sillis the orbital way. There were plentiful examples of conquest in human history; however, the UN's lack of slavery and brutality led me to conclude this was different. Terran mercy had gone haywire at the worst time.

The Prophet-Descendant of the Betterment Office, Giznel, was presiding over the trial. I'd branded myself as one of the true believers, and earned his favor among chief hunters. There was a reason I was assigned to the juiciest sector, with weak targets like Venlil and Zurulians. The question was if he suspected my treasonous intent, with how fervently I defended Earth. Human carelessness was jeopardizing my zealous persona.

"Chief Hunter Isif! Raise your condemnation for your empire," Giznel stated. "Begin when you are ready."

My pupils scanned the battered prisoner. "What is our birthright, hallowed Prophet? Arxur stand atop the food chain, and the animals populating other worlds exist to suit our whims. The accused mocks our very existence."

There was no option to show mercy to her. Betterment has eyes and ears everywhere. They'd question me not seeking the death penalty.

"She, whose name has been revoked for treason, disgraces this military. Food is a precious commodity, due to the Federation's butchery of our cattle," I continued. "What right does a lowly underling have to dispose of food in an airlock? Food which could've fed a worthy mouth!"

I narrowed my eyes, slapping my tail across her snout. Hardened gray skin was pierced by my scales, which added to her array of marks. The Arxur restrained her yelps, as she knew such weakness would lessen slim hopes of Betterment sparing her. Not that there was any chance the Prophet-Descendant would forgive a capital offense.

Giznel yawned in boredom. "The punishment you seek, meritorious Isif?"

"Death! None who oppose the Arxur shall stand," I snarled. "I wish to strike this thief down with my own claws, here and now."

"Very well. I concur with the Chief Hunter's assessment. Accused, any last words for your honor?"

The prisoner released a wet cough. "The Gojids are people...true sapients. They ate meat like us. How can you still treat them as cattle?"

"I'll defer that question to you, Isif," the Prophet-Descendant chuckled.

Sapient consumption was a requisite for our survival; I'd come to terms with that years ago. Sure, the Gojid jerky I'd eaten with my crew hadn't gone down as easily, with the thought of Nulia calling me Siffy. Food that didn't emit playful giggles, and wasn't capable of higher reasoning was preferable. Still, there was nothing I could do about our current practices. My actions saved a lot more prey than one sliced-and-diced Gojid.

My tail lashed in faux irritation. "The entire ideal of Betterment is that the strong cull the weak. The prey are still prey based on their actions; how they snivel, and piss themselves over any challenge. These are not the behaviors of true sapients! Even if they once were cogent, that bears no relevance on today."

"Well said. Go ahead; split that traitor's throat," Giznel said.

I stalked around the prisoner, arching the ridges on my spine. Fear glistened in her eyes, which caused my adrenaline to hum. It felt good to be in control, and to have a release for my pent-up aggression. Of course, I didn't really want to complete this execution, but my primal side liked it.

The humans and the Venlil would label me a monster, if they witnessed me strike a prisoner down in cold blood. They didn't understand the confines of my system. The chatty Terrans had entire rituals with lawyers, and testimonies that could drag on for weeks. Here, Betterment's determination was the difference between innocence and guilt; made without a word edgewise.

Chief Hunter Shaza curled her lip. "I don't see any blood. What are you waiting for?"

"Can a man not savor his kill anymore? I was hoping she'd beg," I growled coldly.

My claws slashed across the soft flesh, and scarlet blood spurted between my digits. The Arxur prisoner sagged in her restraints, with gurgling noises escaping her maw. Fluid frothed up to her teeth, and her eyes lolled. The truth was, this wasn't the first, the tenth, or even the hundredth person I'd killed in the name of survival. It got easier every time; the sympathy I felt became muted.

As a cruelty-deficient individual, I learned to fake dominant traits from a young age. A televised execution was when I realized that most people didn't wince at screaming cattle, or cry when their family members died. That voice was always there, no matter how much logic I employed. Watching the humans glamorize kind acts, I wondered what Arxur society was like when empathy abounded.

Maybe it could've been the Venlil buddying up to us. Though, ones like Slanek are too emotional for even my liking.

"They die too quickly." I turned to face the holograms, waving my bloodstained claws. "Shaza, I bring word from the humans."

The female Chief Hunter grinned. "How can you be so right about the Gojids being weak, yet you fail to apply that to the humans?"

"Humans are not sniveling prey. They are destructive and prideful, to their own detriment at times. Don't let their pudgy appearance fool you. They bested us in combat, unlike any other race."

"Their prey-like interactions with each other sicken me."

"You are mistaking prey-like for social. Empathy is not a defect in pack predators, though humans must learn to temper such tendencies. Still, they are apex predators on their world."

Giznel narrowed his eyes. "Humans understand cruelty and aggression. They need the same push Betterment gave us."

The Terrans had figures much like our Laznel in their history; I'd done research on a holopad I found in New York's wreckage. Every herbivore alien questioned how such a leader could rise, but the primates already knew that answer. Their modern populace feared that becoming a reality again. Presently, humanity demonized 'predatory' attitudes; they detested an equivalent to the Northwest Bloc resurfacing.

Imposing Betterment on the Terrans was an awful idea, but I wasn't going to voice that opinion. Perhaps in the future, Earth would take in defective Arxur as refugees. The Dominion sentenced anyone lesser to death, so they might be amenable to lending 'slaves' to Earth. It wasn't like Wriss had a use for condemned weaklings.

Would humanity even want my people on their world? Some UN personnel looked at us like we were diseased animals. Secretary-General Meier wouldn't have taken much convincing, but alien goals weren't on Zhao's agenda. Every action had to lend a direct benefit to Earth, or advance their war efforts. I yearned for the original leader and his calming ideology.

Chief Hunter Shaza scowled. "This human message better be good, Isif. Why did they claim two territories under Arxur siege?"

"The United Nations sees conquest as a way to obtain the entire planet as our catch," I responded. "They believe in maximizing resources, and are willing to negotiate a deal. Human interference was meant as aid."

"Aid? Terran commanders messaged my ships, demanding that we back off. Their claim of Sillis, then Fahl, was a bold-faced attempt to swipe our prize!"

"I agree with Shaza. Humans are proving ungrateful, despite how Isif saved their Earth." Giznel's fangs protruded with disdain. "We attacked these worlds to enact their vengeance, while their own military floundered. We shouldn't negotiate for what is ours already."

"Of course, Your Savageness. Humanity were tactless," I agreed hastily. "Going orbital on their army seems unwise though. Predators must stay united, until the Federation is eradicated."

Shaza snorted. "Ah, yes. The Federation that humanity is pulling their alliance members from?"

"Pets. Not allies. If you're tricked by lies tailored for prey..."

The female Arxur stiffened with indignation, and her holographic tail blurred with motion. The Prophet-Descendant scrutinized us both closely, spending an extra second on me. Perhaps I'd painted myself too much in Earth's camp. A proper Chief Hunter should want to bash the humans' nose in; humility wouldn't be the worst thing to teach them, regardless.

"I want Fahl and Sillis in our control, by the end of the week. I don't care how you do it, Shaza. You and Isif settle that part among yourselves," Giznel decided.

Shaza's eyes gleamed with triumph. "Yes, Great One. As you wish."

"It will be settled. I am fully committed to our glory," I managed.

The Chief Hunter tossed her head in gloating, as Giznel left the holopad call. The prisoner body sat at my feet throughout this exchange, which I hope bolstered my tough exterior. Shaza had near-full autonomy over her sector, except for the rare case of Betterment's direct orders. People of our rank merely filed reports, and had thousands of ships to do their bidding.

Human generals were chained by comparison, with more oversight and rules to adhere to. I understood what they meant by war crimes now, though I couldn't believe my eyes. What value was artwork in the middle of combat?! Why wouldn't an army take out medics that were limiting enemy casualties? It was a miracle that Zhao hadn't elected to shed this softness.

But I suppose their docility was why I believed they could pioneer a better future. Perhaps I could take another crack at the United Nations, or persuade Shaza of their value to our cause. Pride was important to an Arxur's culture, especially given how concessions would be framed. The long-term value of social allies needed to be put in a way a brute could understand.

"Hear me out, Shaza. I will explain to you why tolerating humans benefits our cause, despite their irritating emotions," I growled. "Every good hunter should have the facts before drafting a plan."

The Chief Hunter swished her tail. "I've had enough talking for today. There's only so much social blabbering one can take."

"Of course, this discourse has dragged on too long. My patience is also tested," I lied. "Opposing opinions are grating, and solitude would be welcome. Just one more thing."

"What is it?"

"We need to have this conversation, in person. Your attack may be detrimental to the Dominion's long-term success. Allow me to present the military pros and cons, at a location of your choice. The decision will be yours."

Shaza presented her fangs in a warning gesture, though the details were grainy in the hologram. I responded by dropping into a hunting crouch; cowing before a threat was admitting defeat. The humans were the only way I saw the war ending, and leaving us with a non-sapient meat supply. As idiotic as the leaf-lickers could be, I couldn't allow our tensions to escalate.

"I respect an elderly...I mean, veteran general enough to entertain your speech." A snicker shook her sides. "Stop by the cloaked farm habitat just inside my sector; it's a day's travel from your post. You can have a tour of a modern operation."

"Age means surviving combat and nature's assassination attempts. If you're lucky, it will come to you as well," I replied.

"Enough of your platitudes. Will you travel to the farm or not?"

"Yes. I'll be there."

Chief Hunter Shaza terminated the call, and I stormed back to my shuttle. Tolerating her condescending attitude, and groveling on the humans' behalf wasn't a thrilling prospect. I couldn't even wash the death from my body. Cleaning the blood off my claws would suggest that I wasn't proud of my kill.

A day of warp travel would allow me to process options, and play out various scenarios in my mind. Why couldn't the humans just let two species who assaulted them perish? It would be much easier for all parties involved.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 94
Memory transcription subject:

Chief Hunter Isif,
Arxur Dominion Sector Fleet

Date [standardized human time]:
December 4, 2136

The empathy tests were an assortment of prey species facing torment. For the first time since childhood, I leaned into my defective voice. It was painful to allow myself to feel fully, without casing those primal sensations in a shell of logic. Witnessing unnecessary suffering elicited a shameful amount of pity, just as it had back at Shaza’s farm. Now, more than ever, I knew herbivores were not just spineless animals.

The look on Secretary-General Zhao’s face, as his scientists explained my results, was vindicating. The human leader did honor his agreement with Tarva, permitting me to board her ship. I was surprised the Venlil leader wanted me confined with her for hours; from what I could tell, she carried no firearms. Shouldn’t a prey individual expect me to snap on a whim, and thus not want me seated across from her?

I rested in a brooding state, mostly keeping to the co-pilot’s seat in the cockpit. Governor Tarva sensed my sour mood, and allowed us to travel in silence. It made for an awkward ride, with the rescued Zurulians in the cabin behind us. The Venlil possessed more patience than myself, coaxing the quadrupeds to indulge in basic self-care. Her constant reassurance and crooning tone grated on my nerves, whenever she ventured back to their locale.

“Thank the Prophet we’re almost to Venlil Prime.” My pupils snapped toward Tarva, as she returned to the cockpit once more. “How the fuck did the humans survive all these exchange programs?”

The governor shot me a disapproving look. “Have some sympathy. Those three were literally just captured and brought to a farm, where your lovely comrades threatened to eat them.”

“I do have sympathy. I didn’t want them to be eaten, did I?”

“Never mind, Isif. You can have this ship when we get to my homeworld. If my people saw me riding with you…”

“I appreciate your assistance, Governor Tarva. I too considered Elias Meier a friend and an ally. Even with his intervention, the fact that you would listen to an Arxur is not lost on me.”

The Venlil was silent for a long moment, and her ears pinned back with a meek emotion. Her limbs weren’t quivering, so I wasn’t inclined to label it fear. Though it was tough to read prey cues, my best guess was that it was grief. Sadness swirled in her irises, before she looked at me with something bordering contempt.

Tarva cleared her throat. “I know you have done…have presided over horrible things, Isif. Genocides, raids, and systematic slaughtering. Your motivation to avoid your own execution doesn’t change that.”

“You are right. I see why my statements about not assigning responsibility can be perceived as callous. Please, do not take my detachment as a sign that I do not regret my culpability.”

“Didn’t you order the raid on the cradle? The Gojids are an endangered species because of you.”

“Someone else would’ve done it if not me, yes? But it was me, and at the time…I believed coexistence was not possible. My beliefs have since shifted.”

Governor Tarva was silent, scowling at the viewport. The Gojid cradle was intended to be like any other raid; with their border defenses down, it made a frontal assault tantalizing. I hadn’t known why the defenses were offline until later, when reports from the planet’s surface circled back to me. Another predator race taking on the Federation…it was too good to be true!

We’d be alone for so long. I was certain it would be disproved, I mused. Then, humanity took the cradle back from us. The sheer guts! The audacity!

The Terrans bested us fair and square, allegedly using Venlil ships in their arsenal. It baffled me that they worked hand-in-hand with prey, but that led to my deduction of humanity’s social nature. Intrigued by these specific aliens, I aimed to learn more about them. A new predator opened up avenues with their presence; it meant someone else wasn’t indoctrinated by the Federation’s spiel.

Looking back at the Gojid cradle through Tarva’s lens, I realized how differently humans viewed our first meeting. Planetary raids instilled very little guilt after all these years; it was something I deigned not to dwell on. What would Nulia think, if she learned “Siffy” was behind the “bad monsters’” arrival? How many children like her had I doomed to cattle farms?

One of the last things Elias Meier did was convince the Mazics to aid the Gojid refugees. From what I’d heard, the Zurulians and the Paltans took in a handful as well. The spiky herbivores had limited numbers now, and Earth was in no place to be offering asylum. The United Nations had lifted their protection of Gojid colonies, which led many survivors to flee.

“The Gojids were a sad case, Tarva. I did give those orders; I’m not dodging responsibility. I understand that my past actions have been hurtful,” I offered.

“You don’t know hurtful. You took my daughter.” The Venlil leader’s voice quavered, and she shoved me with shocking aggression. “YOU TOOK MY DAUGHTER! It was you. You ordered the grays to gas Venlil s-schools: what, to crush our morale?!”

“I…I am sorry. I had no idea that you were personally affected by our raids, and you do not deserve that. Whether I directly ordered this instance or not, the Arxur who did it reported to me. They were under my command. I took no actions against routine attacks, certainly nothing to draw suspicion.”

“It was just ‘routine’, huh? I fucking know you feel empathy, and you could’ve done things differently. Why did you have to be so cruel?!”

“I will not disrespect you by making excuses for myself. If there was any way I could undo the past, I would, Tarva. But I cannot. Your hatred and inability to forgive me, it is understandable.”

The Venlil governor swiped at the tears in her eyes, and I felt a strange urge to place my tail on her shoulder. My logical brain reminded me I was the last person she’d want comfort from. Most species loved their children, referencing their loss as the greatest pain imaginable; that was why the Dominion learned to target the youth. Perhaps if my nurturing instincts had been cultivated better, I could understand.

Tarva cleared her throat. “I am willing to work with you, but I will never forgive you. I cannot forget what you’ve done.”

“Your animosity is justified. My only atonement is to pave a better future, so that this will not happen again,” I hissed. “That is my sincere hope…I will do everything in my power to protect Venlilkind.”

“You must’ve had a difficult life, Isif. To never be allowed to express your emotions, forced to fit in with despicable people. You deserve a friend. I just cannot be that friend, even if Elias would’ve wanted me to.”

“Silly leaf-licker. No prey will befriend me. The Zurulian mishap proved that, yes?”

“In real life, sure. It would be best if they didn’t know who you are. You can talk anonymously on the internet though. General Jones gave me this holopad over here, said you’d ‘want it back.’”

“Seriously Tarva? You think that holopad is meant to join…some Federation chatroom? I have nothing in common with you people!”

“That’s just my advice. I think it would be good for you to understand us ‘hunting-challenged’ races better. To express your empathetic side, and not to be alone.”

I offered a dramatic huff, and turned away from Tarva to reinforce my disdain. My paws did snatch the holopad, though I was suspicious that General Jones may have tampered with it. The Terran officer had returned my standard-issue device as well; I inspected it closely. Whatever purposes I used these electronics for, I should be certain I was okay with humans viewing them.

Governor Tarva was attempting to be empathetic, but her suggestion was lunacy. What good would it be to get attached to a prey alien, when I might have to kill and butcher their kind later? What had relaxing my guard around Nulia accomplished? All discourse with the herbivores resulted in was guilt.

***

Hours later, alone on the ship with my thoughts, I set course for my spy station. Governor Tarva bade me farewell, after supplying me with meat rations from the local factories. Knowing the Venlil’s anti-carnivore values, the generosity of that offering couldn’t be understated. I wondered if this was the start to building a bridge of trust. We would never be friends, but partnership wasn’t out of the question.

That was all a moot point, if I didn’t return to commanding my sector. Arxur were solitary creatures, who cared little for others’ welfare. However, if I didn’t check in soon, the Dominion would start asking questions for practical reasons. I needed to drum up an explanation for why I’d lost my own vessel, and returned in a Venlil transport.

Perhaps the humans’ tooth drive could help you. Why haven’t you given it more than a cursory glance?

Instead of crafting my story, I was learning how to navigate through the Federation internet. Passing close to our FTL backdoor with Mileau, the Dossur homeworld, I’d been able to establish a connection. As small rodents, the Dossur weren’t at the top of our meal list; they were the “least valuable” species in my sector. Their territory bordered Gojid space, but on the opposite side from the Zurulians.

“Stupid Tarva,” I growled aloud. “Putting stupid ideas in my defective brain. How did she know that I wanted that?!”

The Dossur had a social media site called SwiftPair, which would randomly assign anonymous users to chat. The rodents had few abilities beyond jabbering to each other, so of course they’d devise such a platform. Then again, humans had a propensity to run their mouths about nonsense too. That was just how desperate social creatures were for belonging.

My traitorous claw hovered over the “Pair” button, and I cursed myself. Perhaps I should just let Tarva’s recommendation backfire, so I could move on. Honestly, what harm could a single chat do? I could always intimidate the little critter away if they became a nuisance.

I clicked the button, and the algorithm found a chat partner in a half-second. The public profile classified this Dossur as a mid-twenties female located on a space station.

Hi, I typed hesitantly.

How’s it going? Please tell me you’re not just on here to flirt, came the instant reply. I swear, it’s like this became a dating app overnight.

What? I don’t know why I’m here, but it’s certainly not for that.

Good, ‘cause I will block you if you’re lying. So I’m Felra, and I’m a spaceship inspector. Catching every slapstick, half-assed repair job the human alliance throws at us.

You work with humans?

Not directly. We just let their allies marshal some forces at the old Fed spots. The UN is talking about an exchange program, but we’re the smallest species in the galaxy. Problematic.

There was a pause, before the Dossur typed another message. What’s your name?

Nerves crept into my throat. Not only did I have little clue how to sustain conversation with an herbivore, but my real name was infamous. Word must’ve gotten around about the sector’s Chief Hunter, after my broadcast on Earth. It wasn’t like I could tell Felra that I was an Arxur; it would stop her little heart, assuming she believed me.

Siffy, I decided.

That’s adorable! You must get that a lot, but props to your parents.

I do not wish to discuss my parents.

Sorry, I didn’t mean to offend you. What do you do for a living, Siffy?

“I bomb planets, execute people for empathy, and farm sapients,” I quipped aloud.

This and that, was the actual reply I sent her. Nothing you’d be interested in.

Felra typed back hastily. You don’t talk about much, do you? You’re prickly as a Gojid.

I’m not…used to talking. This was a mistake…I deserve to be alone.

This was a waste of time; I reprimanded myself for indulging these urges. There was no telling how the humans were faring at Sillis, and I needed to check back in with the Dominion fleet soon. Rather than making preparations, I was chatting with a creature that resembled an Earth ‘mouse.’ Had the loneliness really been this crippling for all these years?

A banner popped up on the app, indicating that Felra sent a friend request. I had no clue what was going through that Dossur’s tiny brain, but she must’ve been meaning to block me. As I prepared to fire up my Arxur communicator, I made out the rodent’s next message. It read, “No one deserves to be alone.”

Snorting in amusement, I accepted the request before dipping offline. General Jones should’ve kept this Terran holopad, so I wouldn’t get sidetracked on preylike pastimes. The human officer knew I was defective, and didn’t take precautions to suppress these tendencies. Wasn’t that what she meant about getting myself killed?

There was no guarantee Felra would respond to future messages, but I wasn’t going to squander more time. With my direct course for the spy habitat, the Arxur Dominion required notification of my vehicle change. I entered my credentials, before pinging my headquarters. The day-long absence made it likely I’d be in contact with the brass, rather than my underlings.

It was time to put on the façade for our government, and resume my role as Isif the fanatic.

Prophet-Descendant Giznel accepted my video call. “Is there a reason you’ve been avoiding your check-ins, Isif? For a less-faithful hunter, I would have you executed.”

“Your Savageness, I take it you know that I visited Earth. Shaza is a fool, and your wise decree was for us to settle the dispute,” I explained. “The humans may have seen the wisdom of standing down…yet alas, I was too late to accomplish that.”

“You disappeared for a full day. I doubt both your conviction and your loyalty, Isif. You are not willing to kill the humans, are you?”

“That’s absurd! I am gathering intelligence on Earth, in case we need to fight the leaf-licking apes. I don’t care about humans. I want Betterment imposed on the galaxy, at any cost. Hallowed Prophet, they can learn to drink from the river of cruelty! You knew this yourself!”

It was unclear whether Giznel believed my argument, but he had opted not to kill me on sight. The Prophet-Descendant could be convinced of diplomacy’s usefulness; as long as I was strengthening our cause, I was safe. The alarming part was his overt accusation that I was a human conspirator. Betterment had been partial to me for years, and this development meant I couldn’t hide behind favoritism.

The Arxur leader narrowed his eyes. “That is not your ship you’re streaming from, either. Is that…”

“Yes, I made off with prey technology. The humans found tactical advantages commandeering Venlil ships,” I growled. “I will dissect the design, because those grass-brains aren’t worthy of killing us. If war is inevitable, the Dominion will be ready.”

“We pay Venlil technology the respect of studying it now?”

“I want our glory, Savage One. Our victory must be resounding, and prove our superiority.”

“You are straying from the path, Isif. But you were right about humans being formidable foes.”

“Is that so? Nobody agreed with me before. I have missed something from Sillis and Fahl, yes?”

Giznel scrutinized me for another second, before swiping at his holopad. The compilation contained distress signals from across Shaza’s sector, which were sent through our FTL networks. Farm habitats forwarded footage of humans raiding our facilities, and undefended stations being reduced to rubble. The Terrans severed our comms infrastructure shortly after these transmissions.

The UN could’ve cut the proverbial wire earlier. They want the Arxur government…and Shaza to see this.

Laughter rumbled in my chest, as I realized the UN’s true strategy. The humans used the occupied worlds as bait, and Chief Hunter Shaza played into their hands. That foolish Arxur was so eager to teach the “weaklings” a lesson, that she hadn’t guarded her most valuable possessions. Every strategic asset and supply depot across hundreds of light-years was erased.

“This amuses you?” Giznel hissed.

I bared my teeth. “Shaza’s incompetence brings me nothing but joy. Does she know yet?”

“Word is reaching her around the same time as us. She will be made aware soon, but I have to deal with her mess now.”

“Ah, don’t bail her out! This was her great master plan, after all. I know how to handle humans, and I need your trust going forward.”

“You can hardly fuck up worse. I’ll humor your weird ideology, Isif, but I’m watching you.”

The Prophet-Descendant terminated the call, and left me to chew on his words. My first conversation as an official human spy, and I already had Giznel sniffing around my business. This was going to require me to operate more carefully; the freedom I’d enjoyed in the past had waned. General Jones was right to warn me about eyes and ears everywhere.

My gaze drifted to the Terran holopad, which sat in the cockpit. Browsing alien internets was perilous too, unless I could find a suitable cover. With my actions under a microscope, talking with a Dossur inspector was a fool’s errand. Felra shouldn’t occupy my thoughts, since I’d only be able to sneak sporadic messages at best.

How long could I hide my Arxur identity from her? What if I have more in common with prey than my kind?

I shook my head. The future of the galaxy was at stake; this was no time for emotional baggage. It took a weight off my shoulders, to know that the humans punched back from Sillis. A straight-up fight had been inadvisable, but Shaza’s arrogance was her undoing. I would pay a pretty penny to see the look on her face, when she discovered her empire had collapsed.

My goal was to ensure that humanity’s war remained with a single warlord. However, keeping Betterment off their backs might prove to be a challenge.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 97
Memory transcription subject:

Captain Sovlin,
United Nations Fleet Command

Date [standardized human time]:
December 5, 2136

Sitting behind the helm of a ship felt cathartic, after my long absence from the captain’s chair. Tyler volunteered as my copilot, while Onso lounged in the backseat. The Yotul seemed too casual for our current suicide mission. Even with the UN’s distraction, there was a chance the Arxur would come after us on our descent.

Dominion forces were concentrated around Sillis’ supercontinent, since circumplanetary targeting was not an option. While the unique geography narrowed the staging points available, it also condensed settlements into a single region. That meant less bombs were needed to cover the planet. Our plan was to slip the shuttle in on the ocean side, as the Terrans hounded the grays head-on. I wondered how our original defensive line, which had vanished into the atmosphere, would factor in.

Perhaps they can cover our ass during atmospheric re-entry. That’s if they’re not involved with the rescues themselves.

Those vessels would be the easiest ones to sneak down to the surface, given that they didn’t have an Arxur buffer in the way. Getting back up to orbit would be a challenge though, and the grays watched for evacuation ships. Small patrollers weren’t built to tote more than a handful of passengers regardless. Outside help was required to rescue entire platoons.

Tyler blinked his icy eyes. “Take us in, Sovlin. Godspeed.”

“You think predators would build guns into evacuation shuttles,” I grumbled. “Might be helpful for your trigger-happy pal to shoot anything that moves.”

“In most events that we’re using these, it’s a dire emergency and we’re abandoning ship. These aren’t average transports.”

Onso narrowed his eyes. “But why can’t we abandon ship with guns?”

“I don’t build these things! Are we going to sit here and argue about this all day?”

This was no time for playful banter; action was picking up on the viewport. The Terran fleet moseyed in with purposeful movements, and ensured that the Arxur spotted their advance. Dominion vessels rushed out to meet the numerically inferior armada, leaving the ocean side open. I increased our acceleration, and broke out of our low-emissions glide. Until now, our shuttle had been taking a quiet course to flank the enemy.

It was impossible to tell which ship was commandeered by Captain Monahan. Carlos and Samantha were in over their heads alone on sensors, but I trusted our replacements to pick up the slack. The worst Terran crew member was probably more fit for service than the average herbivore. Humans were nothing if not competent in combat. We just needed this distraction to work as planned, to reaffirm that very idea to the grays.

The Terran armada dispensed a few explosives to attract attention. The grays took the bait, once their unsophisticated brains zeroed in on the UN’s aggression. Backing down from a duel signaled weakness; the humans and the Arxur were both obsessed with not appearing infirm. Pride was a shared trait between the two predator species, and seemingly, our primitive Yotul. I was unconvinced Onso wouldn’t run off and get us killed the second we landed.

My eyes darted to our data feed. “It seems our side is getting their snouts bashed in. I hope this is worth it.”

In close-range combat, the UN was unequipped for a confrontation without resorting to tricks. The humans’ front line was getting picked off several at a time, evidenced by the explosions in the viewport. I wasn’t sure how much time they could buy us, so I kicked our speed up another notch. No Arxur had come to intercept our shuttle, and we had breached Sillis’ high orbit already. My heart was hammering in my throat all the same.

Perhaps my fear was for the crew we’d abandoned. Our minimal numbers couldn’t resist an Arxur charge; there were less than a thousand vessels in the shadow fleet. The Dominion had six times that ship count at hand, and were using most assets at their disposal. Following their humiliation across the sector, this was personal. Rare instances of teamwork sprouted, with the grays ganging up on wounded Terran craft.

We need more numbers. Surely the UN defensive line is coming any second, right?

Blips blinked onto my radar, as friendly contacts emerged from Sillis’ orb on cue. The Arxur had learned that humans practiced ambush tactics, and their rear flank was ready for the sneak attack. The enemy vessels swiveled around on a dime, unleashing munitions with prejudice. The resurfacing Terrans lobbed explosives back, desperate to stem the tide. The grays’ onslaught was unrelenting, with minimal attention given to any inbound missiles.

“Pick up the pace!” Tyler barked. “I imagine we’re pulling all ships back at any moment.”

I sighed in exasperation. “I’m going as fast as I can. Do you want the ship to break apart on descent?”

Onso bared his teeth. “Is it better to get gunned down up here? As the humans say, no guts, no glory!”

“There is no glory in being scattered across Sillis’ orbit! What is wrong with you?”

“Yeah, I think we need to wean you off Earth sayings, buddy. You interpret them all with the utmost aggression,” the blond predator muttered.

“I’ll try again. Ahh, a predator! Its eyes are forward facing…and it f-flashed its teeth!” The Yotul utilized a high-pitched voice, and faked an occasional stutter. “It’s an evil abomination and needs to d-die! That better, Tyler?”

“You’re too much.”

The primitive was distracting me from my approach, so I shut his antics out from my mind. The shuttle obeyed my commands, its slender frame humming softly. I offered a final bit of juice to the engines, and they answered with a hearty push. This would be a tricky entry, but there was no option to follow safety guidelines. If the Arxur circled over to us, we would be easy pickings.

Marcel and Slanek’s survival relied on us getting through to the planet. I’d rather take a riskier path, and know I’d done everything in my power to save them. Everyone onboard this shuttle was willing to gamble with our fates, for our comrades’ good. The thought of the duo in an Arxur farm made my blood simmer; it was an unacceptable outcome. Both of them had suffered enough at my paws.

The shuttle blazed toward Sillis’ azure surface, and I leaned forward with concentration. The shadow fleet was pulling back, while the UN defensive outfit covered for them behind enemy lines. Those re-emerged friendlies followed suit shortly after, dipping back into the Tilfish world’s atmosphere. A few grays gave chase, not wanting to let the Terrans slip under the radar again.

“Two Arxur cruisers changing course, and targeting us for interception,” Tyler growled.

I gritted my teeth. “They won’t catch us. They won’t try to follow this descent.”

My claws smacked the throttle lever, and pushed us well past recommended output. We hurtled toward Sillis at a breakneck pace, while the Arxur clocked in at sensible speeds. Their vector lessened the distance between us, but it wasn’t closing the gap fast enough. The planet ahead was enlarging much quicker, and our trajectory scraped the edge of the atmosphere.

Humans built for durability, so I had to trust that emergency shuttles could take a beating. Actively accelerating into a descent was madness, and even Tyler looked nauseous. The shuttle frame quivered from the stress, sending jolts through my body. Controls offered erratic responses, and I warred with the steering column. Alarms blared from the main systems, warning us of excessive heat.

The temperature climbed on the interior accordingly, as hull shielding failed to contain the environmental effects. Incineration was an agonizing way to die; an undercurrent of fear ebbed through my veins. I cobbled myself together enough to check our sensors. The Arxur contacts were pulling back, and our track on them was spotty. That meant they were losing us as well.

I hurled all power into reverse thrusters, and corrected our descent angle. The harness dug into my shoulders, as it restrained me during the sudden shift. Tyler’s face had gone ashen, and he squeezed his eyes shut. The massive predator was not enjoying the turbulent ride. The shuttle’s velocity slowed, though not before our hull had taken a beating.

“I’ve got it under control,” I gasped out. “Going to bring us in low and fly to the stated coordinates.”

Tyler groaned. “You unstable, neurotic Gojid! You were about two seconds from getting us cooked.”

“No guts, no glory. Sovlin’s an honorary Yotul after that stunt!” Onso yipped.

Don’t insult me like that, I thought to myself. I grew up with electricity.

I leveled out the shuttle’s flight course, once we neared the choppy water. The waves were a blur at our speed, zooming by as I gunned it toward our location. It was dizzying to look at our surroundings, but the human was gawking all the same. It was rare to fly with such quickness in-atmosphere, due to civilian traffic and hazards.

“You don’t realize how fast supersonic flight is in space.” Tyler pressed his hand to his chin, and turned his eyes toward me. “Here, you can tell what our velocity is. You see the world zooming by.”

I drummed my claws on the console. “There’s no time to waste. I’m just keeping enough altitude to clear any buildings. Marcel’s coordinates are inland a bit.”

“You did great, Sovlin. But hey…I’m still not sure it’s a good idea for you to make an appearance.”

“Marcel visited me in jail. I hope my presence will not be an undue burden on him. I will comply with whatever his wishes are.”

Our shuttle cleared wide patches of ocean, and another yawn crossed Tyler’s face. The sensors officer hadn’t slept since the battle commenced; I suspected the big predator craved a distraction. He could chat anyone’s ear off, if he got started on a topic he liked. Perhaps he’d be interested in jawing about his family? The shoreline would be visible within a minute, so he just needed to stay awake a little longer.

I cleared my throat. “What’s something you did as a child that you cherish, Tyler?”

“Right on. Me and my pops used to go out to the lake, rent a boat,” the human reminisced. “We’d sit out there for hours and shoot the wind. You know, enjoy nature. Our relationship’s become…estranged, but I miss fishing with him. We caught some real beauts.”

“Your FAVORITE childhood pastime is water hunting?! Your father took his kid to do this?”

“Hey, chill out! It’s not like we ate any. We just caught ‘em on a hook, took a picture, and threw ‘em back.”

“That…then what was the point of catching them?! Just when I stop thinking of you as predators, you say shit like that! You torment fish for father-son bonding time.”

Onso suppressed a growl. “I rarely cry ‘predator’, but that is twisted and unnatural. It would be fine if you were seeking food, but you are just doing it for kicks.”

“It’s just a way to relax, man. And maybe some humans do like hunting; so what? It’s not like we’re killing them.”

Disgust swelled in my chest, hearing the predator discuss hunting as “relaxing” entertainment. I could picture the blond beast on a boat, giggling as he toyed with a suffocating fish. To think that a father passed those behaviors to his son! How could an empathetic species consider that a socially acceptable pastime? How did Tyler not see how fucked up that hobby was?

I brooded for the rest of the journey, scowling out the windshield. Buildings blurred beneath us, alongside charred ruins and mushroom clouds. There was no telling if Marcel’s corner of Sillis was intact. That human, who I knew was vegetarian, would surely recognize the ethical flaws in his packmate’s sadism. I hadn’t thought Officer Cardona was a vicious animal before now.

Tyler tapped my shoulder as we landed. “Shit, I’m sorry. I know that’s a sensitive subject for you guys. I was just thinking about the one time my dad was proud of me, and it was that.”

“W-well, that’s fucked. Your father instilled heinousness in you. P-parents have a responsibility to teach their kids good values,” I managed.

“Right. We cool?”

“Yeah. Let’s go kill some Arxur.”

I couldn’t look at the primate the same, thinking of him learning predation. Humans claimed that they didn’t hunt in the modern day; Noah said their meat was grown in labs. Clearly, that wasn’t the whole truth, if Tyler had no qualms about his family outings. How could any feeling person go along with that?

Tyler admits Terrans are violent and bloodthirsty. Sometimes, those base instincts must be given higher consideration than their empathy.

Humans policed themselves with moral laws; progress was still needed on the specifics. When hunting was ingrained in their ancestry, it made sense that remnants persisted into the civilized era. The predators just needed an introduction to proper values. I was certain well-meaning brutes like Tyler could learn that animals weren’t playthings.

I parked the shuttle on a sidewalk, in close proximity to Marcel’s coordinates. With the Arxur traipsing about, this was no time to relapse into human phobia. Onso snapped his gun up and clambered out into the open. I checked my surroundings, before raising my own weapon. There was nothing around us besides the faint glow of dawn’s sunlight.

“Marcel, do you read me?” Tyler croaked into his radio. “It’s me, Tyler. Your better half. We’ve landed, but I don’t have a visual on you.”

The pavement was rough beneath my hindlegs, and the air felt acrid in my throat. I steered a wide path around Tilfish bodies in the street, as did the human. Terrans were averse to death on the Gojid cattle ship, but this was a different response. Tyler had a case of the shakes, rather than wanting to puke. His binocular eyes twitched in an odd way; I wondered darkly when his last meal occurred.

Muzzle flashes appeared in our periphery, and I dropped to the ground on instinct. The human herded Onso into a storefront; I scurried over to them on shaking legs. Bullets peppered our refuge, as Arxur enemies rallied to our location. The raiders had established a heavy presence in the city. What if they were looking for Terrans to round up?

The blond human tossed an explosive into the street, and high-pitched growls echoed through the air. Peeking through the broken glass, I saw mutilated grays soaked in blood. Whatever Tyler deployed sent shrapnel in a wide radius, and caught the aggressive beasts off-guard. The surviving enemies circled back to regroup, giving us a breather.

“Marcel, tell us you’re still alive, bro. We’re right on top of you, and there’s no signs of friendly activity. Have you relocated?” Tyler panted.

The Yotul blinked his dilated eyes. “Let’s get back to the ship. I think they’re…”

“Shit Tyler, it’s good to hear your voice.” Gunfire sounded in the background, and audible scratches surfaced from Marcel fumbling his radio. “We’re in the sewers. Need backup ASAP!”

That information gave me the adrenaline boost I needed. I unloaded a magazine at the approaching Arxur posse, in the hopes of pushing them back. Marcel’s packmate jerked his pupils downward, and rushed over to a manhole cover. The predator searched for a lever, finding one with his hands. Tyler tugged at the mechanism, and robotic systems popped the hatch.

Onso growled, as he took down a gray with a well-placed shot. The Yotul protested when Tyler pulled at his shoulders; the primitive was the first to descend into the manhole. The human insisted on being the last one to enter, and hurried me to the ladder next. I hopped down the rungs, jumping into the mucky tunnel.

Tyler dropped onto the ground, landing awkwardly on his ankle. He’d sealed the cover behind him, and I hoped that would delay our attackers. Thankfully, our shuttle could be locked to human biometrics; that should prevent the Arxur from running off with our ride. We didn’t need the same problem I had on the Harchen’s Blissful Modernity.

“My leg is fucked. Double-time it, people,” the tall Terran barked. “Onso, if you ever wanted to charge in…now’s a good time.”

Now that we were in the tunnels, I could detect the same gunfire I’d heard on the radio. My ears assured me the fight was still ongoing, but Slanek had already been wounded before this clash. With Marcel stuck guarding his Venlil buddy, there was no telling if he could best the Arxur. His band was lucky to survive on Sillis this long.

I channeled my inner Onso, dashing off like a madman. This was my opportunity to save the human I’d brutalized, and give some meaning to his decision to spare my life.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯